Preface

India is the only country in the world that has been, since the beginning of time, fully conscious of and faithful to its very lofty spiritual goal. Indian civilization has not only been a great cultural system which has had tremendous achievements in every field of human endeavor and thought, but has been an immense religious effort of the human spirit which has nurtured the Sanatana Dharma, a perfect way to move towards and realise this noble spiritual goal in the fastest and most integral way possible both for the individual and the collectivity.

At present, India seems to be going through a period where every aspect and value of its life seems to be more and more influenced by the Western utilitarian spirit and the following of an alien way. This has created problems, and the current attempts at solving these under the same spirit in an unthinking duplication of the Western ways seem to be a huge mistake. Not by following an alien law, but only by going within, can we find again our true life-giving sources and our forgotten Atma-Shakti. That is why, in the present time, the most important task before India – which being accomplished most of her current problems and difficulties will automatically dissolve – is to become conscious of the profound truth hidden at the root of her great culture, its glorious past and its supreme achievements. To build a greater future, we have to know our great past and making it the basis, move forward.

This book has brought together Sri Aurobindo’s words on Indian culture and Dharma and the Essential Spirit behind it which have then been conscientiously interpreted. The purpose of this interpretation has been to elucidate those profound thoughts of Sri Aurobindo which alone can tell us the profound and true reasons behind the various outer expressions that our culture had used in the past and for the ups and downs it has undergone in this effort of self-expression. It is only by so knowing – and this cannot be done on the surface but only by sympathetically entering into its fundamental spirit – that we can understand the profounder truths hidden behind the outer forms of this culture and their necessity in their own time (when they were in vogue) – something, naturally, beyond the reach of the modern surface materialistic consciousness – and adopt a more balanced and more just attitude in this matter.

The various informal talks and discussions between me and various sadhaks of the Sri Aurobindo Divine Life Ashram while reading our own publication ‘The Greatness of India and Its Culture’(2015) form the basis of this book. Pankaj Bagaria has not only painstakingly transcribed and edited these talks, but has diligently completed the innumerable tasks that go towards publishing such a book. All quotations from Sri Aurobindo and the Mother have been put in quotation marks. The commentary has been put in between (‡ ‡) marks to distinguish it from the original.

We hope that this book, dedicated to the work of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother on this Earth will be such a beacon of light in whose presence many moved by their self-nature and aligning their hearts and minds to it will resolve to dedicate themselves to working for the renaissance of India and its destined role in the world.

– Chandra Prakash

Dedicated to the work of

Sri Aurobindo and the Mother

on this Earth

Excerpts from Sri Aurobindo’s Famous Uttarpara Speech

“I say no longer that nationalism is a creed, a religion, a faith; I say that it is the Sanatana Dharma which for us is nationalism. This Hindu nation was born with the Sanatana Dharma, with it it moves and with it it grows. When the Sanatana Dharma declines, then the nation declines, and if the Sanatana Dharma were capable of perishing, with the Sanatana Dharma it would perish. The Sanatana Dharma, that is nationalism.” (CWSA 8: 12)

“Then He placed the Gita in my hands. His strength entered into me and I was able to do the sadhan of the Gita. I was not only to understand intellectually but to realise what Srikrishna demanded of Arjuna and what He demands of those who aspire to do His work, to be free from repulsion and desire, to do work for Him without the demand for fruit, to renounce self-will and become a passive and faithful instrument in His hands, to have an equal heart for high and low, friend and opponent, success and failure, yet not to do His work negligently. I realised what the Hindu religion meant. We speak often of the Hindu religion, of the Sanatana Dharma, but few of us really know what that religion is. Other religions are preponderatingly religions of faith and profession, but the Sanatana Dharma is life itself; it is a thing that has not so much to be believed as lived. This is the dharma that for the salvation of humanity was cherished in the seclusion of this peninsula from of old. It is to give this religion that India is rising. She does not rise as other countries do, for self or when she is strong, to trample on the weak. She is rising to shed the eternal light entrusted to her over the world. India has always existed for humanity and not for herself and it is for humanity and not for herself that she must be great.” (CWSA 8: 5-6)

“…day after day, He showed me His wonders and made me realise the utter truth of the Hindu religion. I had had many doubts before. I was brought up in England amongst foreign ideas and an atmosphere entirely foreign. About many things in Hinduism I had once been inclined to believe that it was all imagination; that there was much of dream in it, much that was delusion and maya. But now day after day I realised in the mind, I realised in the heart, I realised in the body the truths of the Hindu religion. They became living experiences to me, and things were opened to me which no material science could explain.” (CWSA 8: 9)

“When I approached God at that time, I hardly had a living faith in Him. The agnostic was in me, the atheist was in me, the sceptic was in me and I was not absolutely sure that there was a God at all. I did not feel His presence. Yet something drew me to the truth of the Vedas, the truth of the Gita, the truth of the Hindu religion. I felt there must be a mighty truth somewhere in this Yoga, a mighty truth in this religion based on the Vedanta. So when I turned to the Yoga and resolved to practise it and find out if my idea was right, I did it in this spirit and with this prayer to Him, “If Thou art, then Thou knowest my heart. Thou knowest that I do not ask for Mukti, I do not ask for anything which others ask for. I ask only for strength to uplift this nation, I ask only to be allowed to live and work for this people whom I love and to whom I pray that I may devote my life.” I strove long for the realisation of Yoga and at last to some extent I had it, but in what I most desired, I was not satisfied. Then in the seclusion of the jail, of the solitary cell I asked for it again. I said, “Give me Thy adesh. I do not know what work to do or how to do it. Give me a message.” In the communion of Yoga two messages came. The first message said, “I have given you a work and it is to help to uplift this nation. Before long the time will come when you will have to go out of jail; for it is not my will that this time either you should be convicted or that you should pass the time as others have to do, in suffering for their country. I have called you to work, and that is the adesh for which you have asked. I give you the adesh to go forth and do my work.” The second message came and it said, “Something has been shown to you in this year of seclusion, something about which you had your doubts and it is the truth of the Hindu religion. It is this religion that I am raising up before the world, it is this that I have perfected and developed through the rishis, saints and avatars, and now it is going forth to do my work among the nations. I am raising up this nation to send forth my word. This is the Sanatana Dharma, this is the eternal religion which you did not really know before, but which I have now revealed to you. The agnostic and the sceptic in you have been answered, for I have given you proofs within and without you, physical and subjective, which have satisfied you. When you go forth, speak to your nation always this word that it is for the Sanatana Dharma that they arise, it is for the world and not for themselves that they arise. I am giving them freedom for the service of the world. When therefore it is said that India shall rise, it is the Sanatana Dharma that shall rise. When it is said that India shall be great, it is the Sanatana Dharma that shall be great. When it is said that India shall expand and extend herself, it is the Sanatana Dharma that shall expand and extend itself over the world. It is for the dharma and by the dharma that India exists. To magnify the religion means to magnify the country.” (CWSA 8: 9-10)

“The name of your society is “Society for the Protection of Religion”. Well, the protection of the religion, the protection and upraising before the world of the Hindu religion, that is the work before us. But what is the Hindu religion? What is this religion which we call Sanatana, eternal? It is the Hindu religion only because the Hindu nation has kept it, because in this peninsula it grew up in the seclusion of the sea and the Himalayas, because in this sacred and ancient land it was given as a charge to the Aryan race to preserve through the ages. But it is not circumscribed by the confines of a single country, it does not belong peculiarly and for ever to a bounded part of the world. That which we call the Hindu religion is really the eternal religion, because it is the universal religion which embraces all others. If a religion is not universal, it cannot be eternal. A narrow religion, a sectarian religion, an exclusive religion can live only for a limited time and a limited purpose. This is the one religion that can triumph over materialism by including and anticipating the discoveries of science and the speculations of philosophy. It is the one religion which impresses on mankind the closeness of God to us and embraces in its compass all the possible means by which man can approach God. It is the one religion which insists every moment on the truth which all religions acknowledge, that He is in all men and all things and that in Him we move and have our being. It is the one religion which enables us not only to understand and believe this truth but to realise it with every part of our being. It is the one religion which shows the world what the world is, that it is the lila of Vasudeva. It is the one religion which shows us how we can best play our part in that lila, its subtlest laws and its noblest rules. It is the one religion which does not separate life in any smallest detail from religion, which knows what immortality is and has utterly removed from us the reality of death.” (CWSA 8: 11-12)

Contents

Prefacev

Excerpts from Sri Aurobindo’s Famous Uttarpara Speechix

1. What Is India?1

2. Indian Civilisation and Culture17

I. The Fundamental Idea and the Essential Spirit22

II. Indian Culture in the Eyes of a Rationalistic Critic55

A. Leading Ideas58

B. Life-Value of Indian Philosophy69

C. Life-Value of Indian Religion75

D. The Rationalistic Critic’s Arguments Against Hinduism81

(i) The Total Irrationality of Hinduism81

(ii) The Paganism of Indian Religious Spirit85

(iii) Lack of All Moral Worth and Ethical Substance89

(iv) Lack of Power and Vitality in Indian Culture97

III. The Life-Value of Indian Culture – the Supreme Achievements of Indian Culture in Its Dealings with Life100

A. The Original Conception of Life – the European and the Indian100

B. The High Value and Soundness of the Indian Conception of Life110

(i) The Two Main Truths of Human Existence118

(ii) The Workings of Dharma – the Religious Law of Action and the Deepest Law of Our Nature121

(iii) The Exceeding of Dharma – The Ideal of Moksha or Mukti128

C. The Power of the Forms, Types and Rhythms That the Indian Culture Has Given to Life130

(i) The Three Stages or Periods in the History of the Indian Culture131

(ii) The Firm Outward Basis for the Founding of the Practical Development of the Spirit of Indian Culture and Its Idea in Life – The Fourfold Varnasram System133

IV. The Greatest Accomplishment of Indian Culture – the Web of the Sanatana Dharma151

A. The Whole Root of Difference between Indian and European Culture156

B. The Four Necessities of Human Life158

C. The Fundamental Idea and the Core of Indian Religion160

D. The Liberty of Religious Practice and Complete Freedom of Thought in Indian Religion168

E. The Combination of a Firm Spiritual Order with an Untrammelled Spiritual Freedom173

F. The Total Movement of Indian Spirituality – the Transmutation of All the Instruments of the Human Living into Instruments of a Divine Living179

G. The Spirit and Forms of Indian Religion and Spiritual Culture185

(i) The Vedic and Vedantic Form185

(ii) The Post-Vedic Age201

(iii) The Purano-Tantric Stage208

(iv) The Third and the Last Stage213

H. The Dynamic Formulation of Indian Religious Culture221

(i) The First Perception222

(ii) The Second Perception222

(iii) The Frame for the Execution of Its First Perception – The Triple Quartette223

(iv) The Cultural Effort for the Execution of the Second Perception – the Endeavour to Cast the Whole Life into a Religious Mould224

(v) The Third Perception – The Varying Natural Capacity of Man, Adhikāra226

(vi) The Means Used to Give Effect to the Third Perception – the Perception of the Three Types or Levels of the Evolving Human Soul and the Creation of the Varying Religious Atmosphere Suited to Each228

(vii) The Provision for or the Admittance of the Possibility of a Direct Approach to the Spiritual Reality Free of the Gradations234

V. The Linking of the Graded System of Religious Development and Spiritual Evolution to the General Culture of the Life of the Human Being and Its Powers235

A. The Rishi and the Shastra – the Linking and the Culture of the Thinking Being of Man235

B. The Dharma – the Culture and the Ordering of the Ethical Nature241

C. All the Arts Under the Sanction of the Rishi – the Linking and Culture of Aesthetic and the Hedonistic Being of Man243

D. The Building Up of Great Shastras – the Dealings with the Ordinary Dynamic, Political, Economical and Social Being of Man244

E. The General Character of the Endeavour to Apply Indian Ideals to Life246

VI. The Record of the Great Achievements of
India in Every Field246

3. The Ancient Indian Spirit, Its Four Powers and the Secret of Its Greatness – the Aryan System of Education254

I. The Spirit of Ancient India254

II. The Four Powers258

A. Spirituality258

B. Stupendous Vitality260

C. Strong Intellectuality263

D. The Sounding of the Extremes and the Synthetic Impulse266

III. The Aryan System of Education273

A. The Basis – the Discipline of Brahmacharya274

B. The Process – the Conversion of the Retas into Ojas276

C. The Three Gunas and the Development of Sattva278

D. The Achievements of the Aryan System288

4. Indian Polity291

I. The Legend of India’s Political Incompetence291

II. The Nature of the Indian Monarchical State – Its Subjection to the Yoke of the Dharma294

III. The Secret of the Difficulty in the Political Unification in Ancient India300

A. The Charge of Incapacity for Political Unifications Against the Indian People300

B. The Logic of the Indian Mind in Its First Seeking of Spiritual and Cultural Oneness Before Seeking Political Unity303

C. The Sense in Which the Earlier Mind of India Understood the Problem of Unification305

D. The Ancient Rishis’ Perception of the Solution of the Problem: the Ideal of the Chakravarti307

IV. The Muslim Conquest and India’s Retaliation318

V. The Future of India319

Index329

1. What Is India?

“India is not the earth, rivers and mountains of this land, neither is it a collective name for the inhabitants of this country. India is a living being, as much living as, say, Shiva. India is a goddess as Shiva is a god. If she likes, she can manifest in human form.”1

‡ Sri Aurobindo had a living experience of the soul of India, so here he has opened before us a very novel and unique perspective. According to him, just as Lord Shiva, Sri Radha and other gods and goddesses have their own separate Being, similarly the Goddess of India has her own separate Being, which has its special mission. Considering the example of an individual soul, in its true being it is essentially one with the Paramatman and comes into this terrestrial manifestation, perhaps, with the aim of manifesting one attribute, one special aspect from among the infinite aspects of the Paramatman. So, in evolution it takes up a personality made up of a mind, vital and physical. This personality, a conglomerate of many personalities, has into it the entry of the different levels of consciousness, ranging from the inconscient and subconscient to the deepest and highest superconscient levels. That is why in life we see such infinite complexity, so many dualities – like pain and pleasure, loss and gain, success and failure, rise and fall. Making use of all these complexities, the Divine effectuates the manifestation of that special attribute which in the embodied soul is ingrained as the inner faith. Even in an individual’s life we can see such infinite variety and complexities – which tend to increase successively as he ascends to the higher and deeper levels of consciousness – and only after a long evolution of many many lives does an individual being begin to move towards its culmination, so how much more difficult it must be for us to even conceive of the dimensions and vicissitudes involved in the evolution of a cosmic being. Sri Aurobindo says that just as an individual has a separate being, similarly a nation too has a separate being. The Earth has its own distinct being as has the solar system and the universe. Each of these beings have their own inherent truth which they have to express. Similarly India too has a separate being which has its own profound truth that it has to express. When even in an individual being, it takes a long time for the soul to come to the front and effectuate its true expression, then the time taken in the development of a collective being must be very great by any of our human standards of time. When a person comes into contact with that being and has the experience of its soul only then can the person know something about its true purpose, about its past, present and future development, about its destiny. Without that contact and experience he always sees and judges things, persons, happenings etc. only superficially and fails to understand their true reason and their true course of movement. Having this direct experience and identification, Sri Aurobindo discusses in his work ‘The Human Cycle’ that the earth has a special destiny and has a place of distinction in the whole universe. And even in that, India has a very special place. From this wide perspective he reveals the past, present and the future course of the whole human race. At the same time, he reveals how during this entire course of development the function of India has always been to unlock the soul’s riches for the world and in future too her role would be to lead the world in the movement towards an integral fulfilment of the Divine Law on this earth. Only when we look with this perspective do we somewhat understand the deep logic behind the whole course of the development of our culture from its Vedic age to the present time and on the basis of that can be assured of India’s splendid future. But before India is ready to fulfil her great role, she must first rise out of the present degenerate condition and develop a strong nationalism and emerge as a powerful nation. The institutions, organizations, policies etc. which will prove to be helpful in the development of this nationalism will be the only ones that will be able to last, all the others will be discarded as alien elements. But unlike other nations the rise of India will not be to become powerful only to fulfil her self-interests. In the words of Sri Aurobindo, “She does not rise as other countries do, for self or when she is strong, to trample on the weak. She is rising to shed the eternal light entrusted to her over the world. India has always existed for humanity and not for herself and it is for humanity and not for herself that she must be great.”(CWSA 8, 6)

Qs: How can this being manifest in a human form?

Ans: We have the example of Sri Aurobindo before us. It was as if the soul of India found a concrete expression in him. Though in himself Sri Aurobindo represents a decisive action of the Supreme and by announcing the transformation of the entire earthly manifestation gives to the destiny of the whole earth a new dimension, but at the same time it seems that the soul of India has found its fullest self-expression in him. The secrets of the Indian culture, its spirit, its Sanatana Dharma, the Gita, the Vedas, Upanishads, Puranas, etc. have all been revealed, revived and re-established by him. In the past also, the soul of India has been given a voice from time to time through Swami Vivekananda, Guru Govind Singh, Shivaji and numerous other great souls. ‡

* * *

“Mother India is not a piece of earth; she is a Power, a Godhead, for all nations have such a Devi supporting their separate existence and keeping it in being. Such Beings are as real and more permanently real than the men they influence, but they belong to a higher plane, are part of the cosmic consciousness and being and act here on earth by shaping the human consciousness on which they exercise their influence.”²

* * *

“The Soul of India is one and indivisible. India is conscious of her mission in the world. She is waiting for the exterior means of manifestation.”3

* * *

INVOCATION, 15 August 1947

“O our Mother, O Soul of India, Mother who hast never forsaken thy children even in the days of darkest depression, even when they turned away from thy voice, served other masters and denied thee, now when they have arisen and the light is on thy face in this dawn of thy liberation, in this great hour we salute thee. Guide us so that the horizon of freedom opening before us may be also a horizon of true greatness and of thy true life in the community of the nations. Guide us so that we may be always on the side of great ideals and show to men thy true visage, as a leader in the ways of the spirit and a friend and helper of all the peoples.”4

* * *

“In the whole creation the earth has a place of distinction, because unlike any other planet it is evolutionary with a psychic entity at its centre. In it, India, in particular, is a divinely chosen country.”5

‡ The Mother has revealed here a profound and occult truth. In our Puranas and other ancient Indian literature also we get indications that even the gods wish to be born as humans, but Sri Aurobindo and the Mother have revealed the occult secret behind these things in a manner that we seldom find elsewhere. According to them, this entire universe is created as if the Divine wanted to manifest himself in circumstances completely opposite to his true self. And it is a great riddle in itself how the Divine who is Sachchidananda (i.e. ever existent, conscious and blissful) comes to manifest his true self again from the seemingly completely opposite circumstances – circumstances of Falsehood instead of Truth, complete Unconsciousness and Inconscience instead of Consciousness and pain and suffering instead of Bliss. For the ease of understanding, we may say that when we need to solve a huge problem or want to build something on a grand scale we first try it out on a small scale in the laboratory and only then apply the successful results on the large scale. In this sense the earth is the laboratory of this whole universe. The results obtained here can be applied in the whole universe. This is because on this earth all the other worlds have an entry. When the consciousness descends from its superconscient levels to the complete Inconscience, this process creates a descending series of increasingly dense planes which Sri Aurobindo calls the true mind, the true vital, the true physical. But when after the involution, the evolution of consciousness begins, then the physical, vital and mind evolve, but because of their Inconscient origin all kinds of impurities can be seen in them. But since all the different levels of consciousness have an entry into this earthly manifestation, when there is a descent of the divine consciousness and there is a divine manifestation here then it has its effect on all the other worlds. That is why in the whole creation the earth has a very special place. Whatever is realised here effects spontaneously the whole universe.

In the Puranas and other scriptures we find the description of myriad worlds. In them when we read the descriptions of the worlds of goddesses, worlds of the gods, world of Truth, of Sāketadhāma, of Goloka and of various other higher and subtle worlds, of their grandeur, their splendour, their great power, their immense and unimaginable opulence, then the earth seems to be nothing compared to their magnificence. In Sri Aurobindo’s epic ‘Savitri’ we find a vast scheme of higher, lower and deeper levels of consciousness. Then what is the thing that makes the earth such a special place that even the gods are eager to take birth here? According to Sri Aurobindo and the Mother, the earth is the chosen laboratory where the difficulties of the universe are concentrated and it is here that the solution will be given and therefore this is the one place where the Supreme Himself has descended. Unlike any other world, the earth is evolutionary, while all other worlds, no matter how magnificent in themselves, remain stationary and cannot ascend or come down because they do not have the contact of the Supreme through the psychic being, which is accessible only on the earth. It is only the earth that has the supreme privilege of the phenomenon of evolution. And since the Supreme Lord himself is always incarnate here, its splendour is far greater than any other world. It is this that the Gita terms ‘parāprakritirjīvabhūtā’[1] which means that the Consciousness-Force of the Supreme herself becomes the Jiva (the embodied Soul). This element of the Supreme is innate in the earth as the soul and the psychic being and that is why all possibilities are latent here. No matter how ignorant and obscure the earthly conditions may seem to us on the basis of outer appearances, Sri Aurobindo and the Mother have assured us that after the supramental transformation, after the establishment of the Divine Law, this obscurity of falsehood ignorance, etc. will not persist any longer and the terrestrial evolution will then not be from darkness to light but will be from light to ever greater light and will rise to ever diviner levels. Even on such a special earth, India has been chosen to fulfil a very special role. From the writings of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother and from the ancient Indian literature we come to know that the physical or subtle presence of some perfected souls, in the form of Rishis, have always been presiding and leading this nation towards its true destiny. This is why while today we barely find even the traces of any other ancient cultures, the Indian culture has not only survived the long periods of slavery, suffering, darkness and inertia, but, along with its growing external influence on the whole world, it is greatly increasing its spiritual and cultural influence and is now moving rapidly towards regaining its glory. ‡

* * *

“India is the guru of the nations, the physician of the human soul in its profounder maladies; she is destined once more to new-mould the life of the world and restore the peace of the human spirit.”6

‡ Qs: What is the meaning of the profound maladies of the soul and how has India been their physician?

Ans: At present we can see all around us how the whole socio-economic-political system is centred exclusively around the satisfaction of the lower physical and vital propensities. Essentially, all maladies are born when man ignores his soul and takes his vital and physical impulses as his true self, and it is from this that all physical and psychological problems arise, as we are witnessing today in the whole world. Sri Aurobindo writes at one place, “To see your Self in all creatures and all creatures in your Self – that is the unshakeable foundation of all religion, love, patriotism, philanthropy, humanity, of everything which rises above selfishness and gross utility. For what is selfishness? It is mistaking the body & the vital impulses for your true self and seeking their gratification, a gross, narrow and transient pleasure, instead of the stainless bliss of your true self which is the whole Universe & more than the Universe. Selfishness arises from Avidya, from the great fundamental ignorance which creates Ahankara, the sense of your individual existence, the preoccupation with your own individual existence, which at once leads to Desire, to Hunger which is Death, death to yourself and death to others. The sense that this is I and that is you, and that I must take this or that, or else you will take it, that is the basis of all selfishness; the sense that this I must eat that you, in order to live & avoid being eaten, that is the principle of material existence from which arises strife and hatred. And so long as the difference between I and you exists, hatred cannot cease, covetousness cannot cease, war cannot cease, evil & sin cannot cease, and because sin cannot cease, sorrow & misery cannot cease.” (CWSA 17, 140)

And this is what we are currently seeing everywhere. But no matter how many outer schemes or policies we make, how much change we make in the outer machinery, until we realise this fundamental truth, we will not be able to truly cure our ills. Sri Aurobindo says that, “This erring race of human beings dreams always of perfecting their environment by the machinery of government and society; but it is only by the perfection of the soul within that the outer environment can be perfected. What thou art within, that outside thee thou shalt enjoy; no machinery can rescue thee from the law of thy being.”(CWSA 12, 468)

This has been the true message of India and this is how it has been the physician of the profoundest maladies of mankind because it alone has always remained faithful to the Spirit. Once again it will rise and fulfil its destined role. But at present it seems to have been completely overwhelmed by the influence of Western materialism. This is the reason why Swami Vivekananda cautioned the Indians that, “...if you give up that spirituality, leaving it aside to go after the materialising civilisation of the West, the result will be that in three generations you will be an extinct race; because the backbone of the nation will be broken, the foundation upon which the national edifice has been built will be undermined, and the result will be annihilation all round.”(CWSV 3, 153)

That is why, looking at the current appearances any person of goodwill will feel concerned whether India will perish? If that were to happen then according to Swami Vivekananda, “...from the world all spirituality will be extinct, all moral perfection will be extinct, all sweet-souled sympathy for religion will be extinct, all ideality will be extinct; and in its place will reign the duality of lust and luxury as the male and female deities, with money as its priest, fraud, force, and competition its ceremonies, and the human soul its sacrifice. Such a thing can never be.”(CWSV 4, 347) ‡

* * *

“There is only one country in the world that knows that there is only one Truth to which everything should be turned, and that is India. Other countries have forgotten this, but in India it is ingrained in the people, and one day it will come out. ...I know the conditions of the country. Even if one person could put himself faithfully at the disposal of the Truth, he could change the country and the world.”7

‡ Therefore, to think that what after all can a single person do, is a mistake. And to justify this by saying that outer circumstances and times are not favourable, people are like this or that – is all a falsehood. When in truth there exists no separate being other than one’s own true self then, to use external circumstances, things and people as an excuse for one’s inaction is a deluded way of seeing things and negates the fundamental truth of one’s being, for so says the Vedanta, ‘ekamevadvitiyam’, meaning that there exist no two separate beings. In a true sense, whatever we see around in the outside world, or which-soever states of being or worlds we may have experienced or can ever experience even in our intensest trance, or any of the greater worlds and planes that we may find described somewhere, or even that whom we call the Supreme Self, essentially all of these are projected from our own consciousness only. Therefore, it is a fundamental truth that we can never come into contact with anything that has not been projected from within ourselves. So it is necessary that instead of remaining engrossed in his petty surface self, a person should discover his true self and live in it. Sri Aurobindo says in his epic ‘Savitri’ that, “One man’s perfection still can save the world.”(CWSA 34: 531) From a material stand-point a person is nothing whereas spiritually he is everything. So, depending upon whether we identify ourselves with the material part or with the inner spirit, in one case we are nothing and in the other we are everything. Out of ignorance a person blames outer circumstances, his surroundings, other people, the environs, social milieu or even the outer nature he has been endowed with, as obstacles to his progress. Or the person blames fate saying that he has not been given the opportunity to progress. But all these suggestions are deceitful in a sense and just become excuses for the person to not make an effort. It would be better for a person to get out of this deceitful condition as soon as possible and move in the right direction. ‡

* * *

“India is the country where the psychic law can and must rule and the time has come for that here. Besides, it is the only possible salvation for this country whose consciousness has unfortunately been distorted by the influence and domination of a foreign nation, but which, in spite of everything, possesses a unique spiritual heritage.

Blessings.”8 				(2 August 1970)

* * *

“From a spiritual stand-point, India is the foremost country in the world. Its mission is to give the example of spirituality. Sri Aurobindo came on earth to teach this to the world.

This fact is so obvious, that even a simple, ignorant farmer here is in his heart closer to the Divine than all the intellectuals of Europe.”9

* * *

“India shall take her true place in the world only when she will become integrally the messenger of the Divine Life.”10

‡ This will be the culmination of the revelation of the Vedic Rishis. The principle conception of the Truth, the Right and the Vast revealed by them in the Veda would be truly realised only when the ‘Divine Life’ is established upon earth and matter itself is transformed. Sri Aurobindo came for the establishment of this Divine Law which he termed as the Supramental Manifestation. Although, in the whole scheme of the different levels of consciousness as propounded by Sri Aurobindo, the Supermind itself is only the first of the spiritual levels in which the Spirit can freely express itself. In the planes higher than the Supermind, an increasingly grand and free expression of the Self is possible, but the human mind has no entry into these worlds, so we cannot truly conceive anything about them. But since the splendours of all those diviner worlds are inherent in the human soul, it is only proper that the soul should reveal those inherent possibilities and manifest them. It is for this that Sri Aurobindo and the Mother announced the Supramental Manifestation. They did not leave it as a philosophy or principle but, by a lifelong endeavour, actuated its descent in the subtle physical on the 29th of February, 1956. According to them, the true resolution of the inconscience, ignorance and other problems of the material world can be achieved only by the Supramental transformation. When India will give this message of a ‘Divine Life’ to the whole world – as it is already doing to some extent but must do it integrally now – only then will it be able to gain its true place in the world. ‡

* * *

“…Of all the proud nations of the West there is an end determined. When their limited special work for mankind is done they must decay and disappear. But the function of India is to supply the world with a perennial source of light and renovation. Whenever the first play of energy is exhausted and earth grows old and weary, full of materialism, racked with problems she cannot solve, the function of India is to restore the youth of mankind and assure it of immortality. She sends forth a light from her bosom which floods the earth and the heavens, and mankind bathes in it like St. George in the well of life and recovers strength, hope and vitality for its long pilgrimage. Such a time is now at hand. The world needs India and needs her free. The work she has to do now is to organize life in the terms of Vedanta,…”11

‡ Qs: ‘Of all the proud nations of the West there is an end determined. When their limited special work for mankind is done they must decay and disappear.’ What is the meaning of this?

Ans: The permanence of any nation depends on its fundamental idea about existence. Whatever physical, vital and mental forms there are in this world, they all derive their truth from the Eternal. The closer they are to the Eternal, the more permanence they will have. But if one considers the Eternal as only distantly true and confuses Him with His physical or psychical manifestations in this world, then it is a relatively false and impermanent ideal, and for this very reason one will not be able to survive for long.

The Greeks confused the Eternal with His physical manifestations and realised Him in the aspect of beauty; beauty therefore was the only law of morality which governed their civilization. Even their ethics were based on the avoidance of excesses in all directions, that is, to avoid excessive virtue as much as excessive vice, because for them, the excessiveness of either was hurtful to the sense of beauty. The whole system of governance was based on keeping a fine balance between one’s responsibilities to oneself and one’s obligations to others, and the sense of proportion was the one law of restraint in their private ethics. This was the peculiarity of the Greek culture and also the very reason for its failure to endure as a separate culture. The Roman culture conceived and defined the Eternal not in the aspect of beauty but of force governed by law, and accordingly erected their whole social and political structure and systematised their ethics. By religion they meant a constraint that bounded by certain fixed laws and they restrained life by strictly moulding it according to them. Discipline stood as the keynote of their system; discipline of the actions created an inelastic faithfulness to domestic and public duties; and since discipline greatly exercises a check on animal impulses, it produced an orderly courage and a cold, hard purity. Although all this strict discipline was very favourable to the creation of a powerful and well-ordered State and it is this that made the Roman civilization more long lived than the Greek, but it was not at all a favourable environment for the development of a many-sided civilization and it is due to this shortcoming that the Roman culture too could not last.

Similarly, the civilisations that we know of today or of which some traces are found, all of them sooner or later ceased to exist due to the insufficiency of their conception of the Eternal. It is in this sense that we may say that all of these have been experiments of nature in the cosmic evolution whose results clearly show us that every aspect of the Divine has its own truth but, when applied or insisted upon with exclusiveness, it turns into falsehood and, that is why, once its limited special work is done it must disappear. The peculiarity of the Indian culture has been that it raised the surface veil and saw the Eternal in its true form. But it saw the Eternal not only as the Universal Transcendent Self but also saw the same as the particular Self in each. It reached the singleness of the Eternal separate from this phenomenal universe, and at the same time saw the same Eternal pervading the numberless manifestations of the universe. It is this comprehensive and integral realisation that did not allow any kind of rigidity to enter into its philosophy and prepared infinite number of paths for reaching the Transcendent. It is because of its many-sidedness and plasticity that this culture exists even today. Also, whatever qualities or specialties other cultures had developed, they were present in this culture more completely and it is because of the wideness of these conceptions that the defects seen in exclusive or one-sided conceptions elsewhere are not seen here. In this context Sri Aurobindo writes about Indians that, “They had in full measure the Roman discipline, courage, purity, faithfulness to duty, careful conservatism; but these elements of character & culture which in the Roman were hard, cold, narrow and without any touch of the spirit in man or the sense of his divine individuality, the Hindus warmed & softened with emotional & spiritual meaning and made broad and elastic by accepting the supreme importance of the soul’s individual life as overriding and governing the firm organization of morals and society. They were not purely devoted to the worship and culture of beauty like the Greeks and their art was not perfect, yet they had the sense of beauty & art in a greater degree than any other ancient people; unlike the Greeks they had a perfect sense of spiritual beauty and were therefore able to realise the delight & glory of Nature hundreds of years before the sense of it developed in Europe. On the ethical side they had a finer justice than the Greeks, a more noble public decorum, a keener sense of ethical & social balance, but they would not limit the infinite capacities of the soul; they gave play therefore to personal individuality but restrained and ordered its merely lawless ebullitions by the law of the type (caste). In addition to these various elements which they shared with one civilization or another they possessed a higher spiritual ideal which governed & overrode the mere ethics (mores or customary morality) which the other nations had developed. Humanity, pity, chivalry, unselfishness, philanthropy, love of and self-sacrifice for all living things, the sense of the divinity in man, the Christian virtues, the modern virtues were fully developed in India at a time when in all the rest of the world they were either non-existent or existent only in the most feeble beginnings. And they were developed, because the Aryan Rishis had been able to discover the truth of the Eternal and give to the nation the vision of the Eternal in all things and the feeling of His presence in themselves and in all around them. ”(CWSA 17, 221) ‡

* * *

“India has in herself a faith of superhuman virtue to accomplish miracles, to deliver herself out of irrefragable bondage, to bring God down upon earth. She has a secret of will power which no other nation possesses. All she needs to rouse in her that faith, that will, is an ideal which will induce her to make the effort.”12

* * *

“India cannot perish, our race cannot become extinct, because among all the divisions of mankind it is to India that is reserved the highest and the most splendid destiny, the most essential to the future of the human race. It is she who must send forth from herself the future religion of the entire world, the Eternal religion which is to harmonise all religion, science and philosophies and make mankind one soul. In the sphere of morality, likewise, it is her mission to purge barbarism (mlecchahood) out of humanity and to aryanise the world. In order to do this, she must first re-aryanise herself.”13

* * *

“This nation is not a new race raw from the workshop of Nature or created by modern circumstances. One of the oldest races and greatest civilisations on this earth, the most indomitable in vitality, the most fecund in greatness, the deepest in life, the most wonderful in potentiality, after taking into itself numerous sources of strength from foreign strains of blood and other types of human civilisation, is now seeking to lift itself for good into an organised national unity. Formerly a congeries of kindred nations with a single life and a single culture, always by the law of this essential oneness tending to unity, always by its excess of fecundity engendering fresh diversities and divisions, it has never yet been able to overcome permanently the almost insuperable obstacles to the organisation of a continent. The time has now come when those obstacles can be overcome. The attempt which our race has been making throughout its long history, it will now make under entirely new circumstances. A keen observer would predict its success ... because the freedom, unity and greatness of India have now become necessary to the world.”14

* * *

[1]	Gita VII.5

References:

1.	CWM 13: 372

2.	CWSA 28: 482

3.	CWM 13: 351

4.	CWM 13: 352

5.	CWM 13: 368

6.	CWSA 07: 906

7.	India the Mother: 184, Mira Aditi Centre, Mysore, 1998

8.	CWM 13: 370

9.	India the Mother: 232, Mira Aditi Centre, Mysore, 1998

10.	India the Mother: 234, Mira Aditi Centre, Mysore, 1998

11.	CWSA 07: 1086

12.	CWSA 07: 1017

13.	CWSA 06: 84

14.	CWSA 08: 23

CWM: Collected Works of the Mother, Sri Aurobindo Ashram Trust 1978, Puducherry, Second Edition 2004

CWSA: Complete Works of Sri Aurobindo, Sri Aurobindo Ashram Trust, Puducherry

CWSV: Complete Works of Swami Vivekananda, Mayavati Memorial Edition, Published by Advaita Ashram, Kolkata.

Yogi Sri Krishnaprem, by Sri Dilip Kumar Roy, Publisher Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan, 3rd Edition, 1992

2. Indian Civilisation and Culture

“Indian civilisation must be judged mainly by the culture and greatness of its millenniums, not by the ignorance and weakness of a few centuries. A culture must be judged, first by its essential spirit, then by its best accomplishment and, lastly, by its power of survival, renovation and adaptation to new phases of the permanent needs of the race.”¹

‡ Often we come across criticisms of India and its culture charging that this nation has always been subjugated and downtrodden by foreign invaders and there has always been poverty here. Whatever modern development we now see here is all a gift of the Europeans. Mostly the criticisms we come across of this culture are based exclusively on the period of her decline, inertia and inactivity. But actually, this cannot be the right basis of judging any culture, and certainly is no way of judging a culture as ancient as the Indian. It would be easy for any discerning person to understand that even when describing some great personality we depict his greatness by that period of his life during which he had expressed himself best, and not only by the period of his outworn condition or his old age. A culture that had for millenniums irresistibly and incessantly manifested on a colossal scale in all the spheres of spirit, thought and life, explored new dimensions, opened up untrodden paths in every field for the whole human race, cannot be judged rightly or justly by anyone who concentrates exclusively on its weakness of a few centuries.

But a fundamental question arises that, what after all should be the proper standards for judging a culture? For, if the standards themselves are unsound, then no reasonable outcome can be expected from an evaluation based on these. For instance, if the Indian culture is to be reckoned by its military aggressiveness, its success in warfare against other nations and the triumph of its organised acquisitive and predatory instincts, its irresistible push towards annexation and exploitation, then India would hardly measure up to the standards of greatness, because any such tendency was completely alien to the spirit of her culture. While sharply criticising the use of such confused standards of greatness for judging India, Swami Vivekananda says, “It is said – the fittest alone survive. How is it, then, that this most unfitted of all races, according to commonly accepted ideas, could bear the most awful misfortunes that ever befall a race, and yet not show the least signs of decay? How is it that, while the multiplying powers of the so-called vigorous and active races are dwindling every day, the immoral (?) Hindu shows a power of increase beyond them all? Great laurels are due, no doubt, to those who can deluge the world with blood at a moment’s notice; great indeed is the glory of those who, to keep up a population of a few millions in plenty, have to starve half the population of the earth, but is no credit due to those who can keep hundreds of millions in peace and plenty, without snatching the bread from the mouth of anyone else? Is there no power displayed in bringing up and guiding the destinies of countless millions of human beings, through hundreds of centuries, without the least violence to others?”(CWSV 4, 323)

If wealth, opulence and external prosperity are the only benchmarks for the evaluation of a culture, then the fact remains that the splendour of Asia, and particularly the opulence of India, were once stigmatised by the indigent Europe as signs of barbarism. But after a long period of reckless plundering of that wealth when the circumstances were reversed, then that very Europe, taking pride in its plundered wealth, began to declare itself on that very basis to be civilised and developed, and it started deriding as uncivilised, poor and naked the very people whose wealth it had plundered and whose culture it had tried to annihilate in a systematic and motivated manner. The difference in life-values leads to a difference in outlook, and people start judging things according to their own prejudiced outlook. Swami Vivekananda, giving an example of what a great difference there lies between the Indian and the European mentality about their own past, says, “Did you ever hear of a country where the greatest kings tried to trace their descent not to kings, not to robber-barons living in old castles who plundered poor travellers, but to semi-naked sages who lived in the forest? Did you ever hear of such a land? This is the land. In other countries great priests try to trace their descent to some king, but here the greatest kings would trace their descent to some ancient priest.”(CWSV 3, 153)

It is clear from all this description that if a culture, especially the Indian culture, is judged on the basis of such prejudices and if the critic happens to be unsympathetic as well as prejudiced, or even more, if he is hostile, then from such a one we can never get that true appraisal of this culture for which Sri Aurobindo provides us the standards here. In order to evaluate a culture we have to first consider its essential spirit or motive. When we go to meet a great personality, before judging him, we need to have a sense of what his fundamental motive is. If a person visits Sri Aurobindo Ashram in Pondicherry, but does not have some sense of what the motive of that place is, what the philosophy of Sri Aurobindo is, what the fundamental aim of the Ashram is, for the realisation of which all the arrangements have been made, then he would only be able to have at best a view of the outer details of the organisation and will describe the place accordingly. Even the description of a unit like Sri Aurobindo Ashram in Pondicherry can be truly meaningful only when a person intimately understands the fundamental motive and the philosophy of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother. A right appreciation, to any extent, even of the outer details of a person, institution, system etc. can be made only in the light of its fundamental motive, purpose, central idea, and not otherwise. And once we know the fundamental motive of a nation, then we will have to consider the amount of effort it has put in the direction of realising that motive, and what are its achievements. If the motive in itself is great, but lacks outer expression or manifestation, or only very meagerly, then this will be a sign of insufficiency or imperfection and such a motive will have to be considered ineffective in practice. Instead, in the earthly manifestation, importance will be given to the nation which, even though having a comparatively less sublime motive, has successfully fulfilled it and with whatever capacity and resources at hand, has made achievements towards that motive. In practice, a motive will be considered to be realistic only to the extent it succeeds in molding itself in practical application. Now, even if a culture possesses both these characteristics, still its perfection will depend on how long it is able to survive. If the essential spirit of some culture is high and it has even made great achievements, but they are short lived, or if the culture lacks the capacity to bear any shock, or has not the necessary power to revive itself from some accident and move forward with renewed vigour, then this will be a sign of its incapacity, weakness and imperfection, and not of any greatness. Such a culture cannot be called an ideal culture. Therefore, a great culture should also have the power of survival and the capacity to bear all shocks triumphantly. Any long lived culture faces difficult times or periods in the course of its development. These periods have their own physical, psychological and spiritual demands, to which the culture has to respond by revealing new forms in the light of its fundamental spirit. If a person, society or culture lacks the power to adapt to the changed times or circumstances, then it will be a sign not only of its inflexibility and rigidity but also an indicator of its demise. In the course of its development, Indian culture has not only had the experience of the profound intuitive golden period of Satya yuga, but has over time also tasted the bitterness of subjection, servitude, inactivity and inertia. But during all these periods, preserving its original motive deep within itself, it has always expressed itself in new forms suitable to the period in question. The occult reason for this has been the constant presence, whether manifest physically or subtly, of the Rishis (seers) which has always upheld and led this nation towards its predestined goal. Moreover, the spirit of this culture has been so strong, all-pervasive and all-inclusive that, assimilating all the changing forms of different times and climes and purifying them in the divine fire that burns in its spiritual heart, it has always been able to shape them anew into forms suited to its spirit.

At present, too, in the course of its evolution mankind is undergoing a stage of crisis in which the human mind has achieved an enormous development in certain directions while in others it stands arrested and bewildered, and is trying to find its way. Physical science has put at its disposal many potencies of the universal Force and has made the life of humanity materially one. Humanity has erected such a huge and complex structure of external life for the service of his mental, vital, physical claims and urges that it is becoming unmanageable for his narrow intelligence. This structure is a complex political, social, administrative, economic, cultural machinery which is an organised collective means for his intellectual, sensational, aesthetic and material satisfaction. It is a system of civilisation which is getting ever more difficult to manage for his limited mental capacity and understanding and his still more limited spiritual and moral capacity. Due to man’s individual and communal ego and its ever increasing demands, a sense of apprehension or concern has started to arise in discerning persons that if things continue to follow the same course, then destruction is certain. At such a time, the soul of this culture has proclaimed, through the agency of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother, the descent of the supramental consciousness upon earth and the goal of the realisation of a divine life in a divine body. It is a sign of the remarkable adaptability of this culture that even amidst the most grim of circumstances, it sends forth a new light from its soul which creates new forms suited to the time.

After having set these standards for judging a culture, Sri Aurobindo will now move on to evaluate and reveal how this culture has fully lived up to these standards. ‡

I. The Fundamental Idea and the Essential Spirit

“It is essential, if we are to get a right view of Indian civilisation or of any civilisation, to keep to the central, living, governing things and not to be led away by the confusion of accidents and details. This is a precaution which the critics of our culture steadily refuse to take. A civilisation, a culture must be looked at first in its initiating, supporting, durable central motives, in its heart of abiding principle; otherwise we shall be likely to find ourselves, like these critics, in a maze without a clue and we shall stumble about among false and partial conclusions and miss entirely the true truth of the matter. The importance of avoiding this error is evident when we are seeking for the essential significance of Indian religious culture. But the same method must be held to when we proceed to observe its dynamic formulation and the effect of its spiritual ideal on life.

‡ If we wish to analyse the actions of a person, we need to first find out the purpose he is striving to fulfil. For, only when we know the destination of a person, can we rightly say whether the path he has taken to reach it is the right one or not. Similarly, when we have an understanding of the fundamental motive of the Indian culture, then only will we be able to view in a real perspective how suitable have those dynamic forms been in which it has embodied its essential spirit and how effective they have been for its expression. It is only then that we will be able to overview the course of the development of this culture in a proper perspective.

But even in getting a clear perception of the essential spirit of this culture, a formidable difficulty presents itself before us, and, that is of our own narrow externalised vision that is accustomed to seeing only the surface of things, and being engrossed in our ego we do not even have any perception of its narrowness, shallowness and smallness. For example, just as it is not possible for an ape’s consciousness to perceive the infinite possibilities latent in human consciousness as compared to an animal’s consciousness. In the same way, when an individual or a community who has not had any deeper realisation, and confusing the surface self for its true self, keeps engrossed in and strives day and night after the satisfaction of its petty material and vital hungers and cravings, it is not possible for such an individual or community living in such a consciousness to even get a glimpse of the riches of a culture that is based on the unfolding of the deeper parts of our being. It is for this reason that in their evaluation of the Indian culture, the critics find themselves caught in a maze of appearances. On the one hand, there is the teeming life of fast, festivals, customs, rituals, injunctions, various cults, etc., of which they cannot understand the first thing, on the other, the austere life of a Sannyasin. For a person living in ordinary surface consciousness, it is not possible to get even a glimpse of what joys there may be in an austere life, a life dedicated to overcoming desire rather than satisfying it. And it is due to this difference of consciousness that he will tend to describe an austere life as a life of impoverishment, the drying up of life-energy. One who has never had a sight of the lofty peaks of the Himalayas, the experience of the deep joy of climbing them and of the passion to stake even one’s life for such a venture, may call all this endeavour as nothing but an unproductive and futile frenzy which really should have no utility or attraction for a sane and rational person or society. As compared to any such adventurous external aims, the Indian culture placed before itself an aim unthinkably greater. It had glimpsed and had the experience of the absolute transcendent Being and developed a vast and complex system in the form of Sanatana Dharma which could lead, as swiftly as possible, each individual and collectivity, from whatever its immediate physical, emotional, psychological and inner state to the state of self-experience, self-attainment and self-fulfilment. Seldom do we come across a person who, even with an aspiration for self-realisation – which itself is not common – can actually fulfil it in his life to any extent and mould his life according to that ideal. The reason for this lies in the kind of outer nature with which we start in the evolution. This nature is such that it is occupied, almost exclusively, with the satisfaction of one’s egoistic and baser animal appetites. And since this journey of self-transcendence is much more of an inner and psychological nature than of the external, the path is compared to a razor’s edge and is full of deceptions and dangerous traps and ambushes because even a slight deviation in the inner course leads to a great deviation from the path externally. Still, Indian culture did not aim to take only a few gifted souls to this strenuous and formidable ideal of self-realisation but to prepare each and every soul for this ultimate journey and even achieved great success in this very difficult endeavour. During this great effort, this culture built – or rather, developed spontaneously through the inspiration of the Rishis – numerous external, but deep rooted forms, codes of conduct, systems, institutions, etc. We cannot get to the true purport of these forms on the basis of their outer appearance alone. It is only in the light of the fundamental motive of this culture that one can begin to rightly approach and understand these. When a critic tries to review the outer details without even understanding the basic motive of the culture and the need of such disciplines for its practical implementation, misconceptions naturally arise. It must be kept in mind that for anyone to have a deeper perception of even the fundamental motive itself, a certain inner cultivation and refinement is a prerequisite. When even to acquire the qualification for analysing a particular art demands long and methodical training under proper guidance, it is obvious that the capacity to really appreciate the deep motive of a spiritual culture can be acquired only by a great previous preparation, hard labour and discipline in the close company of persons who are solely moved by such a motive in their lives. ‡

Indian culture recognises the spirit as the truth of our being and our life as a growth and evolution of the spirit. It sees the Eternal, the Infinite, the Supreme, the All; it sees this as the secret highest Self of all, this is what it calls God, the Permanent, the Real, and it sees man as a soul and power of this being of God in Nature. The progressive growth of the finite consciousness of man towards this Self, towards God, towards the universal, the eternal, the infinite, in a word his growth into spiritual consciousness, by the development of his ordinary ignorant natural being into an illumined divine nature, is for Indian thinking the significance of life and the aim of human existence. To this deeper and more spiritual idea of Nature and of existence a great deal of what is strongest and most potential of fruitful consequences in recent European thinking already turns with a growing impetus. This turn may be a relapse to “barbarism” or it may be the high natural outcome of her own increasing and ripened culture; that is a question for Europe to decide. But always to India this ideal inspiration or rather this spiritual vision of Self, God, Spirit, this nearness to a cosmic consciousness, a cosmic sense and feeling, a cosmic idea, will, love, delight into which we can release the limited, ignorant, suffering ego, this drive towards the transcendental, eternal and infinite, and the moulding of man into a conscious soul and power of that greater Existence have been the engrossing motive of her philosophy, the sustaining force of her religion, the fundamental idea of her civilisation and culture.”²

‡ The fundamental conception of Indian culture is that, in the form of his soul, there is a truth inherent in man which is eternal, infinite and supremely blissful. His perception of the whole phenomenal world, the entire outer manifestation is, as though, an imperfect, crude or distorted form of that truth. The soul, in this manifestation, puts on as its instrument a personality made up of mind, life and body, and using it, marches towards regaining its own real self, its original truth. Since the composition of physical, emotional, psychological and inner parts in a person is entirely different from that of any other, and even in the same person their balance keeps shifting during his life – and not only that, the more conscious and inwardly developed a person becomes, the more will this change the balance of his emotional, psychological and inner parts, and their interrelationships – therefore the path of one person to reach his true goal is likely to be different from that of any other. It is a remarkable characteristic of the ancient Indian culture that from the very beginning it has been aware of this diversity. It knew that the Divine has infinite qualities, attributes and dimensions, and in each embodied soul He fulfils some particular facets of his Being. It is to effectively bring out and embody this truth that all the various systems of this culture evolved.

At the time when Sri Aurobindo was writing these articles about the Indian culture, he observed, in a progressive section of the Europe of that time, an inclination towards the deeper truths of life as propounded by the Indian culture. But in Europe itself this tendency was decried by others as a return to barbarism under the influence of Asia. Therefore, it was in view of the then current circumstances that Sri Aurobindo wrote that whether that turn was a relapse to barbarism or a natural outcome of opening and developing towards deeper and sublimer values of life, was for Europe itself to decide. The situation in the West has now changed a lot compared to that at the time of Sri Aurobindo and, as envisaged by him, the impact of Indian culture is increasing there day by day. In Western countries, while earlier there was hardly any Hindu temple, or ashram, or any spiritual centre to be found, but now the situation has changed so much that there would hardly be any city in which one would not find a number of these and in which the locals do not participate wholeheartedly. An example of this is the huge procession of the Chariot of Jaggannath celebrated with great pomp and show even in Western countries, and likewise, the celebration of some other Indian festivals and events is also becoming popular. While earlier the ancient Indian texts were looked down upon with scorn as the records of a barbaric mankind, now their study has become more and more the subject of research in universities. Texts of Indian spirituality are readily available at any good bookshop or library in any of the cities of the West. Where earlier, the inclination towards such study or towards the values of this culture, or visiting some spiritual teacher, etc. were looked down upon and disapproved, now such notions or such an outlook are almost gone and such an inclination is beginning to be considered proper. All these changes in the West are clearly visible to anyone who cares to observe them. But the question of whether the West is actually moving or going to move towards the spirit, towards deeper values of life in near future is a different matter. Here we are concerned only with the fundamental conception of Indian culture which, since its very beginning, has been that the spirit is the main element of our life and the sole purpose of life is to progressively express and fulfil it in terrestrial nature. ‡

* * *

“…the principle, the essential intention of Indian culture was extraordinarily high, ambitious and noble, the highest indeed that the human spirit can conceive. For what can be a greater idea of life than that which makes it a development of the spirit in man to its most vast, secret and high possibilities, – a culture that conceives of life as a movement of the Eternal in time, of the universal in the individual, of the infinite in the finite, of the Divine in man, or holds that man can become not only conscious of the eternal and the infinite, but live in its power and universalise, spiritualise and divinise himself by self-knowledge? What greater aim can be for the life of man than to grow by an inner and outer experience till he can live in God, realise his spirit, become divine in knowledge, in will and in the joy of his highest existence? And that is the whole sense of the striving of Indian culture.

‡ The conception, the vision of Indian culture has been the highest possible for human capability. It holds that the small and limited personality that man appears to be in this phenomenal manifestation is not the actual or the whole truth of his being. In its true Self, it is the Eternal itself that has come down into this temporal manifestation and it is the Infinite Consciousness that has become limited, and it is the Transcendent and Universal consciousness that has manifested as an individual personality. Such has been the conception of our Rishis. But they did not leave it as a sublime conception only, instead they made it the practical aim of the whole race. The voice of the Rishis has always been that man in his life can, by increasingly developing his inner consciousness, dwell in the native qualities of the soul, such as knowledge, bliss, love, etc. He can make his life a field for the ever more perfect expression of all those qualities, and by developing his consciousness can even become one with the Supreme Divine. This fundamental idea was behind all the creation that took place in India based on the Spirit and shaped by the spontaneous intuition and inspiration of the Rishis. ‡

It is easy to say that these ideas are fantastic, chimerical and impracticable, that there is no spirit and no eternal and nothing divine, and man would do much better not to dabble in religion and philosophy, but rather make the best he can of the ephemeral littleness of his life and body. That is a negation natural enough to the vital and physical mind, but it rests on the assumption that man can only be what he is at the moment, and there is nothing greater in him which it is his business to evolve; such a negation has no enduring value. The whole aim of a great culture is to lift man up to something which at first he is not, to lead him to knowledge though he starts from an unfathomable ignorance, to teach him to live by his reason, though actually he lives much more by his unreason, by the law of good and unity, though he is now full of evil and discord, by a law of beauty and harmony though his actual life is a repulsive muddle of ugliness and jarring barbarisms, by some high law of his spirit, though at present he is egoistic, material, unspiritual, engrossed by the needs and desires of his physical being. If a civilisation has not any of these aims, it can hardly at all be said to have a culture and certainly in no sense a great and noble culture. But the last of these aims, as conceived by ancient India, is the highest of all because it includes and surpasses all the others. To have made this attempt is to have ennobled the life of the race; to have failed in it is better than if it had never at all been attempted; to have achieved even a partial success is a great contribution to the future possibilities of the human being.”³

‡ The main difference between the West and India is that while the life of the West is turned outward, that of India is turned inward. This fundamental difference in outlook is the reason for their difference in attitude towards life and, correspondingly, in all the forms that have arisen from it. While the Indian tendency has always been to first know the reason and the deeper truth behind things and then in that light to see and judge the outer forms and their interrelationships, the Western tendency, in the absence of any deep perception, measures a being exclusively by its more surface expressions and considers the sensible life alone as the all in all. Therefore, its whole effort has naturally been to satisfy man’s physical and vital being. The proper business of the mind – a part of the being and a power higher in scale than the vital and the physical – is to remain open to intuitions and inspirations coming from the higher and deeper parts of the being and be instrumental in expressing these in life as best as it can by keeping the physical and vital parts under its control and guidance. But, instead, due to the externalising outlook of life in the West, it gets enslaved by the physical and vital parts and – as can be seen clearly in the modern societies – remains largely confined to the search for ever more and more efficient arrangements for the satisfaction of these parts. Therefore, when it comes to the question of the reality of the Self, the Eternal and the Infinite, the Western mentality tends to call these fanciful. For it, the structure of our mind, life and body that we have got at present, is all that we have and we should try to make an increasingly efficient use of this in such a way that we may derive the maximum possible comfort, enjoyment and satisfaction out of this ephemeral life. The root of this belief is that man can only be what he is at present. Therefore, it is necessary that he is trained to make the most of his endowments by making increasing use of the powers and potencies of physical science for this purpose. To its view, this is the real meaning of development, whereas, truly, the chief aim of any great culture should be to progressively open before man novel dimensions on an ascending scale and help him in his ascension so that, from whatever his current stage, he may keep rising to ever greater heights of his being and, at the same time, keep progressively expressing them in his life. In the beginning, the natural man is engrossed in the crudeness, unreason, ugliness, discords, desires and wants and needs of the physical being. Therefore, the primary aim of any culture should be to refine and cultivate a man to be more civilised, reasonable, aesthetic, sensitive, harmonious and self-controlled. It is relatively easy to see the necessity of the refinement of the external personality – almost all cultures realise its importance and try to work for it – but Indian culture did not just stop here but went far beyond it and in attempting to lift man beyond his transience placed before him the aim of realising his true self, of gaining the riches of the Spirit. An aim greater than any other and containing in itself all other aims transcends them, because it opens before him the inconceivable idea in which human life becomes not only an expression of his external capabilities but of inner and higher states of being. And life finds its true meaning and fulfilment in becoming the sphere for this sublime expression. This has been the highest aim of Indian culture and centred on it, it has created its whole structure. The spiritual aim of Indian culture is so unimaginably great that even to have made an effort for it is a sign of an indomitable courage. To even have the courage to set out for such a great endeavour and apply one’s full capacity for its realisation – even though the chances of success in such a highly improbable adventure may appear to be bleak, or even when failure seems certain – is to open for man new avenues and possibilities and greatly increase his future prospects. To explore the secrets of even the material world, we see scientists making untiring efforts and despite the substantial time and resources spent, the first efforts are not always successful. But without getting discouraged they continue to make fresh efforts and thanks to such spirit, physical science has put in the hands of mankind so many new capabilities. All this would not have been possible if the first failures had prevented man from making new attempts. Of course, the ceaseless efforts of physical science cannot really be compared to the work of Indian culture to realise its lofty aims because the scope of the physical science is completely different and limited. However, it does illustrate how the use of greater than the expected energy and resources are not wasteful in any attempt to realise a lofty aim. Actually, the more lofty the aim, the greater will be the possibilities that will open before one in the course of its pursuit. But just as it cannot be really explained to a grossly utilitarian person that without literature, art and music one is as good as an animal and it is only these things that make up one’s true manhood, similarly, it cannot be explained to a person having materialistic views that life gets its true meaning and justification only when one makes it the means to rise to ever higher levels of his consciousness, surpasses oneself and realises the truth of one’s being. ‡

* * *

“A true happiness in this world is the right terrestrial aim of man, and true happiness lies in the finding and maintenance of a natural harmony of spirit, mind and body. A culture is to be valued to the extent to which it has discovered the right key of this harmony and organised its expressive motives and movements. And a civilisation must be judged by the manner in which all its principles, ideas, forms, ways of living work to bring that harmony out, manage its rhythmic play and secure its continuance or the development of its motives. A civilisation in pursuit of this aim may be predominantly material like modern European culture, predominantly mental and intellectual like the old Graeco-Roman or predominantly spiritual like the still persistent culture of India. India’s central conception is that of the Eternal, the Spirit here incased in matter, involved and immanent in it and evolving on the material plane by rebirth of the individual up the scale of being till in mental man it enters the world of ideas and realm of conscious morality, dharma. This achievement, this victory over unconscious matter develops its lines, enlarges its scope, elevates its levels until the increasing manifestation of the sattwic or spiritual portion of the vehicle of mind enables the individual mental being in man to identify himself with the pure spiritual consciousness beyond Mind. India’s social system is built upon this conception; her philosophy formulates it; her religion is an aspiration to the spiritual consciousness and its fruits; her art and literature have the same upward look; her whole dharma or law of being is founded upon it. Progress she admits, but this spiritual progress, not the externally self-unfolding process of an always more and more prosperous and efficient material civilisation. It is her founding of life upon this exalted conception and her urge towards the spiritual and the eternal that constitute the distinct value of her civilisation. And it is her fidelity, with whatever human shortcomings, to this highest ideal that has made her people a nation apart in the human world.”4

‡ It is quite obvious that even our physical body can be at ease and happy only when all its organs are healthy and functioning smoothly. If even one of the organs is in pain or is diseased, or is damaged, the body cannot feel happy. Just as the body, with all its organs, is an integral unit, similarly the human being too with its various parts – body, vital, mind and soul – is a whole unit that can function smoothly only by a proper coordination and harmony between all these parts. True happiness of life cannot be achieved by establishing harmony between the outer parts of our being only and neglecting the inner parts, which should, in the true nature of things, govern the outer parts and use them to express themselves. For, as pointed out by Sri Aurobindo, “Even to have a healthy body, a strong vitality and an active and clarified mind and a field for their action and enjoyment, carries man no more than a certain distance; afterwards he flags and tires for want of a real self-finding, a satisfying aim for his action and progress. These three things do not make the sum of a complete manhood; they are means to an ulterior end and cannot be made for ever an aim in themselves. Add a rich emotional life governed by a well-ordered ethical standard, and still there is the savour of something left out, some supreme good…”(CWSA 25, 224) And that thing is man’s soul, his true spirit.

Ancient Indian culture had a deep understanding of this fundamental truth from the very beginning that, behind our outer being is the eternal spirit and the whole meaning of life is to become conscious of its presence and to realise it by self-discovery and self-mastery. It is only by such a self-mastery that we can find what is good and beautiful in life otherwise it is full of unhappiness and disharmony. But as clearly the Rishis saw the spirit enveloped in matter and the inevitability of its progressive unfolding over time, so clearly did they also see the complexity of human nature and knew that only a system which recognized this complexity could be enduring. It is through the agency of such great ancient seers that by the action of the divine inspiration a grand system of eternal religion – Sanatana Dharma – got developed. Sanatana Dharma is the most perfect and efficient vehicle that strives to lead, as effectively as possible, both the individual and the collectivity to the accomplishment of the most sublime spiritual goal. In this pursuit, it surrounded the whole of the individual and communal life at every step with such symbols, rites, ideals, injunctions etc. as to keep its supreme goal in front of individuals and the society constantly and help them move towards that. Moreover, it was organised to govern all the parts by some higher Law, and yet leave plenty of room not only for the satisfaction of the mental, intellectual or ethical parts of the being, but also for the satisfaction of the most outer and hedonistic parts.

The undeniable evidence of India’s faithfulness to its soul and its persistent effort and success in expressing it in practice in all the fields of life such as music, drama, architecture, sculpture, painting, literature, astronomy, astrology and in countless other fields is available for anyone who sincerely cares to look for it. It was able to excel in each field because its faithfulness to the Spirit, which is behind everything, was not one-sided but expressed itself through all the fields of mind, life and body.

At present India has become a living representation of all the acute problems faced by humanity at large and the true purpose of India is to solve these problems on the basis of the Spirit not only for itself but for the whole world. Spirituality is the innate quality given to India by the Divine to fulfil its special role. This it can do by rediscovering itself and showing to the world that it is only by the harmonisation of the truth of its outer nature with the truth of its inmost spiritual nature that it can live in harmony and find a true and lasting solution to its present discords. We feel that the chances of success on this front have increased significantly due to the February 29, 1956 descent of the supramental consciousness. ‡

* * *

“…there is a great difference between the spiritual and the purely material and mental view of existence. The spiritual view holds that the mind, life, body are man’s means and not his aims and even that they are not his last and highest means; it sees them as his outer instrumental self and not his whole being. It sees the infinite behind all things finite and it adjudges the value of the finite by higher infinite values of which they are the imperfect translation and towards which, to a truer expression of them, they are always trying to arrive. It sees a greater reality than the apparent not only behind man and the world, but within man and the world, and this soul, self, divine thing in man it holds to be that in him which is of the highest importance, that which everything else in him must try in whatever way to bring out and express, and this soul, self, divine presence in the world it holds to be that which man has ever to try to see and recognise through all appearances, to unite his thought and life with it and in it to find his unity with his fellows. This alters necessarily our whole normal view of things; even in preserving all the aims of human life, it will give them a different sense and direction.”5

‡ This fundamental difference of view about life is the reason for the complete difference between the Indian spiritual and the Western materialistic culture. It is only when one gets a deep experience of the fact that it is only our spirit or soul which gives to life and all its strivings their true meaning and value that one will be able to truly understand and appreciate the whole effort of the Indian culture, the profound object of all its art, literature, music, etc., and the great extent to which they have been able to faithfully express it. Only a deeper and sympathetic view will enable one to see the deep rationale behind those uncountable forms, traditions, customs, institutions, rituals, ceremonies which spontaneously sprang up in the process of an increasing expression of the truth of the spirit in human life. Only such a deep and sympathetic view can enable one to appreciate the superhuman genius and effort of a culture which has always been faithful to its deepest spiritual vision of the existence of the one without a second – Ekamevadvitiyam. And not only that one without a second, the Infinite, Transcendent and Eternal Being, but even this finite, terrestrial and time-bound being too is the same One, because, as India always saw, only the infinite can become finite, only the transcendent can manifest in universal conditions, and only the Eternal can take birth in time, otherwise there can be no basis for such a time-bound limited existence that we experience here. Not only this, but what seems to us undivine, even that, it saw as a mere disguise of that sole-existent One. It is on the basis of this supreme and comprehensive vision that the Indian culture structured its whole web of life. And since in everything it saw the One – the Infinite and the Eternal behind, therefore its all-absorbing interest was always to reveal that divine source behind the visible appearances and connect these with the Source.

According to Sri Aurobindo, “The superconscient, not the subconscient, is the true fountain of things. The significance of the lotus is not to be found by analysing the secrets of the mud from which it grows here; its secret is to be found in the heavenly archetype of the lotus that blooms for ever in the Light above.”(CWSA 31, 616) Now, in the light of the above it becomes obvious that the current approach of science in its search for truth is just the opposite of what is needed. It is only through consciousness that things can be truly understood. Therefore, the attempt to reach the truth on the basis of matter alone cannot be very successful. In this context the following remark of Sri Aurobindo is very illuminating, “There is no fundamental significance in things if you miss the Divine Reality; for you remain embedded in a huge surface crust of manageable and utilisable appearance. It is the magic of the Magician you are trying to analyse, but only when you enter into the consciousness of the Magician himself can you begin to experience the true origination, significance and circles of the Lila. I say “begin” because the Divine Reality is not so simple that at the first touch you can know all of it or put it into a single formula; it is Infinite and opens before you an Infinite Knowledge to which all Science put together is a bagatelle.”(CWSA 28, 332) So the only thing worthwhile and meaningful is that we should go within, develop our consciousness, realise our true self and then try to express only that. ‡

* * *

“If we would understand the essential spirit of Indian civilisation, we must go back to its first formative period, the early epoch of the Veda and the Upanishads, its heroic creative seed-time. If we would study the fixed forms of its spirit and discern the thing it eventually realised as the basic rhythm of its life, we must look with an observing eye at the later middle period of the Shastras and the classic writings, the age of philosophy and science, legislation and political and social theory and many-sided critical thought, religious fixation, art, sculpture, painting, architecture. If we would discover the limitations, the points at which it stopped short and failed to develop its whole or its true spirit, we must observe closely the unhappy disclosures of its period of decline. If, finally, we would discover the directions it is likely to follow in its transformation, we must try to fathom what lies beneath the still confused movements of its crisis of renascence. None of these can indeed be cut clean apart from each other; for what developed in one period is already forecast and begun in the preceding age: but still on a certain large and imprecise scale we can make these distinctions and they are necessary for a discerning analytic view. But at present we are only concerned with the developed forms and the principal rhythms which persisted through its greater eras.

‡ Thus there are broadly three periods through which the Indian culture passed. The first was the seed-time, followed by the outflowering of that seed-time in various forms, and finally the period of decadence. Here we should keep in mind that the things of the seed-time did not disappear even in the second and the last period, only their outer appearance underwent some change. This is the reason why even in the present times the Vedas, the Upanishads, the Puranas, the Gita and other texts are still present and keep their influence behind each and every detail of our social and individual life in one form or the other.

But to understand why after all this culture had to go through these stages, we must first understand what the aim of this culture was. For, only in the light of that aim can we rightly analyse the course of development it followed, and understand the logic of all the different forms, vicissitudes etc. that it met on the way. Once we understand this, then the periods through which the Indian culture passed will appear not as random accidents, but as perfectly interconnected and systematic episodes of the progression. If the goal of a person is to ascend a lofty mountain, or to take a long sea voyage, or to build a huge palace, then according to the respective goals broad outlines will have to be prepared first. According to these outlines the routes or the courses will be different, as also the materials required for the endeavour. Even the nature of the problems or crises likely to be met on the way will be different, and eventually, the greatness of the success achieved in the pursuit will be in proportion to the sublimity of the goal, because there can hardly be any comparison between climbing a small hill and scaling a towering mountain, and, therefore, between the successes achieved in both these endeavours. Now, if the critic happens to be ignorant about the goal, then on what basis can he judge whether or not the actions or activities of a person are in accordance with it? Even more absurd than this is when the critic tries to denigrate a person for having failed in accomplishing something which the person was not even striving for. So, it is only when we understand what the real aim of the Indian culture was – although even to have a true sense of that requires a deep inner cultivation and a vast and refined intelligence – that we will be able to truly understand the logic of the periods through which it passed. We can somewhat try to understand the course of development of this culture through this example : suppose we get an inspiration to build a huge palace and we resolve to give shape to that inspiration. We prepare a broad framework for the construction and mobilise the initially necessary resources and the construction work begins. It involves first building some supporting structures that can be removed once their use is over. Since the plan is so huge and vast, it takes a long time for even the basic structure to be ready. Not only that, until it reaches its completion, it probably has to face many seasons, many natural adversities or numerous other exigencies, or even such disruptions as were not and could not have been anticipated at the time of the initial conception. Now, the person who doesn’t know or does not have the capacity to understand either the whole plan, or the process of execution of such a huge plan, or the nuances involved in the process and the challenges of such a work, or has any sense of the time taken in such constructions, then, can one ever hope to understand anything much of the whole plan from the perspective of such an ignorant person? This can be seen happening at present, almost universally, in India where the educated class – groomed under the system of education, values, institutions brought in wholesale from the West – has been trying to arrive at an understanding of their (Indian) culture. Never suspecting that they may be utterly incapable and off, and that in their ignorance they have been (especially since Independence) asserting their understanding and deprecatory judgement as the final truth about the Indian culture. Needless to add that there can be no comparison between the deep complexities and obstacles in the course of development of a great spiritual culture and the surface complexities and obstacles or problems involved in the construction of even the largest mansion or a city.

Seed-time was that period of the Indian culture when its fundamental conception or the fundamental aim was being formulated and the large lines were being laid accordingly. This was the time when the whole secret of our existence, of how the supreme consciousness manifests itself, was revealed through the Vedas. Since our Rishis dwelt in a consciousness of spontaneous spiritual intuition not expressible in plain mental terms, the truths were revealed in an apparently ambiguous language of symbols and figures which for the common masses, living predominantly in their physical consciousness, bore only some exoteric ritualistic sense while to those initiates and seers who were ready to understand and live according to that deeper purport, it revealed its secret inner meaning and the esoteric sense. This was the period when the Rishis were spontaneously open to and in union with the Divine consciousness in their inner being and so through their agency the Divine consciousness could flawlessly create the necessary forms, systems, institutions etc. for its self-expression. It is perhaps because of this that the vast and comprehensive structure of the Sanatana Dharma could evolve, for it is not possible for a mental consciousness to even conceive such a thing. The second period of this culture was the time when the original conception of the Rishis was expressed in more visible and external forms of life. The final stage came while facing the problems that arose in the course of practical implementation of that conception and resolving these in its light and adapting to the changed demands of the time marked by a further descent of the spirit into the vital and physical nature of man.

Qs. What is the meaning of the confused movements of the crisis of renascence?

Ans. There is an appearance of confused movements when in the course of development of a culture a period is nearing its maturity and a new period is emerging and, as a result, the new element begins to take greater prominence, although the achievements and elements of the previous period remain and still have their impact but do so mostly indirectly. Thus, the original intuitional and spiritual character of the Indian culture, which was predominant in the first period, fundamentally remained unchanged even in the changing forms of the subsequent periods; it only changed its expression in forms suited to the new period. As the initial age of intuition began to pass and mind began to dominate more and more, there came the period of the Upanishads and the six Darshanas and accordingly there was a change in the visible structure of society. Thus, as the spirit moved from the deeper to the more outer parts of being, that is, after intuition, as it moved more and more towards the outer parts of mind and vital, there came the changes in art, literature and other forms of expression, along with the changes in the social framework of Indian culture. At present the spirit seems to have come down to the most material parts of our nature and – coupled with the appearance of confused outer movements – is facing an acute difficulty in expressing itself through these. As always, Indian culture has again responded to this new equation in a most fitting manner. The coming of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother and their announcement of the descent of the supramental consciousness upon earth and thus opening the way towards the eventual transformation even of the material nature may be looked upon as the response of the Indian culture to the need of the hour. It is only Sri Aurobindo’s vision of a divine life upon earth that resolves the riddle of such an earthly existence. It is an enigma to the human reason that why should the supreme spirit descend and get entrapped into matter in the first place if the only purpose – as declared by a galaxy of great Yogis and Tapaswis – is to escape out of this earthly life into some form of liberation or Nirvana. In Sri Aurobindo’s view the earth is meant to express perfectly the highest heights of the spirit of which the Supramental Consciousness is the first decisive step which marks the ascent from chequered evolution in the ignorance to an evolution not from ignorance to knowledge but from knowledge to a greater knowledge. At present, mankind is going through a serious evolutionary crisis and a stage seems to have come where its very existence seems to be at stake. It is a crisis where all the problems facing humanity will have to be resolved in the light of the supramental spirit, for the current problems seem to be too overwhelming for the human mental consciousness to handle – preoccupied, as it is, with the petty satisfactions of its surface physical and vital nature. ‡

The problem which Indian culture had to solve was that of a firm outward basis on which to found the practical development of its spirit and its idea in life. How are we to take the natural life of man and, while allowing it sufficient scope and variety and freedom, yet to subject it to a law, canon, dharma, a law of function, a law of type, a law of each actual unideal human tendency and a law too of highest ideal intention? And how again are we to point that dharma towards its own exceeding by the fulfilment and cessation of its disciplinary purpose in the secure freedom of the spiritual life? Indian culture from an early stage seized upon a double idea for its own guidance which it threw into a basic system of the individual life in the social frame. This was the double system of the four Varnas and the four Asramas, – four graded classes of society and four successive stages of a developing human life.”6

‡ It is only when we understand the problem which Indian culture was striving to solve that we can understand the reason and the significance of the periods or ages through which it passed. This whole book is, as it were, a detailed elucidation of this very problem and the remarkable way in which the Indian culture has tried to resolve it. If a culture sets for itself a goal of self-realisation, self-mastery and the establishment of the rule of the spirit in life, then how should it go about building such a comprehensive system in which every person with all the complexities of his individual being, and the whole society, with all its various aspects and forms, can accomplish this goal as swiftly and as integrally as possible. Even an individual being is comprised of infinite complexities, with many personalities and various parts, such as material-physical, hedonistic, emotional, imaginative, aesthetic, idealistic, ideative and intellectual and increasingly higher and deeper parts of consciousness. The balance of all these parts and personalities varies from person to person, and even in one person it changes with the changing stages of his physical, psychical and inner development. Therefore, to lead even an individual to self-realisation and self-mastery, starting from a particular equation of his being, is perhaps the most difficult task in human life. But the complexities involved become far too unfathomable and profound for the human mind to even contemplate when such a goal is set for the whole society. Still, such has been the very effort of this culture. The problem before it was how to build a system in which even the most insignificant activity and even the smallest detail of human life may be brought into contact with the soul and kept under a higher law, a system in which, even while allowing them their just chance of satisfaction, the lower tendencies of the vitalistic parts of man are refined and opened to a higher aim, and in which having freed them from their narrow grooves, the mind is filled with wider perspectives. In the course of this pursuit the comprehensive system or structure that developed through the agency of our Rishis is what we call Sanatana Dharma or the Eternal Religion. Here there is an important point which we should always keep in mind. When it is said that this structure was developed through our Rishis, then in fact it may be more appropriate to say that since the Rishis lived in an intuitive consciousness and were in constant union with the spiritual consciousness, the divine nature spontaneously used their agency to express itself as and when and where, and in forms and ways as suited best to its purpose. This is perhaps the secret of how such a comprehensive, all-embracing and ever-growing system of Sanatana Dharma could manifest. It is not at all necessary that the Rishis had consciously planned for or would have even been conscious of any such system in this way – the way Sri Aurobindo has been able to perceive it. By the divine providence, it was left to Sri Aurobindo to provide a perfectly coherent and deep systematic perspective on the functioning of the Sanatana Dharma in Indian culture and thereby put in the right perspective the forms, types and rhythms that it gave to life in its long evolutionary course. Nowhere else do we find the rationale of why in the pursuit of its goal did this culture develop novel forms, rhythms and systems such as the four varnas and the four ashramas. In addition to these there was yet another quartette of the four purusharthas which we shall be discussing later on in greater detail.

When talking of the system of varnas, being generally ignorant of the fundamental truth behind it, one tends to regard it as based on an occupational or a caste distinction. But fundamentally, in our ancient tradition the division of Chaturvarnas or the fourfold order of society was based on a profound spiritual and psychological truth of our being and nature, which is as relevant even today as it was in the ancient times. The basis of this truth is our innate nature, our swabhava. Originally this division was made from the point of view of sadhana, not from the point of view of any occupation or economic division, for, profession or outer work was only a means for the expression of that innate nature. Later on, when the identification of the inner swabhava became difficult, birth came to be taken as the main determining factor and the varna of a person began to get determined solely on the basis of his heredity.

The fundamental truth behind the Chaturvarna or the fourfold order, as revealed by Sri Aurobindo, is that the Divine Mother has infinite powers and personalities, but in terrestrial manifestation only four of her personalities – Maheshwari, Mahakali, Mahalakshmi and Mahasaraswati – have been prominently active, and so, whichever power happens to be more prominently active in a person, the nature of the outer work most suited to him will be in accordance with that. For instance, if the action of Mahakali is prominent in a person then he will be more facilitated in a work that is in accordance with it, while on the contrary, if he were asked to engage in the work of service, he would not be able to truly perform it. Or, if in someone the aspect of knowledge happens to be predominant and therefore, has spontaneously a strong seeking for knowledge, then, he will find it cumbersome to undertake a work other than the one suited to his disposition, and he will not be able to do it well. This has been the rationale behind the system of the fourfold order in this culture. When the aim was to take the whole of society and the whole of humanity towards the Divine, then the work most suited to a person in leading him to the Divine depended much more on his inner nature, swabhava, than on his outer nature. Even in one single family there can be people with varying natures and to try to take them all towards the Divine by any one single line of work would not be fruitful. By not acting in accordance with his own swabhava, there arises a conflict within the person and the whole society will be deprived of the best that he could have otherwise given to it. Therefore, in order that a person may get the right guidance and proper standards for doing works ordained by his own swabhava, extensive and comprehensive shastras were written. When in this light we deeply meditate upon the system of fourfold order, we realise how indispensable it was for an individual and the society having the aim of self-exceeding before it. Along with it, there was yet another perception in this culture that generally the movement of a person towards his goal is necessarily marked by some distinct stages (Ashramas) in his life. For instance, even for a person endowed with the swabhava of brahmin, the dharma or the standard of conduct applicable to him at any given time will depend on whether he is in his childhood or in adulthood. For, can the same rules or obligations be imposed on a child as they can be on an adult? Not only this, along with the system of varnashrama, the law or the notion of desh-kala-patra, that is, place-time-person, also got developed. The very same dharma or law that is beneficial to one person may be absolutely disastrous for another. Even for the same person a thing that proved to be beneficial at a certain period of time may not prove to be so at a different time or in a different setting. Thus, the actual implementation of any dharma or law was not done without a reference to the time, place and person.

But the singular uniqueness of this culture was that despite all the complexity and pervasiveness of its various systems, it was still so flexible and sensitive to the call of the soul that once a person received the inner call, no varnashrama dharma would any longer be binding on him, rather only the law of his own soul or the word of his guru, since both are essentially the same, alone became binding on him. Therefore, it was a system in which the lower appetites were always kept strictly under the yoke of a higher law, yet it gave complete freedom to everyone to follow the call of their soul when that came. ‡

* * *

“On this first firm and noble basis Indian civilisation grew to its maturity and became a thing rich, splendid and unique. While it filled the view with the last mountain prospect of a supreme spiritual elevation, it did not neglect the life of the levels. It lived between the busy life of the city and village, the freedom and seclusion of the forest and the last overarching illimitable ether. Moving firmly between life and death it saw beyond both and cut out a hundred high-roads to immortality. It developed the external nature and drew it into the inner self; it enriched life to raise it into the spirit. Thus founded, thus trained, the ancient Indian race grew to astonishing heights of culture and civilisation; it lived with a noble, well-based, ample and vigorous order and freedom; it developed a great literature, sciences, arts, crafts, industries; it rose to the highest possible ideals and no mean practice of knowledge and culture, of arduous greatness and heroism, of kindness, philanthropy and human sympathy and oneness; it laid the inspired basis of wonderful spiritual philosophies; it examined the secrets of external nature and discovered and lived the boundless and miraculous truths of the inner being; it fathomed self and understood and possessed the world. As the civilisation grew in richness and complexity, it lost indeed the first grand simplicity of its early order. The intellect towered and widened, but intuition waned or retreated into the hearts of the saints and adepts and mystics. A greater stress came to be laid on scientific system, accuracy and order, not only in all the things of the life and mind, but even in the things of the spirit; the free flood of intuitive knowledge was forced to run in hewn channels. Society became more artificial and complex, less free and noble; more of a bond on the individual, it was less a field for the growth of his spiritual faculties. The old fine integral harmony gave place to an exaggerated stress on one or other of its elemental factors. Artha and kāma, interest and desire were in some directions developed at the expense of the dharma. The lines of the dharma were filled and stamped in with so rigid a distinctness as to stand in the way of the freedom of the spirit. Spiritual liberation was pursued in hostility to life and not as its full-orbed result and high crowning. But still some strong basis of the old knowledge remained to inspire, to harmonise, to keep alive the soul of India. Even when deterioration came and a slow collapse, even when the life of the community degenerated into an uneasily petrified ignorance and confusion, the old spiritual aim and tradition remained to sweeten and humanise and save in its worst days the Indian peoples. For we see that it continually swept back on the race in new waves and high outbursts of life-giving energy or leaped up in intense kindlings of the spiritualised mind or heart, even as it now rises once more in all its strength to give the impulse of a great renascence.”7

‡ It is as if Sri Aurobindo has provided here, in this extract, a comprehensive view of the entire history of the post-Vedic age of the Indian culture. It is on the basis of the systematic account given by him of the inner state of this culture during this period that we can better understand the rationale behind the forms it used for its expression, as well as the order in which they were expressed. Without this comprehensive view, one is lost in the multitude of historical events and knows not how to view and judge them. That is why even after having learnt of the whole course of the events of history – although without a deeper perspective even that is not truly possible – one is hardly able to put them together and get a feel for the vaster scheme underlying these seemingly incoherent events. The sense of the succinct and tacit account provided here by Sri Aurobindo becomes more and more apparent only when we approach it through a view based on the deeper truths of our being rather than a grossly materialistic surface view of existence. Then, without getting too perplexed by the outer appearances, we will be able to experience the deeper truth behind them. Also, when perceived through a deeper view, the whole course of evolution of this culture will appear to be a somewhat coordinated and systematic course of individual and collective development.

We have already discussed how the Indian culture had set before itself the great aim of self-realisation and self-fulfilment. The implementation of such an aim demands a system comprehensive and flexible enough to provide each individual with the necessary help and guidance according to the specific ‘swabhava’ of his soul (varna) and the outer stage of development of his life (ashram). A system that contradicts the fundamental nature of a person by ignoring his innate nature, ‘swabhava’, and thus giving rise to a conflict within him, cannot endure. And no firm and effective base can be built in such a state of conflict. Therefore, it is by keeping in view the inner and outer development of the whole being that the Rishis built that firm basis of ‘Varna-Ashram Dharma’ on which the Indian culture grew to its splendid richness.

There was no field of human endeavour, no aspect of life in which, due to its firm basis, this culture failed to achieve astonishing heights of opulence, splendour and magnificence. When we speak of a spiritual culture, generally the picture associated with it in the common mentality is that of an impoverished life of an ascetic who remains engrossed in some meditative state with little or no connection to normal activities of life. But true spirituality never really impoverishes life, rather, it is spirituality that gives life its true meaning and glory. Therefore, while this culture ‘filled the view with the last mountain prospect of a supreme spiritual elevation, it did not neglect the life of the levels. It lived between the busy life of the city and village, the freedom and seclusion of the forest and the last overarching illimitable ether.’ The peculiarity of the Indian mind has been that it tries to get to the spiritual reality behind the surface appearance of each thing and then views and judges the thing in that light only. It is due to this turn of the Indian culture that it did not neglect any of the psychological, vital, emotional and physical parts of the individual and collective existence, but rather gave them their true meaning by turning them into means of a divine manifestation in this earthly existence. This is the whole effort of our entire epic and puranic literature. There we can see how even the hedonistic tendencies in man were not coerced, but while being kept under a higher law, they were allowed their just chance of expression and satisfaction, so that instead of remaining focused on and bound to them forever, a person could gradually move on to higher life-values. Therefore, the unparalleled achievements of this culture during that period in all the fields of human endeavour prove it beyond the possibility of any doubt that as opposed to this general impression that the Indian tendency has always been of abandoning active life and retiring to a forest, in actuality the tendency has been towards laying the spiritual foundation for the true enrichment of life in all possible respects. It is generally believed that away from the busy and clamorous external life and after having done away with all social ties, it is relatively easier in the seclusion of a forest to establish contact with the deeper parts of one’s being and dwell in one’s inner consciousness. It is because of this belief that we see people, troubled by the urban noise and the mental disquiet, taking recourse to secluded places. But the Indian culture not only took all the aspects of the busy life of a city and village in its purview – whether they be economic, social, administrative, educational or commercial, or related to healthcare, animal husbandry or even cooking – and laid down for them detailed dharmas, i.e. laws or canons, but effectively made them the means of self-realisation and self-expression. Thus, ‘moving firmly between life and death it saw beyond both and cut out a hundred high-roads to immortality.’ This is to say that no matter at what stage of one’s inner or outer development of individual existence one was, or what one’s swabhava or inherent nature was, one would always be helped by such systems developed by our seers to move swiftly towards the truth of one’s being. The peculiarity of this system was that it provided for each individual the way most suited to his nature and his immediate stage of evolution and avoided the error of imposing one single path or rule or canon for all. For, if there was only one fixed path for approaching the divine, that might, at best, have been of use for the few suited for that kind of path, but it could never have been universally applicable to all. Depending on the bent of one’s nature, whether it was predominantly dynamic, emotional or intellectual, the path most suited to one was indicated. It is for this reason that in India we come across various paths of devotion and knowledge, various philosophies, systems of yoga and tantra, and numerous other systems and practices. From among these if we consider just one of them, the tantra, it is evident how masterfully it has dealt with even the vitalistic, emotional and hedonistic parts of our being – parts that are generally considered to be the most recalcitrant and unwilling to turn towards light – and has opened even for them very rich and novel ways of approaching the Divine. The uniqueness of this system is that it not only allows a person to approach the Divine through all possible attitudes – that of a disciple, of a slave, that of parental affection, of a beloved, or any other – and encourages him to establish a relationship with the divine through any possible means. Even the feeling of animosity towards the divine was not despised, rather we find in the Puranas examples of those, who, due to their intense enmity towards the divine, could attain a high status difficult even for a devotee to attain. One was free to follow the Shaiva, Shakta or Vaishnava cult or any other cult suited to the turn of one’s nature. Thus, this culture cut-out innumerable broad, as well as specific paths following which one could move towards the truth of one’s being. Here we should remember that for the Indian Rishis immortality did not imply an infinite progression of life without death but a state of consciousness beyond both, a state in which both were merely occasions in the soul’s journey.

‘It developed the external nature and drew it into the inner self; it enriched life to raise it into the spirit.’ The whole effort of this culture has been centred on cultivating the crude and unregenerate outer nature, refining it and making it civilised, awakening it to the deeper and subtler issues, drawing it into the inner self and enriching life so as to raise it into the spirit. This makes the whole terrestrial manifestation meaningful as all the parts of the being can participate in the joy of the divine manifestation here. The mainstream of Indian culture has always tried to give to life its true significance by allowing it its utmost chance of development in the light of the soul even though we do find a long tradition of other-worldly tendency prevalent in this culture. Revealing the deep truth behind this other-worldly tendency Sri Aurobindo writes in his work, ‘The Life Divine’, “...this obstacle of the mind, life and body, – the heavy inertia and persistence of the body, the turbid passions of the life-part, the obscurity and doubting incertitudes, denials, other-formulations of the mind, – is an impediment so great and intolerable that the spiritual urge becomes impatient and tries rigorously to quell these opponents, to reject the life, to mortify the body, to silence the mind and achieve its own separate salvation, spirit departing into pure spirit and rejecting from it altogether an undivine and obscure Nature. Apart from the supreme call, the natural push of the spiritual part in us to return to its own highest element and status, this aspect of vital and physical Nature as an impediment to pure spirituality is a compelling reason for asceticism, for illusionism, for the tendency to other-worldliness, the urge towards withdrawal from life, the passion for a pure and unmixed Absolute. A pure spiritual absolutism is a movement of the self towards its own supreme selfhood, but it is also indispensable for Nature’s own purpose; for without it the mixture, the downward gravitation would make the spiritual emergence impossible. The extremist of this absolutism, the solitary, the ascetic, is the standard-bearer of the spirit, his ochre robe is its flag, the sign of a refusal of all compromise, – as indeed the struggle of emergence cannot end by a compromise, but only by an entire spiritual victory and the complete surrender of the lower nature. If that is impossible here, then indeed it must be achieved elsewhere; if Nature refuses submission to the emerging spirit, then the soul must withdraw from her. There is thus a dual tendency in the spiritual emergence, on one side a drive towards the establishment at all cost of the spiritual consciousness in the being, even to the rejection of Nature, on the other side a push towards the extension of spirituality to our parts of nature. But until the first is fully achieved, the second can only be imperfect and halting.” (CWSA 22, 891-92) It is this ascetic or the other-worldly turn and the escapist tendency born of the spirit’s urge for self-conquest which is popularly taken to be the whole of the Indian culture. But if actually this were so, then the magnificent and great achievements made by this culture in every possible sphere of life would not have been possible. When Sri Aurobindo says that ‘it enriched life to raise it into the spirit’, it must be noted that this enrichment of life was not, as is generally believed to be, for the self-satisfaction of the lower tendencies, rather to equip a person with novel means for an ever richer expression of the spirit. The whole system was geared to cultivating all the various parts of the being with the sole intention of making them fit instruments for the divine manifestation and capable of partaking in its joy. ‘Thus founded, thus trained, the ancient Indian race grew to astonishing heights..’ This is a fact evident enough in the Puranas, the epics and other ancient Indian literature. The account of the immediate system as well as that of the great and magnificent characters in it amply reveal the astonishing heights to which this culture grew not only in the field of the spirit but even in that of the outer life and these characters continue to inspire the whole culture to this day. Through the characters of Ramayana – such as Bharat, Lakshman, Sita, Hanuman, Vibhishan, Sugriva and numerous others – it is as though the human virtues had reached their ultimate heights. Moreover, these virtues were not confined to the elite class only, even the general public tended to abide by high standards of truthfulness, loyalty, straightforwardness, fidelity, heroism and numerous other such moral values and qualities. The Mahabharata also provides us a glimpse of the greatness of this civilisation and culture and also of those marvellous summits to which this culture arose. The modern mentality is to regard the great epics as fanciful poetic creations with some historical content. But even if fanciful, firstly, such a grand and unparalleled flight of conception, where all the values of life – inner or outer – have been taken to their zenith, is nowhere else to be seen. Also, even the flight of imagination does not spring out of a previous void, but requires a firm ground of an intense inner development, refinement, and culture. Therefore, even to have such a sublime imagination is a sure sign of a supremely developed culture. Moreover, we hardly come across any other epic literature of the world that has infused life in the whole nation for millenniums and still continues to uplift and guide the whole race to some extent. Further, this culture ‘lived with a noble, well-based, ample and vigorous order and freedom.’ To establish some kind of effective organisation or system on the basis of rigorous outer regimentation and rules and regulations is one thing, as was in the case of the Roman culture, but a system noble, all-pervasive and vigorous and still inherently free can only be founded on the soul as has been done by the Indian culture. An outer freedom devoid of the soul’s guidance generally degenerates into the unbridled satisfaction of the lower appetites of the mind, life and body and without an inner discrimination an outer system or organisation, sooner or later, becomes mechanical and inflexible and is doomed to pass out. It is only in a spiritually advanced culture that vigorous order and complete freedom may walk hand in hand.

‘It (the Indian culture) developed a great literature, sciences, arts, crafts, industries’. It is in its literature that we must seek for the most flexible and many-sided self-expression of a culture, for it is the word used in all its power of clear figure or its threads of suggestion that carries to us most subtly and variably the shades and turns and teeming significances of the inner self in its manifestation. In the words of Sri Aurobindo, “The greatness of a literature lies first in the greatness and worth of its substance, the value of its thought and the beauty of its forms, but also in the degree to which, satisfying the highest conditions of the art of speech, it avails to bring out and raise the soul and life or the living and the ideal mind of a people, an age, a culture, through the genius of some of its greatest or most sensitive representative spirits. And if we ask what in both these respects is the achievement of the Indian mind as it has come down to us in the Sanskrit and other literatures, we might surely say that here at least there is little room for any just depreciation and denial even by a mind the most disposed to quarrel with the effect on life and the character of the culture. The ancient and classical creations of the Sanskrit tongue both in quality and in body and abundance of excellence, in their potent originality and force and beauty, in their substance and art and structure, in grandeur and justice and charm of speech and in the height and width of the reach of their spirit stand very evidently in the front rank among the world’s great literatures. The language itself, as has been universally recognised by those competent to form a judgment, is one of the most magnificent, the most perfect and wonderfully sufficient literary instruments developed by the human mind, at once majestic and sweet and flexible, strong and clearly-formed and full and vibrant and subtle, and its quality and character would be of itself a sufficient evidence of the character and quality of the race whose mind it expressed and the culture of which it was the reflecting medium.” (CWSA 20, 314-15)

We must remember that the colossal Indian literature that as yet we have been able to deal with is only a fraction of what is still lying extant and what is extant is only a small percentage of what was once written and known because most of it has been either destroyed by the invaders or has perished over time due to the lack of modern facilities of printing. According to historians, the Nalanda university was attacked thrice. After being attacked by Huns and Gauds, it was finally ransacked and destroyed by the army of Bakhtiyar Khilji. A sense of the vastness of the library should impress itself on the reader by the fact that it took the army months to burn down all the books and manuscripts. The huge library of Alexandria, once a vast repository of works of ancient art, literature, philosophy and science, too is recorded to have met with the same fate at the hands of Islamic hordes. These examples are not exceptions, for we find a record of innumerable such instances at other places in India during the Muslim rule. ‡

II. Indian Culture in the Eyes of a Rationalistic Critic

It is felt that before we carefully consider the accomplishments of the Indian culture it is best to clear out certain misconceptions about it which have settled themselves in the mentality of most educated Indians as a result of hostile and unsparing rationalistic criticism directed at it by the people with an occidental mentality. A negative criticism, when it is honest and free from the tendency of overcharging – the criticisms of Mr. Archer, the rationalistic critic Sri Aurobindo addresses, is not of this kind – is good for the soul and the intellect provided we do not allow it to afflict, beat down or shake us from the upholding centre of our living faith and action, “Most things in our human world are imperfect and it is sometimes well to get a strong view of our imperfections. Or, if nothing else, we can at least learn to appreciate opposite standpoints and get at the source of the opposition; wisdom, insight and sympathy grow by such comparisons.”8

“To have put a high value on philosophy, sought by it the highest secrets of our being, turned an effective philosophic thought on life and called in the thinkers, the men of profoundest spiritual experience, highest ideas, largest available knowledge, to govern and shape society, to have subjected creed and dogma to the test of the philosophic mind and founded religious belief upon spiritual intuition, philosophical thought and psychological experience, are signs, not of barbarism or of a mean and ignorant culture, but marks of the highest possible type of civilisation. There is nothing here that would warrant us in abasing ourselves before the idols of the positivist reason or putting the spirit and aim of Indian culture at all lower than the spirit and aim of Western civilisation whether in its high ancient period of rational enlightenment and the speculative idea or in its modern period of broad and minute scientific thought and strong applied knowledge. Different it is, inferior it is not, but has rather a distinct element of superiority in the unique height of its motive and the spiritual nobility of its endeavour.”9

‡ The greatness of a culture depends first on its fundamental conception. Indian culture recognised the Supreme self as the truth of our being and in its light it discovered and expressed the secrets of our being. But its peculiarity lies more in the fact that it could successfully apply that conception to dynamic life also. Any knowledge, thought, or philosophy can be considered to be truly realistic and effective only when it is applied to life and life is shaped by it. Ordinarily, there is such a gulf between a person’s thinking and his action that even if one has very noble thoughts and feelings, in actual active life one mechanically follows the lower impulses in service of the ego. Indian culture called in the most adept for the effective implementation of thought in life. Thus, a system where the society is moulded and governed by spiritually realised people must necessarily be relatively free from those errors and failings that are generally encountered elsewhere.

In Mr. Archer, we find a wholesale and unsparing condemnation and an attempt to unearth and state in the strongest terms all that can be said against India and its culture. His attack covers the whole field and thus allows us to see in a glance the entire antagonist case against Indian culture. Evidently, the eye of such a critic turns, not to the millenniums of culture and greatness of Indian civilisation but to the apparent ignorance and weakness of a few centuries. ‡

“In the poverty, confusion and disorganisation of a period of temporary decline, the eye of the hostile witness refuses to see or to recognise the saving soul of good which still keeps this civilisation alive and promises a strong and vivid return to the greatness of its permanent ideal. Its obstinate elastic force of rebound, its old measureless adaptability are again at work; it is no longer even solely on the defence, but boldly aggressive. Not survival alone, but victory and conquest are the promise of its future.

But our critic does not merely deny the lofty aim and greatness of spirit of Indian civilisation, which stand too high to be vulnerable to an assault of this ignorant and prejudiced character. He questions its leading ideas, denies its practical life-value, disparages its fruits, efficacy, character.”10

‡ While criticizing the Indian culture for poverty, for want of life-values, and so on, the critic forgets that it is his own barbaric civilization that has been, to a great extent, responsible for this destitute condition. The whole of human history testifies how wherever the European invaders have gone, they have always carried out indiscriminate massacres, bloodshed, inhuman atrocities on the people and destroyed the culture there. In this context, Swami Vivekananda said, “British rule in modern India has only one redeeming feature, though unconscious; it has brought India out once more on the stage of the world; it has forced upon it the contact of the outside world. If it had been done with an eye to the good of the people concerned, as circumstances favoured Japan with, the results could have been more wonderful for India. No good can be done when the main idea is blood-sucking. On the whole the old regime was better for the people, as it did not take away everything they had, and there was some justice, some liberty.

A few hundred, modernised, half-educated, and denationalised men are all the show of modern English India – nothing else. The Hindus were 600 million in number according to Ferishta, the Mohammedan historian, in the 12th century – now less than 200 million.

In spite of the centuries of anarchy that reigned during the struggles of the English to conquer, the terrible massacre the English perpetrated in 1857 and 1858, and the still more terrible famines that have become the inevitable consequence of British rule (there never is a famine in a native state) and that take off millions, there has been a good increase of population, but not yet what it was when the country was entirely independent – that is, before the Mohammedan rule. Indian labour and produce can support five times as many people as there are now in India with comfort, if the whole thing is not taken off from them.” (CWSV 8, 475-76) But it crosses all limits of indecency when even after inflicting such inhuman atrocities the tyrant has the audacity to criticise and ridicule this culture for that which they themselves are responsible for. Being deeply troubled by this fact, Swami Vivekananda said this in one of his lectures, on the work of Christian missionaries : “..whenever your ministers criticise us, let them remember this: If all India stands up and takes all the mud that is at the bottom of the Indian Ocean and throws it up against the Western countries, it will not be doing an infinitesimal part of that which you are doing to us. And what for? Did we ever send one missionary to convert anybody in the world? We say to you, “Welcome to your religion, but allow me to have mine.”(CWSV 8: 212-13) ‡

A. Leading Ideas

The rationalistic critic’s most serious charge against the effective value of Indian philosophy is that “it turns away from life, nature, vital will and the effort of man upon earth. It denies all value to life; it leads not towards the study of nature, but away from it. It expels all volitional individuality; it preaches the unreality of the world, detachment from terrestrial interests, the unimportance of the life of the moment compared with the endless chain of past and future existences. It is an enervating metaphysic tangled up with false notions of pessimism, asceticism, karma and reincarnation, all of them ideas fatal to that supreme spiritual thing, volitional individuality. This is a grotesquely exaggerated and false notion of Indian culture and philosophy, got up by presenting one side only of the Indian mind in colours of a sombre emphasis, after a manner which I suppose Mr. Archer has learned from the modern masters of realism. But in substance and spirit it is a fairly correct statement of the notions which the European mind has formed in the past about the character of Indian thought and culture, sometimes in ignorance, sometimes in defiance of the evidence. For a time even it managed to impress some strong shadow of this error on the mind of educated India.”11

‡ To say that by putting an almost exclusive value on spirituality, Indian culture – under the influence of its leading philosophical ideas – turned away from life and has, therefore, been neglectful of the material base, is patently false. Sri Aurobindo makes this clear when he talks of the double aspect of Hindu temperament. According to him, “The Hindu has been always decried as a dreamer & mystic. There is truth in the charge but also a singular inaccuracy. The Hindu mind is in one sense the most concrete in the world; it seeks after abstractions, but is not satisfied with them so long as they remain abstractions. But to make the objects of this world concrete, to realise the things that are visited by sun & rain or are, at their most ethereal, sublimated figures of fine matter, that is comparatively easy, but the Hindu is not contented till he has seized things behind the sunlight also as concrete realities. He is passionate for the infinite, the unseen, the spiritual, but he will not rest satisfied with conceiving them, he insists on mapping the infinite, on seeing the unseen, on visualising the spiritual. The Celt throws his imagination into the infinite and is rewarded with beautiful phantoms out of which he evolves a pale, mystic and intangible poetry; the Hindu sends his heart & his intellect & eventually his whole being after his imagination and for his reward he has seen God and interpreted existence. It is this double aspect of Hindu temperament, extreme spirituality successfully attempting to work in harmony with extreme materialism, which is the secret of our religion, our life & our literature, our civilisation.”(CWSA 1: 212) ‡

Ancient Indian thought admitted that “....material and economic capacity and prosperity are a necessary, though not the highest or most essential part of the total effort of human civilisation. In that respect India throughout her long period of cultural activity can claim equality with any ancient or mediaeval country. No people before modern times reached a higher splendour of wealth, commercial prosperity, material appointment, social organisation. That is the record of history, of ancient documents, of contemporary witnesses; to deny it is to give evidence of a singular prepossession and obfuscation of the view, an imaginative, or is it unimaginative, misreading of present actuality into past actuality. The splendour of Asiatic and not least of Indian prosperity, the wealth of Ormuz and of Ind, the ‘barbaric doors rough with gold’, barbaricae postes squalentes auro, were once stigmatised by the less opulent West as a sign of barbarism. Circumstances are now strangely reversed; the opulent barbarism and a much less artistic ostentation of wealth are to be found in London, New York and Paris, and it is the nakedness of India and the squalor of her poverty which are flung in her face as evidence of the worthlessness of her culture.”12

“To say that Indian philosophy has led away from the study of nature is to state a gross unfact and to ignore the magnificent history of Indian civilisation. If by nature is meant physical Nature, the plain truth is that no nation before the modern epoch carried scientific research so far and with such signal success as India of ancient times. That is a truth which lies on the face of history for all to read; it has been brought forward with great force and much wealth of detail by Indian scholars and scientists of high eminence, but it was already known and acknowledged by European savants who had taken the trouble to make a comparative study in the subject. Not only was India in the first rank in mathematics, astronomy, chemistry, medicine, surgery, all the branches of physical knowledge which were practised in ancient times, but she was, along with the Greeks, the teacher of the Arabs from whom Europe recovered the lost habit of scientific enquiry and got the basis from which modern science started. In many directions India had the priority of discovery, – to take only two striking examples among a multitude, the decimal notation in mathematics or the perception that the earth is a moving body in astronomy, – calā pṛthvī sthirā bhāti, the earth moves and only appears to be still, said the Indian astronomer many centuries before Galileo. This great development would hardly have been possible in a nation whose thinkers and men of learning were led by its metaphysical tendencies to turn away from the study of nature. A remarkable feature of the Indian mind was a close attention to the things of life, a disposition to observe minutely its salient facts, to systematise and to found in each department of it a science, Shastra, well-founded scheme and rule. That is at least a good beginning of the scientific tendency and not the sign of a culture capable only of unsubstantial metaphysics.

It is perfectly true that Indian science came abruptly to a halt somewhere about the thirteenth century and a period of darkness and inactivity prevented it from proceeding forward or sharing at once in the vast modern development of scientific knowledge. But this was not due to any increase or intolerance of the metaphysical tendency calling the national mind away from physical nature. It was part of a general cessation of new intellectual activity, for philosophy too ceased to develop almost at the same time. The last great original attempts at spiritual philosophy are dated only a century or two later than the names of the last great original scientists. It is true also that Indian metaphysics did not attempt, as modern philosophy has attempted without success, to read the truth of existence principally by the light of the truths of physical Nature. This ancient wisdom founded itself rather upon an inner experimental psychology and a profound psychic science, India’s special strength, – but study of mind too and of our inner forces is surely study of nature, – in which her success was greater than in physical knowledge. This she could not but do, since it was the spiritual truth of existence for which she was seeking; nor is any really great and enduring philosophy possible except on this basis. It is true also that the harmony she established in her culture between philosophical truth and truth of psychology and religion was not extended in the same degree to the truth of physical Nature; physical Science had not then arrived at the great universal generalisations which would have made and are now making that synthesis entirely possible. Nevertheless from the beginning, from as early as the thought of the Vedas, the Indian mind had recognised that the same general laws and powers hold in the spiritual, the psychological and the physical existence. It discovered too the omnipresence of life, affirmed the evolution of the soul in Nature from the vegetable and the animal to the human form, asserted on the basis of philosophic intuition and spiritual and psychological experience many of the truths which modern Science is reaffirming from its own side of the approach to knowledge. These things too were not the results of a barren and empty metaphysics, not the inventions of bovine navel-gazing dreamers.”13

‡ To get the right perspective on the point under discussion it is necessary that the charge of the critic be considered in both its positive and negative aspects. To begin with, if the charge against Indian culture, that the whole of its philosophy discourages the dynamism of life, disregards worldly interests and personal volition and lays stress upon other-worldliness and inaction, were true, – although in his answer to this condemnation Sri Aurobindo has already proved its baselessness and the growing evidence only makes his testimony irrefutable – then how is it that a culture unconcerned with worldly life and bent on escaping from it could have made unparalleled accomplishments not only in the field of spirit but in all other fields too? If, despite having disregarded the material world, it has still secured higher and greater achievements – qualitatively and quantitatively – as compared to any other material culture preoccupied exclusively with the development of the material world to make the best it can of the ephemeral existence, it is a sign of supreme greatness of this culture, not of any inferiority. The mathematical tradition in India goes back to Sulba Sutras (around 800 BCE) and it is a well-established fact that the most important mathematical contribution of ancient India to the world is the invention of the decimal system of numeration, including the number zero. Even the most complex rules of modern mathematics can be found in Vedic mathematics prevalent in India even before mathematics had emerged in rest of the world. The decimal system, also known as the Hindu-Arabic numeral system, was invented in India. The unique feature of this system is the use of nine digits and a symbol zero to represent all the integral numbers by assigning a place value to the digits. Without this numeral system, no development of modern mathematics and the subsequent development of modern science and civilisations would have been possible. Similarly, in metallurgy, chemistry, surgery, Ayurveda, astronomy, architecture, city planning, bridge building, boat making, and numerous other areas the Indian culture has been the pioneer. But ignoring these undeniable facts, when a critique of this culture tries to prove this culture to be barbaric, uncivilized and poor, he obviously overlooks the question that why after all, the Muslim and the European invaders were so eager to discover the shortest sea routes to get to such a savage land? The already available and still growing large body of evidence of the looting and destruction perpetrated by these invaders irrefutably testify to the unimaginable opulence of this culture. Neither is there any possibility of charging this account with partiality, exaggeration, prejudice, or false statement, for we get it – either directly or as a contextual reference – through the books, letters, or documents written either by western writers, foreign travelers in India, or the immediate Muslim and English officials. In the multitude of all these records of Indian history, the certainty that emerges is the abundance of material wealth, the powerful application of human energy in all the walks of life. One of the famous books from among the various others on the subject of the plundering of India, ‘The Economic History of India Under Early British Rule’[1] by Mr. Ramesh Chandra Dutta, a lecturer of Indian history at London University College, reveals, by providing incontrovertible detailed data, on how the foreign lands had flourished at the expense of Indian blood. Here are some excerpts from this book. “…a change came over India under the rule of the East India Company. They considered India as a vast estate or plantation, the profits of which were to be withdrawn from India and deposited in Europe. They reserved all the high appointments in India for their own nominees seeking a lucrative career in the East. They bought their merchandise out of the revenues of India, and sold it in Europe for their own profit. They vigorously exacted from India a high interest on their stock-in-trade. In one shape or another all that could be raised in India by an excessive taxation flowed to Europe, after paying for a starved administration.” (pp. xii)

““What are the causes of this intense poverty and these repeated famines in India? Superficial explanations have been offered one after another, and have been rejected on close examination. It was said that the population increased rapidly in India, and that such increase must necessarily lead to famines; it is found on inquiry that the population has never increased in India at the rate of England, and that during the last ten years it has altogether ceased to increase. It was said that the Indian cultivators were careless and improvident, and that those who did not know how to save when there was plenty, must perish when there was want; but it is known to men who have lived all their lives among these cultivators, that there is not a more abstemious, a more thrifty, a more frugal race of peasantry on earth. It was said that the Indian money-lender was the bane of India, and by his fraud and extortion kept the tillers of the soil in a chronic state of indebtedness; but the inquiries of the latest Famine Commission have revealed that the cultivators of India are forced under the thralldom of money-lenders by the rigidity of the Government revenue demand. It was said that in a country where the people depended almost entirely on their crops, they must starve when the crops failed in years of drought; but the crops in India, as a whole, have never failed, there has never been a single year when the food supply of the country was insufficient for the people, and there must be something wrong, when failure in a single province brings on a famine, and the people are unable to buy their supplies from neighbouring provinces rich in harvests.” (pp. vi-vii) But despite high death rates and destitute conditions, there was no easing out on the collection of land taxes. In his book ‘Corporations that changed the world’ Nick Robins writes “Cornelius Walford calculated that in the 120 years of British rule there had been 34 famines in India, compared with only 17 recorded famines in the entire previous two millennia.” (p. 90, Publisher: Pluto Press, London)

Even after enduring a yoke of more than six hundred years of foreign rule India was, even materially, the most developed country of the world until the mid 1800’s. “Samuel Huntington of Harvard university writes that in 1750, India had 25 per cent of the world’s manufacturing output while Europe and America combined had less than 18 percent. But by 1900, after a hundred and fifty years of British rule, India’s manufacturing output had collapsed to less than 2 percent whereas America and the West combined had 84 percent of the world’s share. He writes:– ‘The Industrial revolution of the West was done at the expense of de-industrialisation of the colonies’.”[2] During the first 125 years of British rule more than 30 million Indians (more than 10 percent of the total population) died of starvation. During the same period the export of wheat and rice from India to Great Britain increased about 25 times. Even in the face of such cruel physical subjugation, the achievement of the Indian culture on the planes of mind and spirit continued to be so significant that in spite of the highly motivated attempts of the Western intellectuals, educationists and missionaries who have been trying very hard to undermine Indian religion and culture, it has not only survived but even thrived and has been increasingly penetrating and winning hearts and minds in the West. But in the face of such imposing accounts of opulence and greatness, the question that invariably arises is that if these accounts of the greatness of this culture are true then why did it have to suffer such violent relentless attacks, humiliation and subjugation at the hands of the foreign invaders? Was it only a spiritually advanced culture, and politically utterly incompetent? All these and other such questions, misgivings, and issues will be aptly dealt with and resolved in the closing chapter of this book on the Indian polity in the light of Sri Aurobindo. When viewed from the right perspective not only will it be apparent to us how the legend of Indian political incompetence has arisen from a false view of the historical development and an insufficient knowledge of the ancient past of the country but, even more, we will be able to see how its achievements even in the field of politics have been unthinkably great and unparalleled.

The great achievements of the Indian culture are now well-known and the ongoing researches and their results only add to the details of those achievements. In the face of such records of splendour and material well-being – especially before the establishment of the rule of the British East India Company – how is it that most foreigners have, almost always, gotten a strong impression of the presence of an ascetic tendency in this culture? If this is true – which undeniably seems so – then we need to look deeper to see how these entirely opposite tendencies have existed simultaneously in this culture without doing any harm to each other or, rather, seem to have been supporting each other?

Firstly, it can be clearly seen that among other tendencies, the other-worldly or ascetic tendency too can always be seen in this culture which never shied away from its insistence on the pure spirit and soul as the only true reality. This ascetic view takes man far from the narrow confines of the petty outer satisfactions to things vaster and greater in potency. It holds that the mind, life and body are only outer instruments or coverings of something that is greater and which alone gives them their importance and sustenance, otherwise in themselves these instruments are empty of significance. Therefore the ultimate purpose of life is to identify with that supreme truth of one’s being and to be released from the illusion of the view which gives undue importance to the outer existence and its appearances. The Kena Upanishad declares that ‘That is the divine Brahman and not this which men here adore.’ Throughout the Puranas also we find described in superlatives the much greater splendour and opulence of the various higher and subtler worlds, as compared to that of the earth. In Bhagawat Purana along with the other aspects, this turn is inherent and becomes very explicit at places. The idea of the transience and illusoriness of the world and also of a series of past and future lives is a common theme or undercurrent of the bulk of Indian literature. It is for this reason that to a materialistic view, which is focused exclusively on the preservation and maintenance of the physical body and the fulfilment of its animal appetites and, therefore, gives only secondary importance to the fulfilment even of the vital and mind, the ideas of transience and illusoriness of this world seem contrary to its conception of the fulfilment of the individual and the collectivity.

The mistake of the critics – inevitable in one form or the other when one is full of a censorious spirit – lies in giving an undue and central place to what they call the “other-worldly” tendency specially witnessed during the decadence of the last few centuries. To understand this seemingly excessive stress on asceticism during this period we must look deeply into its psychological necessity – as pointed out by Sri Aurobindo and Swami Vivekananda – for the Indian people in the presence of a wholesale material deprivation and starvation perpetrated by the British. The soul of the people – denied any room for expression in the external (material) life – naturally took psychological refuge in the ascetic tendency to survive and save itself from extinction, for this was the one field which the oppressors shied away from entering. And, as pointed out by Sri Aurobindo, this (its innate spirituality) was the one thing that Indian culture could never lose even in its darkest hours.

During the period of its material well-being before the coming of the foreign invaders – especially the British – the ascetic tendency in this country – though always present – was no more than an important, and even a necessary, strand or facet of its endeavour to spiritualise human life. To fully spiritualise human life all its powers – knowledge, will, love and ananda – must be turned towards the Divine and be consecrated to it by the power of the soul, and this has been the central motive of the Indian culture throughout.

An integral and wholesale pursuit of spirituality by this culture had given rise to three other (besides spirituality) powers – to be discussed in detail in the next chapter – of the ancient Indian spirit. These are, namely: (i) Stupendous vitality, (ii) Strong Intellectuality, and (iii) The synthetic impulse of mind and life. In an unhindered working of these powers lies the secret that is behind the extraordinary richness of life and material opulence of this culture.

In the material culture of the present, work is looked upon as a disutility, for which a person needs to be compensated. This is an obscuration of the tamasic nature and amounts to a perversity. Exercise of will, which is behind all the inner and outer achievements, is one of the greatest sources of joy and fulfilment in life as will be affirmed by any mature and sensible accounting and understanding of human life. When the motive behind the exercising of will is love and consecration to the Divine – present behind all masks of form and personality – all action takes on a very different colour and tends to become incomparably great in quality and quantity. India, during its long history, never lacked in the visible presence of a good number of people with such consecrated hearts. This seems to be the principal reason behind the stupendous vitality of Indian culture and the secret of its great achievements in every sphere of human life. One gets such a joy in performing consecrated acts that it is virtually impossible to stop one from engaging into these all the time. The works of a supreme quality get done automatically in such a state of self-forgetfulness. In India, the greatest achievements in the fields of art, music, literature and even politics seem to have been done by people moved by such a deeper psychology – Yogah Karmasu Kaushalam. As pointed out by Sri Aurobindo, the inherent tendency in India of exclusiveness and carrying the issues, in any field of endeavour, – including asceticism – to their extremes in its pursuit did not at all deter it from making almost superhuman achievements in most of the fields due to its characteristic synthetic impulse of mind and life. ‡

[1] Published by: KEGAN PAUL, TEENCH, TRUBNER & CO. Ltd., 6th Edition

[2] M. Nadkarni, India’s Spiritual Destiny, Sri Aurobindo Society, Pondicherry, Page 32

B. Life-Value of Indian Philosophy

“Equally is it a misrepresentation to say that Indian culture denies all value to life, detaches from terrestrial interests and insists on the unimportance of the life of the moment. To read these European comments one would imagine that in all Indian thought there was nothing but the nihilistic school of Buddhism and the monistic illusionism of Shankara and that all Indian art, literature and social thinking were nothing but the statement of their recoil from the falsehood and vanity of things. It does not follow that because these things are what the average European has heard about India or what most interests or strikes the European scholar in her thought, therefore they are, however great may have been their influence, the whole of Indian thinking. The ancient civilisation of India founded itself very expressly upon four human interests; first, desire and enjoyment, next, material, economic and other aims and needs of the mind and body, thirdly, ethical conduct and the right law of individual and social life, and, lastly spiritual liberation; kāma, artha, dharma, mokṣa. The business of culture and social organisation was to lead, to satisfy, to support these things in man and to build some harmony of their forms and motives. Except in very rare cases the satisfaction of the three mundane objects must run before the other; fullness of life must precede the surpassing of life. The debt to the family, the community and the gods could not be scamped; earth must have her due and the relative its play, even if beyond it there was the glory of heaven or the peace of the Absolute. There was no preaching of a general rush to the cave and the hermitage.

The symmetric character of ancient Indian life and the vivid variety of its literature were inconsistent with any exclusive other-worldly direction. The great mass of Sanskrit literature is a literature of human life; certain philosophic and religious writings are devoted to the withdrawal from it, but even these are not as a rule contemptuous of its value. If the Indian mind gave the highest importance to a spiritual release, – and whatever the positivist mood may say, a spiritual liberation of some kind is the highest possibility of the human spirit, – it was not interested in that alone. It looked equally at ethics, law, politics, society, the sciences, the arts and crafts, everything that appertains to human life. It thought on these things deeply and scrutinisingly and it wrote of them with power and knowledge. What a fine monument of political and administrative genius is the Śukra-Nīti, to take one example only, and what a mirror of the practical organisation of a great civilised people! Indian art was not always solely hieratic, – it seemed so only because it is in the temples and cave cathedrals that its greatest work survived; as the old literature testifies, as we see from the Rajput and Mogul paintings, it was devoted as much to the court and the city and to cultural ideas and the life of the people as to the temple and monastery and their motives. Indian education of women as well as of men was more rich and comprehensive and many-sided than any system of education before modern times. The documents which prove these things are now available to anyone who cares to study. It is time that this parrot talk about the unpractical, metaphysical, quietistic, anti-vital character of Indian civilisation should cease and give place to a true and understanding estimate.

But it is perfectly true that Indian culture has always set the highest value on that in man which rises beyond the terrestrial preoccupation; it has held up the goal of a supreme and arduous self-exceeding as the summit of human endeavour. The spiritual life was to its view a nobler thing than the life of external power and enjoyment, the thinker greater than the man of action, the spiritual man greater than the thinker. The soul that lives in God is more perfect than the soul that lives only in outward mind or only for the claims and joys of thinking and living matter. It is here that the difference comes in between the typical Western and the typical Indian mentality. The West has acquired the religious mind rather than possessed it by nature and it has always worn its acquisition with a certain looseness. India has constantly believed in worlds behind of which the material world is only the antechamber. Always she has seen a self within us greater than the mental and vital self, greater than the ego. Always she has bowed her intellect and heart before a near and present Eternal in which the temporal being exists and to which in man it increasingly turns for transcendence. The sentiment of the Bengali poet, the wonderful singer and rapt devotee of the Divine Mother, –

How rich an estate man lies fallow here!

If this were tilled, a golden crop would spring, –

expresses the real Indian feeling about human life. But it is most attracted by the greater spiritual possibilities man alone of terrestrial beings possesses. The ancient Aryan culture recognised all human possibilities, but put this highest of all and graded life according to a transitional scale in its system of the four classes and the four orders. Buddhism first gave an exaggerated and enormous extension to the ascetic ideal and the monastic impulse, erased the transition and upset the balance. Its victorious system left only two orders, the householder and the ascetic, the monk and the layman, an effect which subsists to the present day. It is this upsetting of the Dharma for which we find it fiercely attacked in the Vishnu Purana under the veil of an apologue, for it weakened in the end the life of society by its tense exaggeration and its hard system of opposites. But Buddhism too had another side, a side turned towards action and creation and gave a new light, a new meaning and a new moral and ideal power to life. Afterwards there came the lofty illusionism of Shankara at the close of the two greatest known millenniums of Indian culture. Life thenceforward was too much depreciated as an unreality or a relative phenomenon, in the end not worth living, not worth our assent to it and persistence in its motives. But this dogma was not universally accepted, nor admitted without a struggle; Shankara was even denounced by his adversaries as a masked Buddhist. The later Indian mind has been powerfully impressed by his idea of Maya; but popular thought and sentiment was never wholly shaped by it. The religions of devotion which see in life a play or Lila of God and not a half sombre, half glaring illusion defacing the white silence of eternity had a closer growing influence. If they did not counteract, they humanised the austere ascetic ideal. It is only recently that educated India accepted the ideas of English and German scholars, imagined for a time Shankara’s Mayavada to be the one highest thing, if not the whole of our philosophy, and put it in a place of exclusive prominence. But against that tendency too there is now a powerful reaction, not towards replacing the spirit without life by life without the spirit, but towards a spiritual possession of mind, life and matter. Still it is true that the ascetic ideal which in the ancient vigour of our culture was the fine spire of life mounting into the eternal existence, became latterly its top-heavy dome and tended under the weight of its bare and imposing sublimity to crush the rest of the edifice.”14

“There can be no great and complete culture without some element of asceticism in it; for asceticism means the self-denial and self-conquest by which man represses his lower impulses and rises to greater heights of his nature. Indian asceticism is not a mournful gospel of sorrow or a painful mortification of the flesh in morbid penance, but a noble effort towards a higher joy and an absolute possession of the spirit. A great joy of self-conquest, a still joy of inner peace and the forceful joy of a supreme self-exceeding are at the heart of its experience. It is only a mind besotted with the flesh or too enamoured of external life and its restless effort and inconstant satisfactions that can deny the nobility or idealistic loftiness of the ascetic endeavour. But there are the exaggerations and deflections that all ideals undergo. Those which are the most difficult to humanity, suffer from them most, and asceticism may become a fanatic self-torture, a crude repression of the nature, a tired flight from existence or an indolent avoidance of the trouble of life and a weak recoil from the effort demanded of our manhood. Practised not by the comparatively few who are called to it, but preached in its extreme form to all and adopted by unfit thousands, its values may be debased, counterfeits may abound and the vital force of the community lose its elasticity and its forward spring. It would be idle to pretend that such defects and untoward results have been absent in India. I do not accept the ascetic ideal as the final solution of the problem of human existence; but even its exaggerations have a nobler spirit behind them than the vitalistic exaggerations which are the opposite defect of Western culture.

After all asceticism and illusionism are minor issues. The point to be pressed is that Indian spirituality in its greatest eras and in its inmost significance has not been a tired quietism or a conventional monasticism, but a high effort of the human spirit to rise beyond the life of desire and vital satisfaction and arrive at an acme of spiritual calm, greatness, strength, illumination, divine realisation, settled peace and bliss. The question between the culture of India and the vehement secular activism of the modern mind is whether such an endeavour is or is not essential to man’s highest perfection.”15 And if it is admitted then the next question that arises is whether it is to be only an exceptional force confined to a few rare spirits or can it be made the main inspiring motive-power of a great and complete human civilisation as was done in India.

‡ The main reason behind this common impression, that Indian culture lays an exclusive stress on escaping from life lies in considering Buddhism and Shankarism as the whole of this culture. Such an impression may arise either when, being ignorant of the true nature of this culture, one approaches it through one’s own prejudices, or because one’s gross materialistic-hedonistic view of life is most contradicted and struck by this other-worldly aspect. Another possible reason for this impression is the widespread propagation and popularisation of Buddhist literature and the monistic works of Shankaracharya at a certain period of time. In the Vedas, Upanishads, Puranas and other ancient Indian literature, such exclusiveness is nowhere to be seen. The following words of the Mother provide a deeper perspective on this whole matter. “In our Yoga there is no room for sacrifice. But everything depends on the meaning you put on the word. In its pure sense it means a consecrated giving, a making sacred to the Divine. But in the significance that it now bears, sacrifice is something that works for destruction; it carries about it an atmosphere of negation. This kind of sacrifice is not fulfilment; it is a deprivation, a self-immolation.” (CWM 3, 114) During one of her discussions on Dhammapada she says, “Throughout this teaching there is one thing to be noticed; it is this: you are never told that to live well, to think well, is the result of a struggle or of a sacrifice; on the contrary it is a delightful state which cures all suffering. At that time, the time of the Buddha, to live a spiritual life was a joy, a beatitude, the happiest state, which freed you from all the troubles of the world, all the sufferings, all the cares, making you happy, satisfied, contented.

It is the materialism of modern times that has turned spiritual effort into a hard struggle and a sacrifice, a painful renunciation of all the so-called joys of life.

This insistence on the exclusive reality of the physical world, of physical pleasures, physical joys, physical possessions, is the result of the whole materialistic tendency of human civilisation. It was unthinkable in ancient times. On the contrary, withdrawal, concentration, liberation from all material cares, consecration to the spiritual joy, that was happiness indeed.”(CWM 3, 203)

C. Life-Value of Indian Religion

“A right judgment of the life-value of Indian philosophy is intimately bound up with a right appreciation of the life-value of Indian religion; religion and philosophy are too intimately one in this culture to be divided from each other. Indian philosophy is not a purely rational gymnastic of speculative logic in the air, an ultra-subtle process of thought-spinning and word-spinning like the greater part of philosophy in Europe; it is the organised intellectual theory of the intuitive ordering perception of all that is the soul, the thought, the dynamic truth, the heart of feeling and power of Indian religion. Indian religion is Indian spiritual philosophy put into action and experience. Whatever in the religious thought and practice of that vast, rich, thousand-sided, infinitely pliable, yet very firmly structured system we call Hinduism, does not in intention come under this description, – whatever its practice, – is either social framework or projection of ritual buttresses or survival of old supports and additions. Or else it is an excrescence and growth of corruption, a degradation of its truth and meaning in the vulgar mind, part of the debased mixtures that overtake all religious thinking and practice. Or, in some instances, it is dead habit contracted in periods of fossilisation or ill-assimilated extraneous matter gathered into this giant body. The inner principle of Hinduism, the most tolerant and receptive of religious systems, is not sharply exclusive like the religious spirit of Christianity or Islam; as far as that could be without loss of its own powerful idiosyncrasy and law of being, it has been synthetic, acquisitive, inclusive. Always it has taken in from every side and trusted to the power of assimilation that burns in its spiritual heart and in the white heat of its flaming centre to turn even the most unpromising material into forms for its spirit.”16

‡ The life-value of Indian philosophy is intimately one with the life-value of its religion, for, fundamentally, the work of religion has been to provide dynamic forms to the spiritual philosophy. After all, how can there possibly be any discordance or disharmony between the thought and action when one common spiritual intuition guides them both? In other cultures, philosophy has been either mostly, or completely, based on mental speculation, logical reasoning, or other abstractions devoid of any deeper spiritual experience, and as a consequence, philosophy lost contact with the truth of dynamic life and both religion and philosophy became two discordant movements. Whereas, in Indian culture, philosophy has been founded on deep spiritual intuition and revelation, and religion serves as a means for the effectuation of that highest revelation in the dynamic life by taking up both the individual and the society in its hands and gradually turning them towards the expression of that spiritual experience. In India, philosophy and religion have become one unified current, therefore the authenticity of philosophy is put to test at every step in its application to dynamic life. To take one instance, in the grand debate of Yajnavalkya with the Brahmavadins at the court of King Janaka, we find that the answer to questioning does not move by logic either in its inception, in its process or in its consummation, and the superiority of the conqueror is not decided by his proficiency in dealing with ever subtler ideas but by the depth of his knowledge and experience. The question one puts to another is not what one thinks, but what one fundamentally knows, what has one experienced, what one is in his true self, how intimately has one realised the truth, and how much of that truth one has been able to put into practice. The Mother asserts something to this effect when she says: “To know is good, to live is better, to be, that is perfect.”(CWM 15, 173)

It is a deep underlying spiritual experience that is the basis of each and every form and element in this culture, and it is that which synthesises them all. It is for this reason, that even seemingly contradictory philosophies have been accepted as different aspects of the same truth. Moreover, even in the presence of the many available methods, an infinite room has always been kept for still noveler paths of approaching the truth. For, this culture has always believed that each individual is and carries within himself a special attribute or truth of the divine which he alone will manifest. Therefore, the course of its unfolding or the path of its manifestation in an individual, even when apparently having close resemblance to some other path or system, is fundamentally unique. Even among those following a particular system, each follows one’s own different course of evolution. For example, even under the aegis of the common guru in Sri Aurobindo Ashram, Pondicherry, each sadhak/sadhika had his/her own line of experiences, and the way Sri Aurobindo and the Mother dealt with each one of them was according to their inner disposition and need as is evident from their correspondence with Sri Aurobindo and the Mother. When such qualities as inclusiveness, tolerance, infinite pliability, receptiveness, acquisitiveness, and so on are attributed to the Indian culture, it should not be taken to mean that an amalgam of an infinite variety of discordant components without coherence was thriving here due to a lack of clear control or management. On the contrary, it is indicative of a firmly founded system where a vast comprehensiveness and an infinite variety could move together in perfect association, a system where the smallest detail was turned into a form consonant with its spirit by the fire burning in the spiritual heart of this culture. As it is common sense to differentiate between a person and his changing raiments, so when we will have a deep understanding and experience of the fundamental spirit, the central motive of this culture, we will not be easily misled by the confusion of changing outer forms and be able to see through them the spirit behind which informs them. If we happen to come across something that doesn’t fall in conformity with the spirit of this culture, then according to Sri Aurobindo, it is ‘either social framework or projection of ritual buttresses or survival of old supports and additions’. Usually, all such forms or practices or things that were once living, but when their utility was over, or when they were no longer able to keep pace with the changing times and circumstances, the spirit inside them was lost and they remained mere frameworks or relics of some old supports. It is by the supply of fresh waters, that is to say, by the constant streaming in of renewed inner experiences, that any system, form or practice stays alive. In the age of intuition, when men live according to some high and profound realisation of their divine possibility, no fixed outer forms are required. But as society moves towards the surface parts of the being and its contact with the spiritual intuition weakens, it has to take recourse to fixed outer forms and practices, which after a time, due to the above mentioned reasons, become lifeless. It is these forms that are generally mistaken for the Sanatana Dharma. Even for a sect it is hardly possible to retain its original spirit and vitality after its founder is gone, and sooner or later it becomes a dead outer framework and finally dissolves unless renewed by an undisturbed line of seekers with genuine spiritual experience. The sects or traditions which have been able to perpetuate themselves for longer periods of time are the ones in which a continuous series of spiritual masters have brought in fresh spiritual revelations, and based on them, renewed outer forms adapted to the changing demands of the time and circumstances. The following words of Sri Aurobindo illumine this whole subject. “Take the hymn of the Rig Veda which is supposed to be a marriage hymn for the union of a human couple and was certainly used as such in the later Vedic ages. Yet the whole sense of the hymn turns about the successive marriages of Suryā, daughter of the Sun, with different gods and the human marriage is quite a subordinate matter overshadowed and governed entirely by the divine and mystic figure and is spoken of in the terms of that figure. Mark, however, that the divine marriage here is not, as it would be in later ancient poetry, a decorative image or poetical ornamentation used to set off and embellish the human union; on the contrary, the human is an inferior figure and image of the divine. The distinction marks off the entire contrast between that more ancient mentality and our modern regard upon things. This symbolism influenced for a long time Indian ideas of marriage and is even now conventionally remembered though no longer understood or effective…. Or let us take, for this example will serve us best, the Vedic institution of the fourfold order, caturvarṇa, miscalled the system of the four castes, – for caste is a conventional, varṇa a symbolic and typal institution. We are told that the institution of the four orders of society was the result of an economic evolution complicated by political causes. Very possibly; but the important point is that it was not so regarded and could not be so regarded by the men of that age. For while we are satisfied when we have found the practical and material causes of a social phenomenon and do not care to look farther, they cared little or only subordinately for its material factors and looked always first and foremost for its symbolic, religious or psychological significance. This appears in the Purushasukta of the Veda, where the four orders are described as having sprung from the body of the creative Deity, from his head, arms, thighs and feet. To us this is merely a poetical image and its sense is that the Brahmins were the men of knowledge, the Kshatriyas the men of power, the Vaishyas the producers and support of society, the Shudras its servants. As if that were all, as if the men of those days would have so profound a reverence for mere poetical figures like this of the body of Brahma or that other of the marriages of Suryā, would have built upon them elaborate systems of ritual and sacred ceremony, enduring institutions, great demarcations of social type and ethical discipline. We read always our own mentality into that of these ancient forefathers and it is therefore that we can find in them nothing but imaginative barbarians.”(CWSA 25, 7-9) This gives us some idea of the deep rationale behind ritualism or karmakanda. Our Vedic Rishis had a deep perception that the supreme truth can be experienced, it can be lived, but cannot be known, for it is not an object of knowledge. After all, what is the practical utility of a truth which cannot effectuate itself into action? Therefore, the whole social framework was surrounded at each step by rituals, ceremonies, festivals, and countless other practices with the sole aim of turning all the various parts of man towards the divine. But according to the Hindu theory of the Yuga cycle, as the culture moves on from the Vedic age of intuitive consciousness to the lower rungs of the cycle, it dwells more and more in its surface parts of the being. The symbols of the Vedic inner sacrifice are then no more as living and vivid as they used to be, rather, due to an externalised mentality and vision of things there is a degradation of the truth of the symbols in the vulgar mind and they begin to be taken into their more external and ritualistic sense. It is such ritual buttresses and survival of old supports that Sri Aurobindo is here referring to and forewarning us not to confuse these with the eternal religion. Apart from being merely ritualistic buttresses, these forms may quite possibly be an excrescence and growth of corruption, a degradation of the truth and its meaning in the crude mind, part of the debased mixtures that tends to overtake all religious thinking and practice over time. Or, in some instances, it may be a dead habit contracted in periods of fossilisation or some ill-assimilated extraneous matter gathered into this giant body. As, in the initial stages of one’s education when one starts learning basic skills of reading, writing, word-formation and comprehension, one often makes mistakes, or, as when a novice tries to draw a picture, his work is very crude and second rate, in the same way, when a person, lacking any deep experience, tries to deal with and enter into some profound truth, a degradation of the truth and its meaning is likely to ensue, even though the truth in itself remains unaffected by any such corruption or debasement. In their effort to refine, civilise and turn the subconscient and cruder parts of the being towards the Divine, the religious practices or tantric systems themselves have to bear dark spots and subjection to corruption. But we should never lose sight of the truth that given the present constitution of human nature, no matter what devices are used to control, discipline and rightly govern such a nature, these devices themselves have to bear its crudities and obscurities.

In the light of the above discussion, it should be evident that, to get the right view of the Sanatana Dharma, one must get to the fundamental spirit of this culture and realise it in oneself so that one may better understand not only the forms and the course it has taken for its self-expression but also get a sense of the difficulties and degradations that any truth is likely to be subjected to in its manifestation. It is only in the light of the right perspective that one is able to see how the things one had considered to be the shortcomings of this culture have been the inevitable consequences of the logic of its effort directed towards the spiritualisation of human life. ‡

D. The Rationalistic Critic’s Arguments Against Hinduism

(i) The Total Irrationality of Hinduism

This is the main theme of Mr. Archer’s attack on Hinduism. “He explains the pervading irrational character of Hindu religion by the allegation that the Indian people have always gravitated towards the form rather than the substance and towards the letter rather than the spirit. One would have supposed that this kind of gravitation is a fairly universal feature of the human mind, not only in religion, but in society, politics, art, literature, even in science. In every conceivable human activity a cult of the form and forgetfulness of the spirit, a turn towards convention, externalism, unthinking dogma has been the common drift of the human mind from China to Peru and it does not skip Europe on its way. And Europe where men have constantly fought, killed, burned, tortured, imprisoned, persecuted in every way imaginable by human stupidity and cruelty for the sake of dogmas, words, rites and forms of church government, Europe where these things have done duty for spirituality and religion, has hardly a record which would entitle it to cast this reproach in the face of the East. But, we are told, this gravitation afflicts the Indian religion more than any other creed. Higher Hinduism can be scarcely said to exist except in certain small reforming sects and current Hinduism, the popular religion, is the cult of a monstrous folk-lore oppressive and paralysing to the imagination, – although here again one would think that if anything an excess rather than a paralysis of the creative imagination might be charged against the Indian mind. Animism and magic are the prevailing characteristics. The Indian people has displayed a genius for obfuscating reason and formalising, materialising and degrading religion. If India has possessed great thinkers, she has not extracted from their thoughts a rational and ennobling religion: the devotion of the Spanish or the Russian peasant is rational and enlightened by comparison.”17

‡ Sri Aurobindo has already mentioned above that the gravitation towards form is a universal tendency of the human mind, and Europe is no exception to it – in fact, it is far more prone to it than the Indian mind. Still, it is the Indian mind that is criticised for gravitating towards form rather than the substance, while really the very opposite is the truth. For, in India the eye is always predominantly on the motive or the spirit behind the act rather than its outer form or expression. It is a recurring note in all Indian literature that the Divine is always the enjoyer of the feeling and the sentiment behind the offering. To understand why such aspersions are cast on the Indian culture we must ponder over why or how the eye of a critic gets the impression of an externalist turn in this culture, and, if even a trace of it is there, then what could possibly be the deep rationale behind such a tendency. Here are some excerpts from the writings of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother that provide us a deep perspective on this whole issue.

The Gita says, ““He who gives to me with a heart of adoration a leaf, a flower, a fruit or a cup of water, I take and enjoy that offering of his devotion” ..it is not only any dedicated external gift that can be so offered with love and devotion, but all our thoughts, all our feelings and sensations, all our outward activities and their forms and objects can be such gifts to the Eternal. It is true that the special act or form of action has its importance, even a great importance, but it is the spirit in the act that is the essential factor; the spirit of which it is the symbol or materialised expression gives it its whole value and justifying significance. Or it may be said that a complete act of divine love and worship has in it three parts that are the expressions of a single whole, – a practical worship of the Divine in the act, a symbol of worship in the form of the act expressing some vision and seeking or some relation with the Divine, an inner adoration and longing for oneness or feeling of oneness in the heart and soul and spirit. It is so that life can be changed into worship, – by putting behind it the spirit of a transcendent and universal love, the seeking of oneness, the sense of oneness; by making each act a symbol, an expression of Godward emotion or a relation with the Divine; by turning all we do into an act of worship, an act of the soul’s communion, the mind’s understanding, the life’s obedience, the heart’s surrender.”(CWSA 23, 162-63) Shedding further light on this quote of Sri Aurobindo, the Mother says, “There is a purely physical form of the act, like those forms in cults in which a particular gesture, a particular movement is meant to express the consecration. That is purely material, as for example, lighting incense, arranging offerings, or even looking after a temple, decorating an idol, indeed all such purely physical acts.

The second part is a sort of mental consecration which makes the act that is performed a symbol. One is not satisfied with merely lighting the incense, but while lighting the incense one makes this gesture symbolic – for example, of the aspiration burning in the body or of self-giving in a dissolution, in the purification of the fire. That is to say, first the act, then the symbol in this act and the symbolic understanding of what is done.

And finally, behind these two, an aspiration for union; that all this, these acts and the symbol you make of them, may be only a means of drawing closer and closer to the Divine and making yourself fit to unite with Him.

These three things must be there for the act to be complete: that is, something purely material, something mental, and something psychic, the psychic aspiration. If one of the three is there without the other two, it is incomplete. As a rule, very rarely are the three consciously combined. That produces beings of exceptional sincerity and consecration: the entire being, in all its parts, participates in the action.”(CWM 8, 234-35)

Along with providing a deep perspective on the accusation that ‘the Indian people have always gravitated towards the form rather than the substance and towards the letter rather than the spirit’, this whole discussion also reveals the supreme importance of the outer expression in order to make any act truly complete. Moreover, any mental speculations and dry metaphysical or rational gymnastics should not be taken for true knowledge. It is only the realisation of the Divine Reality that brings true knowledge, which can only be attained by love and devotion for the Divine. Even if a person professes to have attained the so-called knowledge but is devoid of devotion, then this is an undeniable sign of a lack of any true knowledge of the Divine Reality. Similarly, if a person is supposed to have devotion but the true knowledge of the Divine Reality is as yet absent, then this is a sure indicator of the lack of true devotion. True devotion and true knowledge are movements that always go together, and with them, spontaneously the true action joins in for an effective expression and manifestation of the devotion and knowledge. If a person has devotion but does not act for the Divine, then it means that he has neither knowledge nor devotion. For how is it possible not to act for someone we love or have devotion for? Therefore, (beyond a point) true knowledge, true devotion and true action always go together, complementing and perfecting each other. ‡

(ii) The Paganism of Indian Religious Spirit

“India ... still clings to what not only the Western world, but China and Japan have outgrown for ages. The religion is a superstition full of performances of piety repulsive to the free enlightened secular mind of the modern man. Its daily practices put it far outside the pale of civilisation. Perhaps, if it had confined its practice decorously to church attendance on Sundays and to marriage and funeral services and grace before meat, it might have been admitted as human and tolerable! As it is, it is the great anachronism of the modern world; it has not been cleansed for thirty centuries; it is paganism, it is a wholly unfiltered paganism; its tendency towards pollution rather than purification marks out its place as incomparably the lowest in the scale of world religions. An ingenious remedy is proposed. Christianity destroyed Paganism in Europe; therefore, since any immediate or very rapid triumph of sceptical free-thought would be too happily abrupt a transition to be quite feasible, we unenlightened, polluted, impure Hindus are advised to take up for a time with Christianity, poor irrational thing that it is, dark and deformed though it looks in the ample light of the positivist reason, because Christianity and especially Protestant Christianity will be at least a good preparatory step towards the noble freedom and stainless purities of atheism and agnosticism. But if even this little cannot be hoped for in spite of numerous famine conversions, at any rate Hinduism must somehow or other get itself filtered, and until that hygienic operation has been executed, India must be denied fellowship on equal terms with the civilised nations.”18

‡ The Indians have been advised to, first of all, purify themselves of idolatry and other impure superstitious practices to gain eligibility to sit among the civilised nations. If they find it difficult to do away with their ritualism all of a sudden, then it would at least be a good start to go to church on Sundays, offer a prayer on some occasions, and get the clergyman to perform some funeral rites for the dead. All these observances fall within the realm of being civilised for the very reason that they are followed by Christians, and after all, Christianity is the one to set the standards of being civilised or uncivilised. It has been a general impression about the Indian culture that it is a race of uncivilised people who need to be civilised, for, they are so muddled up in their head that disregarding the things sensible and tangible, they regard insensible or imperceptible things or the so-called subtle worlds as real. What greater imbecility can there be than to personify the forces of nature and to deify and idolise them? A vivid example of such a mindset towards Indian religion is reflected in the article ‘The British Rule in India’ written by Karl Marx on 10th June 1853, which was first published in ‘The New York Daily Tribune’ No. 3608 on 25 June 1853. In this article, while giving an account of the diversity in India, he writes about its religion, “That religion is at once a religion of sensualist exuberance, and a religion of self-torturing asceticism; a religion of the Lingam and of the juggernaut[3]; the religion of the Monk, and of the Bayadere.[4]” Further, giving an account of the atrocities committed by invaders, especially by the English, on the Indians, he writes, “There cannot, however, remain any doubt but that the misery inflicted by the British on Hindostan is of an essentially different and infinitely more intensive kind than all Hindostan had to suffer before.” Then in his own way, he gives a long account of how the British rule completely ruined the country. But he concludes his article by saying that undoubtedly the atrocities afflicted by the English on Indians have been inhuman but then after all, given the kind of uncivilised people Indians are, they had to be civilised somehow or the other. He writes, “We must not forget that these little communities were contaminated by distinctions of caste and by slavery, that they subjugated man to external circumstances instead of elevating man to be the sovereign of circumstances, that they transformed a self-developing social state into never changing natural destiny, and thus brought about a brutalizing worship of nature, exhibiting its degradation in the fact that man, the sovereign of nature, fell down on his knees in adoration of Hanuman, the monkey, and Sabbala[5], the cow.

England, it is true, in causing a social revolution in Hindostan, was actuated only by the vilest interests, and was stupid in her manner of enforcing them. But that is not the question. The question is, can mankind fulfil its destiny without a fundamental revolution in the social state of Asia? If not, whatever may have been the crimes of England she was the unconscious tool of history in bringing about that revolution.” Not only the European critics, the Indian critics, even more than the European critics, under the spell of western education and culture, feel proud in regarding and presenting themselves as free from all Indian religious traditions, idol worship, and other practices. It is because of the lack of any sympathy or understanding of India and its culture that people like Max Muller – whose sole motivation was to malign Indian culture and convince the Indians to give up their old beliefs and religion, and thus pave the way for Christian conversion – are considered to be Vedic scholars and great benefactors of Indian culture, and their books, wilfully written to present a distorted view of Indian history, are still being taught and studied. Now that his letters are in public domain, there remains no doubt that, though he was not a missionary in the literal sense, Max Muller’s work was infused with the Christian missionary spirit. Here is some evidence from the book “Max Muller: A Secular Christian Missionary and Distorter of the Veda” by K.V. Paliwal, published by the Hindu Writers Forum, New Delhi, 2006. Max Muller’s translation of the Veda was highly motivated but he never openly expressed it except in intimate private letters such as the one written to his wife in December 1866, “I hope I shall finish that work, and I feel convinced, though I shall not live to see it, that this edition of mine and the translation of the Veda will hereafter tell to a great extent on the fate of India, and on the growth of millions of souls in that country. It is the root of their religion, and to show them what that root is, I feel sure, is the only way of uprooting all that has sprung up from it during the last three thousand Years.” (p. 26)

Another letter written by Max Muller ten years before the above leaves no doubt about his Christian missionary motives. Writing to Mr. Bunsen on 25.8.1856, he says, “….After the last annexation the territorial conquest of India ceases – what follows next is the struggle in the realm of religion and of spirit, in which, of course, centre the interests of the nations. India is much riper for Christianity than Rome or Greece were at the time of St. Paul….I should like to live for ten years quite quietly and learn the language, try to make friends, and then see whether I was fit to take part in the work, by means of which the old mischief of Indian priestcraft could be overthrown and the way opened for the entrance of simple Christian teaching, that entrance which this teaching finds into every human heart, which is free from the ensnaring powers of priests and from the obscuring influence of philosophers. Whatever finds root in India soon overshadows the whole of Asia, and nowhere could the vital power of Christianity more gloriously realize itself than if the world saw it spring up there for a second time, in very different form than in the West, but still essentially the same.” (p. 20-21)

Qs. What is the rationale behind idol worship?

Ans. The Mother, speaking on this issue, had said, “All this is based on the old idea that whatever the image – which we disdainfully call an ‘idol’ – whatever the external form of the deity may be, the presence of the thing represented is always there. And there is always someone – whether priest or initiate, sadhu or sannyasi – someone who has the power and (usually this is the priest’s work) who draws the Force and the Presence down into it. And it’s true, it’s quite real – the Force and the Presence are THERE; and this (not the form in wood or stone or metal) is what is worshipped: this Presence.

Europeans don’t have the inner sense at all. To them, everything is like this (gesture), a surface – not even that, a film on the surface. And they can’t feel anything behind. But it’s an absolutely real fact that the Presence is there – I guarantee it. People have given me statuettes of various gods, little things in metal, wood or ivory; and as soon as I take one in my hand, the god is there. I have a Ganesh (I have been given several) and if I take it in my hand and look at it for a moment, he’s there.... I have always felt what’s behind, the presences behind.” (Mother’s Agenda 1961, Vol. 2, p. 192-93) ‡

(iii) Lack of All Moral Worth and Ethical Substance

“Incidentally, to support this charge of irrationalism and its companion charge of Paganism, we find a third and more damaging count brought against us and our religious culture, an alleged want of all moral worth and ethical substance. There is now an increasing perception, even in Europe, that reason is not the last word of human mind, not quite the one and only sovereign way to truth and certainly not the sole arbiter of religious and spiritual truth. The accusation of paganism too does not settle the question, since plenty of cultivated minds are well able to see that there were many great, true and beautiful things in the ancient religions that were lumped together by Christian ignorance under that inappropriate nickname. Nor has the world been entirely a gainer by losing these high ancient forms and motives. But whatever the actual practice of men, – and in this respect the normal human being is a singular mixture of the sincere but quite ineffective, the just respectable, would-be ethical man and the self-deceiving or semi-hypocritical Pharisee, – one can always appeal with force to a moralistic prejudice. All religions raise high the flag of morality and, whether religious or secular-minded, all but the antinomian, the rebel and the cynic, profess to follow or at least to admit that standard in their lives. This accusation is therefore about the most prejudicial charge that can be brought against any religion. The self-constituted prosecuting judge whose diatribe we are examining brings it without scruple and without measure. He has discovered that Hinduism is not an ennobling or even a morally helpful religion; if it has talked much of righteousness, it has never claimed moral teaching as one of its functions. A religion that can talk much of righteousness without performing the function of moral teaching, sounds rather like a square which can make no claim to be a quadrilateral; but let that pass. If the Hindu is comparatively free from the grosser Western vices, – as yet only, and only until he enters “the pale of civilisation” by adopting Christianity or otherwise, – it is not because there is any ethical strain in his character; it is because these vices do not come his way. His social system founded on the barbarous idea of the Dharma, of the divine and the human, the universal and the individual, the ethical and the social law, and supported on it at every point, has stupidly neglected to supply him with the opportunities of departing from it so liberally provided by Western civilisation! And yet the whole character of Hinduism, which is the character of the people, indicates, we are calmly told, a melancholy proclivity towards whatever is monstrous and unwholesome!”19

“The rites, ceremonies, system of cult and worship of Hinduism can only be understood if we remember its fundamental character. It is in the first place a non-dogmatic inclusive religion and would have taken even Islam and Christianity into itself, if they had tolerated the process. All that it has met on its way it has taken into itself, content if it could put its forms into some valid relation with the truth of the supraphysical worlds and the truth of the Infinite. Again it has always known in its heart that religion, if it is to be a reality for the mass of men and not only for a few saints and thinkers, must address its appeal to the whole of our being, not only to the suprarational and the rational parts, but to all the others. The imagination, the emotions, the aesthetic sense, even the very instincts of the half subconscient parts must be taken into the influence. Religion must lead man towards the suprarational, the spiritual truth and it must take the aid of the illumined reason on the way, but it cannot afford to neglect to call Godwards the rest of our complex nature. And it must take too each man where he stands and spiritualise him through what he can feel and not at once force on him something which he cannot yet grasp as a true and living power. That is the sense and aim of all those parts of Hinduism which are specially stigmatised as irrational or antirational by the positivist intelligence. But the European mind has failed to understand this plain necessity or has despised it. It insists on “purifying” religion, by the reason and not by the spirit, on “reforming” it, by the reason and not by the spirit. And we have seen what were the results of this kind of purification and reformation in Europe. The infallible outcome of that ignorant doctoring has been first to impoverish and then slowly to kill religion; the patient has fallen a victim to the treatment, while he might well have survived the disease!

The accusation of a want of ethical content is almost monstrously false, – it is the direct opposite of the truth; but we must look for its explanation in some kind of characteristic misunderstanding; for it is not new. Hindu thought and literature might almost be accused of a tyrannously pervading ethical obsession; everywhere the ethical note recurs. The idea of the Dharma is, next to the idea of the Infinite, its major chord; Dharma, next to spirit, is its foundation of life. There is no ethical idea which it has not stressed, put in its most ideal and imperative form, enforced by teaching, injunction, parable, artistic creation, formative examples. Truth, honour, loyalty, fidelity, courage, chastity, love, long-suffering, self-sacrifice, harmlessness, forgiveness, compassion, benevolence, beneficence are its common themes, are in its view the very stuff of a right human life, the essence of man’s dharma. Buddhism with its high and noble ethics, Jainism with its austere ideal of self-conquest, Hinduism with its magnificent examples of all sides of the Dharma are not inferior in ethical teaching and practice to any religion or system, but rather take the highest rank and have had the strongest effective force. For the practice of these virtues in older times there is abundant internal and foreign evidence.”20

“Morality is for the Western mind mostly a thing of outward conduct; but conduct for the Indian mind is only one means of expression and sign of a soul-state. Hinduism only incidentally strings together a number of commandments for observance, a table of moral laws; more deeply it enjoins a spiritual or ethical purity of the mind with action as one outward index. It says strongly enough, almost too strongly, ‘Thou shouldst not kill,’ but insists more firmly on the injunction, ‘Thou shalt not hate, thou shalt not yield to greed, anger or malice,’ for these are the roots of killing. And Hinduism admits relative standards, a wisdom too hard for the European intelligence. Non-injuring is the very highest of its laws, ahiṁsā paramo dharmaḥ; still it does not lay it down as a physical rule for the warrior, but insistently demands from him mercy, chivalry, respect for the non-belligerent, the weak, the unarmed, the vanquished, the prisoner, the wounded, the fugitive, and so escapes the unpracticality of a too absolutist rule for all life. A misunderstanding of this inwardness and this wise relativity is perhaps responsible for much misrepresentation. The Western ethicist likes to have a high standard as a counsel of perfection and is not too much concerned if it is honoured more by the breach than by the observance; Indian ethics puts up an equally high and often higher standard; but less concerned with high professions than with truth of life, it admits stages of progress and in the lower stages is satisfied if it can moralise as much as possible those who are not yet capable of the highest ethical concepts and practice.

All these criticisms of Hinduism are therefore either false in fact or invalid in their very nature.”21

‡ Sri Aurobindo has aptly answered here the charge of a lack of all moral worth and ethical substance levied against the Indian culture. Some of the aspects implicit in the charge and the response need to be pondered over so that we may get a still better perspective on the whole issue. Firstly, very often morality and ethics are confused with true spirituality, while in reality, they have nothing much to do with it. At best, their utility is to curb the animalistic and unbridled vital propensities in man so that, instead of remaining grossly indulgent, he may rise above them a little. Also, morality, ethics, or some other virtues cannot be cultivated by beautiful discourses, for the vital in a man is a despot which is not in the habit of obeying any mental injunctions. Therefore, the chief aim of our education system should be to help the growing soul in acquiring some control over this lawless part and assist in the integral development of the whole being in conformity with its deepest self. But as things stand at present, the education system seems to be doing just the very opposite of what is expected of it. It only inflates the vital tendencies and, as a result, the vital gets swelled up at the expense of the other parts of our being and one becomes a slave of one’s lower appetites for the rest of one’s life. Regarding the role of moral training in education Sri Aurobindo says, “You can impose a certain discipline on children, dress them into a certain mould, lash them into a desired path, but unless you can get their hearts and natures on your side, the conformity to this imposed rule becomes a hypocritical and heartless, a conventional, often a cowardly compliance. This is what is done in Europe, and it leads to that remarkable phenomenon known as the sowing of wild oats as soon as the yoke of discipline at school and at home is removed, and to the social hypocrisy which is so large a feature of European life. Only what the man admires and accepts, becomes part of himself; the rest is a mask. He conforms to the discipline of society as he conformed to the moral routine of home and school, but considers himself at liberty to guide his real life, inner and private, according to his own likings and passions. ...The old Indian system of the guru commanding by his knowledge and sanctity the implicit obedience, perfect admiration, reverent emulation of the student was a far superior method of moral discipline.”(CWSA 1, 389-90) It should now become quite clear from these words of Sri Aurobindo that a living example is much more effective for moral training than any mental teachings. Truly speaking, it is only in and by the spiritual atmosphere and its influence that any real development of true virtues can take place.

Thus, the entire nation was surrounded by countless shining examples of great personalities with high moral virtues, such as self-sacrifice, long-suffering, chivalry, beneficence, compassion, and many-many others, who inspired the whole race of the time and continue to have a profound impact on the life and mentality of the people even to this day. Gandhiji mentions in his biography how he was so deeply moved and influenced by the character of King Harishchandra that he decided to practice it and try never to swerve from the path of truth as he understood it. The characters of Sri Rama, Devi Sita, and of other such high ones continue to inspire the whole country even to this day. All these high ideals and their uplifting influence greatly help both individuals and collectivities to rise above their grosser physical and vital propensities. But an example, however lofty, has its limitations. A person may feel much attracted to an example, be highly inspired by it, may even try to follow and grow into its likeness, but if the necessary dynamism is wanting, then it is quite unlikely that his fascination or effort will amount to much. Not only that, example in itself is rarely sufficient for any spiritual or deeper cultivation. Therefore, an example, though it may and does often have a great importance, is not as powerful and effective as spiritual influence. For, not only does it inspire a person to overcome his lower appetites and rise higher, it even gives him the necessary help to achieve it. Spiritual influence doesn’t stop at merely pointing to the goal, but it takes a person by the hand towards it. Indian culture had a deep understanding of the supreme importance of such forces in the cultivation of moral values. Any discerning eye can see in the ancient Indian literature, especially the epic literature, how great an insistence was laid upon building a truly sound character, and the result was that even the common people would not even think of doing anything contrary to the rightful conduct, dharma. The heights of cultivation to which each virtue has been taken in this culture is to be seen nowhere else.

As regarding morality and ethics, it is only in the light of a spiritual or deeper consciousness that one can have a true sense of their application. By itself, no moral standard, rule, principle or sacred scripture can help one arrive at the right choice at any point of time. There can truly be no fixed outer standards for morality, altruism, benevolence, love, and other such qualities. This is the reason why in India moral ideals and virtues have always been kept under a higher and multi-layered and plastic law, dharma – which varied according to Desha (Place), Kala (Time) and Patra (Person). For example, it is only the dharma that can help one determine whether in the given circumstances forgiveness may be the right movement or else a show of valour and resistance and punishment or something in between may be needed. Even the qualities that at the mental level seem to be contradictory, such as humility and prowess, kindness and severity, and so on can find their rightful reconciliation in the dharma. If the mental ideals are not kept under the yoke of dharma, they always tend towards exclusiveness. A flagrant example of this can be found in one of the episodes of Mahabharata where even in the presence of the greatest of the heroes of the time like Bhisma, Drona, and others, an attempt so wrong as to try to insult and disrobe Draupadi could be made, and being fettered to their narrow one-sided mental ideals all those elders and heroes sat as silent spectators of such a disgrace. This is the reason why Bhishma Pitamaha, Yudhisthira, and countless other such great, virtuous and righteous people, can at best be regarded as ethical personalities. It is only Lord Sri Krishna, not bound by any moral laws, who remains our true ideal. However unethical and immoral his acts and pastimes may appear to the one-sided modern intellect but still all our scriptures call him the Unfallen, the Infallible, the Sinless. This provides us some perspective of the Indian view about the truth or morality and ethics and their place in man’s life.

Qs. Sri Aurobindo here makes a remark about Hindu religion that it is “a non-dogmatic inclusive religion and would have taken even Islam and Christianity into itself, if they had tolerated the process”, then what does he mean by ‘if they had tolerated the process’?

Ans. As we have discussed earlier that all this many-sided and many-staged manifestation is as though only a partial manifestation of, and originated from, the Supreme Divine herself/himself. Each particular manifestation in it has its own special truth and place which it alone can manifest and occupy. Therefore, in the Indian culture not only the human beings, but even the creatures and the material objects were regarded as forms and expressions of that one Supreme Divine and were met in that spirit. Having a deep experience and perception of that Absolute Being, the Sanatana Dharma not only vindicated all possible ways for each of these phenomenal expressions – which are essentially the expressions of that Absolute Being alone – to get back to their source, but even provided a whole wide system for their swiftest arrival. In this endeavour it accepted not only the superconscient but even the half-conscient and inconscient parts of our being and tried to turn them all towards the Divine. In this Godward pursuit it could ill-afford to shut itself from any possible approach, therefore all philosophies, systems of yoga, experiences, realisations, etc. were admitted as the various ways or paths to the goal, and along with it, there was infinite room for still newer approaches to come. It is due to this large catholicity of this culture that even seemingly contradictory philosophies, systems of spiritual practices, tantra, and various others, have always flourished here in harmony. This spirit of all-inclusiveness can be glimpsed in the well-known formula of ‘Vasudhaiva Kutumbakam’, which means that ‘the whole world is one family.’ Along with this all-inclusiveness, there has always been another perception, accepted universally, that no philosophy or system, however high or wide, can ever confine or completely define the Divine, and any revelation, however comprehensively expressive of the truth, can at best be regarded as an expression of one of the infinite attributes of the Divine, but cannot claim itself to be the only and sovereign truth. Even Islam and Christianity would have been easily taken in into the all-inclusive order of Sanatana Dharma if, regarding themselves as one of the numerous other possible ways of moving towards the Divine, they could have accepted to live in harmony with the others. But not only did they claim themselves to be the sole approaches to the Divine but, in their sharply exclusive spirit, went even so far as to try to impose themselves forcibly and violently on others. This spirit of intolerance being contrary to the all-inclusive spirit of the Veda, was entirely alien to the spirit of Sanatana Dharma, and for this reason, these religions remain rejected as some foreign element. According to Sri Aurobindo, only that which conforms with the synthetic, acquisitive, all-inclusive spirit of the Veda, can endure in the Indian culture. ‡

(iv) Lack of Power and Vitality in Indian Culture

A most common charge levied against the Indian culture is that it “..depresses the vital force, paralyses the will, gives no great or vigorous power, no high incentive, no fortifying and ennobling motive to human life.”22

Here the important question is that, “Apart from its transcendental aims, has it any pragmatic, non-ascetic, dynamic value, any power for expansion of life and for the right control of life? This is a question of central importance. For if it has nothing of this kind to give us, then whatever its other cultural greatness, it cannot live. It becomes an abnormal cis-Himalayan hot-house splendour which could subsist in its peninsular seclusion, but must perish in the keen and arduous air of the modern struggle of life. No anti-vital culture can survive. A too intellectual or too ethereal civilisation void of strong vital stimulus and motive must languish for want of sap and blood. A culture to be permanently and completely serviceable to man must give him something more than some kind of rare transcendental uprush towards an exceeding of all earthly life-values. It must do more even than adorn with a great curiosity of knowledge, science and philosophic enquiry or a rich light and blaze of art, poetry and architecture the long stability and orderly well-being of an old, ripe and humane society. All this Indian culture did in the past to a noble purpose. But it must satisfy too the tests of a progressive Life-power. There must be some inspiration for the terrestrial endeavour of man, an object, a stimulus, a force for development and a will to live. Whether or not our end is silence and Nirvana, a spiritual cessation or a material death, this is certain that the world itself is a mighty labour of a vast Life-Spirit and man the present doubtful crown on earth and the struggling but still unsuccessful present hero and protagonist of its endeavour or its drama. A great human culture must see this truth in some fullness; it must impart some conscious and ideal power of self-effectuation to this upward effort. It is not enough to found a stable base for life, not enough to adorn it, not enough to shoot up sublimely to summits beyond it; the greatness and growth of the race on earth must be our equal care. To miss this great intermediate reality is a capital imperfection and in itself a seal of failure.

Our critics will have it that the whole body of Indian culture bears the stamp of just such a failure. The Western impression has been that Hinduism is an entirely metaphysical and other-worldly system dreaming of things beyond, oblivious of the now and here: a depressing sense of the unreality of life or an intoxication of the Infinite turns it away from any nobility, vitality and greatness of human aspiration and the earth’s labour. Its philosophy may be sublime, its religious spirit fervent, its ancient social system strong, symmetrical and stable, its literature and its art good in their own way, but the salt of life is absent, the breath of will-power, the force of a living endeavour. This new journalistic Apollo, our Archer who is out to cleave with his arrows the python coils of Indian barbarism, abounds in outcries in this sense. But, if that is so, evidently India can have done nothing great, contributed no invigorating power to human life, produced no men of mighty will, no potent personalities, no strong significant human lives, no vital human figures in art and poetry, no significant architecture and sculpture. And that is what our devil’s advocate tells us in graphic phrases. He tells us that there is in this religion and philosophy a general undervaluing of life and endeavour. Life is conceived as a shoreless expanse in which generations rise and fall as helplessly and purposelessly as waves in mid-ocean; the individual is everywhere dwarfed and depreciated; one solitary great character, Gautama Buddha, who ‘perhaps never existed,’ is India’s sole contribution to the world’s pantheon, or for the rest a pale featureless Asoka. The characters of drama and poetry are lifeless exaggerations or puppets of supernatural powers; the art is empty of reality; the whole history of the civilisation makes a drab, effete, melancholy picture. There is no power of life in this religion and this philosophy, there is no breath of life in this history, there is no colour of life in this art and poetry; that is the blank result of Indian culture. Whoever has seen at first hand and felt the literature, followed the history, studied the civilisation of India, can see that this is a bitter misrepresentation, a violent caricature, an absurd falsehood. But it is an extreme and unscrupulous way of putting an impression often given to the European mind and, as before, we must see why different eyes see the same object in such different colours. It is the same primary misunderstanding that is at the root. India has lived and lived richly, splendidly, greatly, but with a different will in life from Europe. The idea and plan of her life have been peculiar to her temperament, original and unique. Her values are not easy to seize for an outsider and her highest things are easily open to hostile misrepresentation by the ignorant, precisely because they are too high for the normal untrained mind and apt to shoot beyond its limits.”23

In the next section we shall consider what lies at the root of the rationalistic misunderstanding of India and its culture – the stark difference between the Indian and the European conceptions of life and, as a result, the inability of the latter to understand the former’s masterful dealings with life.

[3]	A huge, powerful, and overwhelming force. – Ed.

[4]	A female Hindu dancer, especially one at a southern Indian temple. – Ed.

[5]	Kamadhenu – the sacred Cow in Hindu mythology. Her other names include Sabala (the Spotted One) and Kapila (the Red One). – Ed.

A. The Original Conception of Life – the European and the Indian

“The European conception of life is a thing with which we in India are now very familiar, because our present thought and effort are obscured with its shadow when they are not filled with its presence. For we have been trying hard to assimilate something of it, even to shape ourselves and especially our political, economic and outward conduct into some imitation of its forms and rhythms. The European idea is the conception of a Force that manifests itself in the material universe and a Life in it of which man is almost the only discoverable meaning. This anthropocentric view of things has not been altered by the recent stress of Science on the vast blank inanities of an inconscient mechanical Nature. And in man, thus unique in the inert drift of Nature, the whole effort of Life is to arrive at some light and harmony of the understanding and ordering reason, some efficient rational power, adorning beauty, strong utility, vital enjoyment, economic welfare. The free power of the individual ego, the organised will of the corporate ego, these are the great needed forces. The development of individual personality and an organised efficient national life are the two things that matter in the European ideal. These two powers have grown, striven, run riot at times, and the restless and often violent vividness of the historic stir and the literary and artistic vivacity of Europe are due to their powerful colours. The enjoyment of life and force, the gallop of egoistic passion and vital satisfaction are a loud and insistent strain, a constant high-voiced motive. Against them is another opposite effort, the endeavour to govern life by reason, science, ethics, art; a restraining and harmonising utility is here the foremost motive. At different times different powers have taken the lead. Christian religiosity too has come in and added new tones, modified some tendencies, deepened others. Each age and period has increased the wealth of contributory lines and forces and helped the complexity and largeness of the total conception. At present the sense of the corporate life dominates and it is served by the idea of a great intellectual and material progress, an ameliorated political and social state governed by science. There is an ideal of intelligent utility, liberty and equality or else an ideal of stringent organisation and efficiency and a perfectly mobilised, carefully marshalled uniting of forces in a ceaseless pull towards the general welfare. This endeavour of Europe has become terribly outward and mechanical in its appearance; but some renewed power of a more humanistic idea is trying to beat its way in again and man may perhaps before long refuse to be tied on the wheel of his own triumphant machinery and conquered by his apparatus. At any rate we need not lay too much emphasis on what may be a passing phase. The broad permanent European conception of life remains and it is in its own limits a great and invigorating conception, – imperfect, narrow at the top, shut in under a heavy lid, poor in its horizons, too much of the soil, but still with a sense in it that is strenuous and noble.”25

‡ This succinct account of the European conception of life provides a deep insight into the essential spirit of the European culture and the forms it used for its expression. If we fail to get a deeper view of even the spirit of the European conception, with which we are overwhelmed with at present, then how can we expect to delve deeper into the heart of the Indian conception of life, which is far more profound and sublime. Most of our post-independence leaders, educated and groomed under the European system of education, were so influenced by that culture and its values that their whole effort was to blindly adopt not only the Western education system but the whole of their constitutional, judicial, legal and administrative system. At present we are mesmerized by the European conception of life to such an extent that we are trying to blindly imitate it in every detail, whether it be its way of living, its ethics, its commerce, economics, medicine, or all the various other systems developed by it for conducting public or private life. Therefore, it is important to be very familiar with this conception and also its likely consequences. Now, what is, essentially, the European conception of life?

First of all, the European view conceives of a ‘Force’ behind everything, which can be called ‘Nature’ or ‘Law’, that governs and arranges all that there is. It is the ever deeper secrets of this ‘Force’ that all the various branches of physical science have been trying to discover. This conception holds Matter, with its own law and mechanism, to be the fundamental basis of all things – material or subtle – in this universe. But the study even of the most subtle elements and energies of material nature and their working has remained – directly or implicitly – focused on man, considering him to be predominantly a physical being. Naturally, the focus has been on an increasingly efficient arrangement for the satisfaction of man’s outer self. Sri Aurobindo has shown clearly how even when dealing with some subjective elements of human psychology, the materialistic approach curbs the flight of human imagination and perception and fails to go beyond a point. Under such a materialistic conception, the society is guided mostly by the gospel of utilitarianism and the whole system – political, economic, educational, social, medical, etc. – is geared towards an increasing fulfilment of the lower propensities of the physical and the vital parts of man. Presupposing matter to be the sole basis of everything, physical science firmly believes that its ever deeper probe into the laws of matter would one day enable it to explain even the most subtle phenomena in the working of this physical world. To this materialistic scientific view, the physical alone is the fundamental basis of the movements of desire, fear, lust, etc., or those others related to our deeper psychology – what we call the deeper feelings, aspirations, intuitions, etc. – or the various other special powers, or faculties in art, literature, music, etc. To it, even a genius is ultimately the result of a particular physiological and cerebral constitution. Therefore, if the same cellular and cerebral arrangement, along with the particular chemical compositions could be replicated, then even a Shakespeare or a Gautama Buddha or any other such personality of the highest order, could be reproduced, for there is nothing in this physical nature which is not composed of material (or subtle material) constituents. The breakthroughs in the field of genetics have made scientists firmly believe that in the foreseeable future, science would be able to produce children with not only predetermined physical characteristics but even desired psychological, mental, emotional, or other subjective traits. The phenomena of supernatural, miraculous, occult, or divine are to it merely the working of some subtle and involved processes of material energy. It hopes that once it discovers those processes it would be in a position to explain even such phenomena and put them to its use. Therefore, it firmly holds that all the so-called divine visions, planes of consciousness, the various states supposed to be experienced in deep trance, or even the most intense spiritual experiences are merely results of certain cerebral patterns and chemical balances of the brain. The Indian culture starts from the exact opposite end. It knows that the true cause of even a physical structure is to be found in the original idea of the one who conceived of that structure, and not in the materials used or the human agencies involved in the construction, for these could at best serve only as means for the fulfilment of the original idea and can be altered or even dispensed with. Likewise, the destination of a person cannot be determined by the available means of transport, on the contrary, a person is free to determine and use the means needed to reach the destination. Thus, in the final analysis, the fundamental cause of this terrestrial manifestation is the Will of the Divine Mother, perceived more clearly in the higher regions, which alone determines the outlines and forms and whatever else is needed for its self-expression. Therefore, only by becoming more and more conscious of the working of that Divine Will can we have some sense of the true cause of things, otherwise, we are likely to mistake the process of manifestation – and that too in a very superficial way – for the true cause.

In an externalised outlook of life, it is quite natural that prominence is given to the surface physical and vital existence, due to which, the mind, even though a power higher in scale than the vital and the physical, remains largely confined to the search for more and more efficient arrangements for the satisfaction of these parts. Thus the whole effort, at large, is geared towards making the most efficient arrangements for the sense gratifications of both the individual and the society. In this arrangement, the free power of the individual ego and the organised will of the collective ego are the two great determining forces that have at times even come into a visible confrontation and conflict with each other. One of them holds that the individual should have the full freedom to pursue his own egoistic perfection, for only by the growth of the individual can the society and country grow. Therefore, the duty of a nation should be to make provision for every individual to enable him to get the utmost opportunity for his fulfilment. The other view holds the collective ego to be of paramount importance and the duty and the value of an individual lies in becoming a faithful instrument of the collective unit or a cell of the national body. History testifies how at different times different ideologies have taken the lead and have been instrumental in giving rise to various ‘isms’, such as, capitalism, socialism, communism, etc., which have even run riot at times, for none of these ideals, which are all partial in themselves, can ever truly serve as a sound basis for any true and lasting organisation. It is only in the depths of our being that a sound basis can be found for any true organisation. There have been various other powers and faculties of human nature, such as life, aesthetics, reason, ethics, etc., that have at times come in and contributed new tones and elements to the complexity and largeness of the conception of life and its practical implementation. These factors give a nation its own peculiar character. It is for this reason that even though fundamentally starting from the same materialistic conception of existence, all the European nations have each their unique identity. Each has, to however subtle or small a degree, its own peculiarity of character, thought, and other subjective traits which are reflected in its art, literature, music, lifestyle, behavioral pattern, etc. It is this unique identity of a nation among the community of other nations that gives its people a sense of superiority and pride for their own nation and its distinctive features. This sense gives rise to the spirit of nationalism which has time and again played an important role in the development of nations. For India also, the movement towards a strong nationalism is the immediate practical need of the country, for only then would it truly be able to move towards the fulfilment of its divinely ordained mission. But, as Sri Aurobindo states, the nationalism of India would not be of the narrow kind concentrated solely on the fulfilment of its own self-interests but would be moved by the all-embracing spirit of the Sanatana Dharma and, therefore, truly beneficial to the whole human race.

At present, the main motive force that drives humanity at large and in detail is the acute and shortsighted gospel of utilitarianism which has made man more and more self-centered, the consequences of which can be clearly seen in the life of individuals and societies. Not only has the touch of this utilitarian spirit resulted in the increasing deterioration of the quality of goods and services, but even worse, it has given rise to serious mental and psychological afflictions such as loneliness, desolation, depression, dissatisfaction, uncertainty, distrust, etc. in the society. Ever since the triple ideal of Liberty, Equality and Fraternity has been brought to the forefront of the European consciousness by the French Revolution, there has been an ongoing effort to follow and establish, with whatever outer resources at hand, either of the two ideals, Liberty and Equality, ignoring the fact that Fraternity is the only base on which the other two can securely stand. It is because of the absence of the true spirit of this godhead, which exists only in the soul and is alien to an egoistic consciousness, that all attempts steeped in the spirit of Western culture and depending on taking either equality or liberty as their starting point or base have failed to establish the triple-godhead. This is a brief account of the European conception of life which, in its own limits, is undoubtedly a powerful and invigorating conception that seems at present to have brought almost everyone under its sway. At present, the visibly impressive march of the advances in science and technology and their deep penetration into almost every walk of life seems to have been successful in hypnotising not only the whole world at large but even those ancient races that possessed a deeper conception of life than the European. ‡

“The Indian conception of life starts from a deeper centre and moves on less external lines to a very different objective. The peculiarity of the Indian eye of thought is that it looks through the form, looks even through the force, and searches for the spirit in things everywhere. The peculiarity of the Indian will in life is that it feels itself to be unfulfilled, not in touch with perfection, not permanently justified in any intermediate satisfaction if it has not found and does not live in the truth of the spirit. The Indian idea of the world, of Nature and of existence is not physical, but psychological and spiritual. Spirit, soul, consciousness are not only greater than inert matter and inconscient force, but they precede and originate these lesser things. All force is power or means of a secret spirit; the Force that sustains the world is a conscious Will and Nature is its machinery of executive power. Matter is the body or field of a consciousness hidden within it, the material universe a form and movement of the Spirit. Man himself is not a life and mind born of Matter and eternally subject to physical Nature, but a spirit that uses life and body. It is an understanding faith in this conception of existence, it is the attempt to live it out, it is the science and practice of this high endeavour, and it is the aspiration to break out in the end from this mind bound to life and matter into a greater spiritual consciousness that is the innermost sense of Indian culture. It is this that constitutes the much-talked-of Indian spirituality. It is evidently very remote from the dominant European idea; it is different even from the form given by Europe to the Christian conception of life. But it does not mean at all that Indian culture concedes no reality to life, follows no material or vital aims and satisfactions or cares to do nothing for our actual human existence. It cannot truly be contended that a conception of this kind can give no powerful and inspiring motive to the human effort of man. Certainly, in this view, matter, mind, life, reason, form are only powers of the spirit and valuable not for their own sake, but because of the Spirit within them. Ātmārtham, they exist for the sake of the Self, says the Upanishad, and this is certainly the Indian attitude to these things. But that does not depreciate them or deprive them of their value; on the contrary it increases a hundredfold their significance. Form and body immensely increase in importance if they are felt to be instinct with the life of the Spirit and are conceived as a support for the rhythm of its workings. And human life was in ancient Indian thought no vile and unworthy existence; it is the greatest thing known to us, it is desired, the Purana boldly says, even by the gods in heaven. The deepening and raising of the richest or the most potent energies of our minds, our hearts, our life-power, our bodies are all means by which the spirit can proceed to self-discovery and the return to its own infinite freedom and power.”26

“The dignity given to human existence by the Vedantic thought and by the thought of the classical ages of Indian culture exceeded anything conceived by the Western idea of humanity. Man in the West has always been only an ephemeral creature of Nature or a soul manufactured at birth by an arbitrary breath of the whimsical Creator and set under impossible conditions to get salvation, but far more likely to be thrown away into the burning refuse-heap of Hell as a hopeless failure. At best he is exalted by a reasoning mind and will and an effort to be better than God or Nature made him. Far more ennobling, inspiring, filled with the motive-force of a great idea is the conception placed before us by Indian culture. Man in the Indian idea is a spirit veiled in the works of energy, moving to self-discovery, capable of Godhead. He is a soul that is growing through Nature to conscious self-hood; he is a divinity and an eternal existence; he is an ever-flowing wave of the God-ocean, an inextinguishable spark of the supreme Fire. Even, he is in his uttermost reality identical with the ineffable Transcendence from which he came and greater than the godheads whom he worships. The natural half-animal creature that for a while he seems to be is not at all his whole being and is not in any way his real being. His inmost reality is the divine Self or at least one dynamic eternal portion of it, and to find that and exceed his outward, apparent, natural self is the greatness of which he alone of terrestrial beings is capable. He has the spiritual capacity to pass to a supreme and extraordinary pitch of manhood and that is the first aim which is proposed to him by Indian culture. Living no more in the first crude type of an undeveloped humanity to which most men still belong, na yathā prākṛto janaḥ, he can even become a free perfected semi-divine man, mukta, siddha. But he can do more; released into the cosmic consciousness, his spirit can become one with God, one self with the Spirit of the universe or rise into a Light and Vastness that transcends the universe; his nature can become one dynamic power with universal Nature or one Light with a transcendental Gnosis. To be shut up for ever in his ego is not his ultimate perfection; he can become a universal soul, one with the supreme Unity, one with others, one with all beings. This is the high sense and power concealed in his humanity that he can aspire to this perfection and transcendence. And he can arrive at it through any or all of his natural powers if they will accept release, through his mind and reason and thought and their illuminations, through his heart and its unlimited power of love and sympathy, through his will and its dynamic drive towards mastery and right action, through his ethical nature and its hunger for the universal Good, through his aesthetic sense and its seekings after delight and beauty or through his inner soul and its power of absolute spiritual calm, wideness, joy and peace.

This is the sense of that spiritual liberation and perfection of which Indian thought and inner discipline have been full since the earliest Vedic times. However high and arduous this aim may be, it has always seemed to it possible and even in a way near and normal, once spiritual realisation has discovered its path. The positivist Western mind finds it difficult to give this conception the rank of a living and intelligible idea. The status of the siddha, bhāgavata, mukta appears to it a baseless chimera. It seems to its Christian associations a blasphemy against the solitary greatness of God, before whom man is only a grovelling worm, to its fierce attachment to the normal ego a negation of personality and a repellent menace, to its earthbound rationalism a dream, a self-hypnotic hallucination or a deluding mania. And yet in ancient Europe the Stoics, Platonists, Pythagoreans had made some approach to this aspiration, and even afterwards, a few rare souls have envisaged or pursued it through occult ways. And now it is again beginning to percolate into the Western imagination, but less as a dynamic life-motive than in poetry and in certain aspects of general thought or through movements like Theosophy that draw from ancient and oriental sources. Science and philosophy and religion still regard it with scorn as an illusion, with indifference as a dream or with condemnation as a heathen arrogance. It is the distinction of Indian culture to have seized on this great dynamic hope, to have kept it a living and practicable thing and to have searched out all the possible paths to this spiritual way of perfect existence. Indian thought has made this great thing the common highest aim and universal spiritual destiny of the soul that is in every human creature.”27

B. The High Value and Soundness of the Indian Conception of Life

The value of the Indian conception of life must depend on the power and effectivity with which it connects its high conception and the distant perfection aimed at with man’s normal living and present every day nature. “Put over against the latter without any connection or any gradations that lead up to it and make it possible, it would either be a high unattainable ideal or the detached remote passion of a few exceptional spirits. Or even it would discourage the springs of our natural life by the too great contrast between this spiritual being and our own poor imperfect nature. Something of the kind has happened in later times; the current Western impression about the exaggerated asceticism and other-worldliness of Indian religion and philosophy is founded on the growing gulf created by a later thought between man’s spiritual possibilities and his terrestrial status. But we must not be misled by extreme tendencies or the overemphasis put upon them in a period of decline. If we would get at the real meaning of the Indian idea of life, we must go back to its best times. And we must not look at this or that school of philosophy or at some side of it as the whole of Indian thought; the totality of the ancient philosophical thinking, religion, literature, art, society must be our ground of enquiry. The Indian conception in its early soundness made no such mistake as to imagine that this great thing can or even ought to be done by some violent, intolerant, immediate leap from one pole of existence to its opposite. Even the most extreme philosophies do not go so far. The workings of the Spirit in the universe were a reality to one side of the Indian mind, to another only a half reality, a self-descriptive Lila or illusory Maya. To the one the world was an action of the Infinite Energy, Shakti, to the other a figment of some secondary paradoxical consciousness in the Eternal, Maya: but life as an intermediate reality was never denied by any school of Indian thinking. Indian thought recognised that the normal life of man has to be passed through with a conscientious endeavour to fulfil its purpose: its powers must be developed with knowledge; its forms must be perused, interpreted and fathomed; its values must be worked out, possessed and lived; its enjoyments must be fully taken on their own level. Only afterwards can we go on to self-existence or a supra-existence. The spiritual perfection which opens before man is the crown of a long, patient, millennial outflowering of the spirit in life and nature. This belief in a gradual spiritual progress and evolution here is indeed the secret of the almost universal Indian acceptance of the truth of reincarnation. It is only by millions of lives in inferior forms that the secret soul in the universe, conscious even in the inconscient, cetano acetaneṣu, has arrived at humanity: it is only by hundreds or thousands, perhaps even millions of human lives that man can grow into his divine self-existence. Every life is a step which he can take backward or forward; his action in life, his will in life, his thought and knowledge by which he governs and directs his life, determine what he is yet to be from the earliest stages to the last transcendence. Yathā karma yathā śrutam.

This belief in a gradual soul evolution with a final perfection or divine transcendence and human life as its first direct means and often repeated opportunity, is the pivot of the Indian conception of existence. This gives to our life the figure of an ascent in spirals or circles; and the long period of the ascent has to be filled in with human knowledge and human action and human experience. There is room within it for all terrestrial aims, activities and aspirations; there is place in the ascent for all types of human character and nature. For the spirit in the world assumes hundreds of forms and follows many tendencies and gives many shapes to his play or līlā. All are part of the total mass of our necessary experience; each has its justification, each has its natural or true law and reason of being, each has its utility in the play and the process. The claim of sense satisfaction was not ignored, it was given its just importance. The soul’s need of labour and heroic action was not stifled, it was urged to its fullest action and freest scope. The hundred forms of the pursuit of knowledge were given an absolute freedom of movement; the play of the emotions was allowed, refined, trained till they were fit for the divine levels; the demand of the aesthetic faculties was encouraged in its highest rarest forms and in life’s commonest details. Indian culture did not deface nor impoverish the richness of the grand game of human life; it never depressed or mutilated the activities of our nature. On the contrary, subject to a certain principle of harmony and government, it allowed them their full, often their extreme value. Man was allowed to fathom on his way all experience, to give to his character and action a large rein and heroic proportions, and to fill in life opulently with colour and beauty and enjoyment. This life side of the Indian idea is stamped in strong relief over the epic and the classical literature. It is amazing indeed that anyone with an eye or a brain could have read the Ramayana, Mahabharata, the dramas, the literary epics, the romances, and the great abundance of gnomic and lyric poetry in Sanskrit and in the later tongues (to say nothing of the massive remains of other cultural work and social and political system and speculation), and yet failed to perceive this breadth, wealth and greatness. One must have read without eyes to see or without a mind to understand; most indeed of the adverse critics have not read or studied at all, but only flung about their preconceived notions with a violent or a high-browed ignorant assurance.

But while it is the generous office of culture to enrich, enlarge and encourage human life, it must also give the vital forces a guiding law, subject them to some moral and rational government and lead them beyond their first natural formulations, until it can find for life the clue to a spiritual freedom, perfection and greatness. The preeminent value of the ancient Indian civilisation lay in the power with which it did this work, the profound wisdom and high and subtle skill with which it based society and ordered the individual life, and encouraged and guided the propensities of human nature and finally turned them all towards the realisation of its master idea. The mind it was training, while not called away from its immediate aims, was never allowed to lose sight of the use of life as a discipline for spiritual perfection and a passage to the Infinite.”28

‡ The value of an aim, however high in itself, must depend on its power to effectuate itself in practical life, without which it would be considered impracticable and remain ineffective in practice. Therefore, had the Indian conception of life been of such a limited and ineffective kind, or had it been something remote and unattainable for the human capability, it could not have persisted and survived for such a long time. According to Sri Aurobindo, even when for some two thousand years at least no Indian has been really able to understand the Vedas, they have persisted and their influence has remained intact, and to this day they continue to be the bedrock of this culture. The Puranic literature – and taking for instance only two of them, the Bhagawat Mahapurana with the stories and pastimes of Lord Krishna, and the Markandeya Purana dedicated to Goddess Durga – seem to the present day modern mentality, coloured by Western rationalism, as utterly fanciful, unrealistic, and exaggerated. But a question that must arise in any reflecting intelligence is how then could writings so unintelligible and chimerical have succeeded in exercising such a deep and pervasive influence – that continues to grow even today – not only over the thought and life of the people of this culture but even on those nations that feel proud to present themselves as developed, rational and free from any superstitious beliefs. It is the same with the influence of the tantras and other Indian yoga systems. All these various systems and ways are, as it were, such infinite dimensions opened by the Indian culture to assist all the various parts of the being to come in contact with the Divine, to get a living experience of the truth of one’s being. The soundness and the all-pervasiveness of the Indian conception of life is established by the fact that it was not just some high ideal in the air with nothing much to do with the actual life of its people but was so intimately bound up with each and every thought and act of individuals and collectivities that even the most ordinary man was able to have a deep perception of the purpose of life and an urge to move towards it. We find a vivid and moving description of how the Indian culture succeeded in effectively connecting its high conception of life with an ordinary man’s actual life and nature in Rabindranath Tagore’s presidential address to the first session of the Indian Philosophical Congress held in 1925. We present here an excerpt from the same. “As in the world of art, so in God’s world, our soul waits for its freedom from the ego to reach that disinterested joy which is the source and goal of creation. It cries for its mukti into the unity of truth from the mirage of appearances endlessly pursued by the thirsty self. This idea of mukti, based upon metaphysics, has affected our life in India, touched the springs of our emotions and supplications for it soar heavenward on the wings of poesy. We constantly hear men of scanty learning and simple faith singing in their prayer to Tara, the Goddess Redeemer:

For what sin should I be compelled to remain in this dungeon of the world of appearances?

They are afraid of being alienated from the world of truth, afraid of their perpetual drifting amidst the froth and foam of things, of being tossed about by the tidal waves of pleasure and pain and never reaching the ultimate meaning of life. Of these men, one may be a carter driving his cart to market, another a fisherman plying his net. They may not be prompt with an intelligent answer, if questioned about the deeper import of the song they sing, but they have no doubt in their mind, that the abiding cause of all misery is not so much in the lack of life’s furniture as in the obscurity of life’s significance. It is a common topic with such to decry an undue emphasis upon me and mine, which falsifies the perspective of truth. For, have they not often seen men, who are not above their own level in social position or intellectual acquirement, going out to seek Truth, leaving everything that they have behind them?

They know that the object of these adventurers is not betterment in worldly wealth and power, — it is mukti, freedom. They possibly know some poor fellow villager of their own craft, who remains in the world carrying on his daily vocation, and yet has the reputation of being emancipated in the heart of the Eternal. I myself have come across a fisherman singing with an inward absorption of mind, while fishing all day in the Ganges, who was pointed out to me by my boatmen, with awe, as a man of liberated spirit. He is out of reach of the conventional prices which are set upon men by society, and which classify them like toys arranged in the shop-windows according to the market standard of value.

When the figure of this fisherman comes to my mind, I cannot but think that their number is not small who with their lives sing the epic of the unfettered soul, but will never be known in history. These unsophisticated Indian peasants know that an Emperor is a decorated slave remaining chained to his Empire, that a millionaire is kept pilloried by his fate in the golden cage of his wealth, while this fisherman is free in the realm of light. When, groping in the dark, we stumble against objects, we cling to them believing them to be our only hope. When light comes we slacken our hold, finding them to be mere parts of the all to which we are related. The simple man of the village knows what freedom is – freedom from the isolation of self, from the isolation of things which imparts a fierce intensity to our sense of possession. He knows that this freedom is not in the mere negation of bondage, in the bareness of belongings, but in some positive realisation which gives pure joy to our being…” (Mother India, Nov. 2003 issue, p. 947-48, Publisher: Sri Aurobindo Ashram, Pondicherry)

Shedding light on how this culture could remarkably succeed in such a formidable task of impressing its high ideals on the hearts of its people, he says: “All this is owing to the wonderful system of mass education which has prevailed for ages in India, and which today is in danger of becoming extinct. We have our academic seats of learning where students flock round their famous teachers from distant parts of the country. These places are like lakes, full of deep but still water, which have to be approached through difficult paths. But the constant evaporation from them, forming clouds, is carried by the wind from field to field, across hills and dales and through all the different divisions of the land. Operas based upon legendary poems, recitations and storytelling by trained men, the lyrical wealth of the popular literature distributed far and wide by the agency of mendicant singers, – these are the clouds that help to irrigate the minds of the people with the ideas which in their original form belonged to difficult doctrines of metaphysics. Profound speculations contained in the systems of Sankhya, Vedanta and Yoga are transformed into the living harvest of the people’s literature, brought to the door of those who can never have the leisure and training to pursue these thoughts to their fountainhead.

In order to enable a civilized community to carry on its complex functions, there must be a large number of men who have to take charge of its material needs, however onerous such task may be. Their vocation gives them no opportunity to cultivate their mind. Yet they form the vast multitude, compelled to turn themselves into unthinking machines of production, so that a few may have the time to think great thoughts, create immortal forms of art and to lead humanity to spiritual altitudes.

India has never neglected these social martyrs, but has tried to bring light into the grim obscurity of their life-long toil, and has always acknowledged its duty to supply them with mental and spiritual food in assimilable form through the medium of a variety of ceremonies. This process is not carried on by any specially organized association of public service, but by a spontaneous social adjustment which acts like circulation of blood in our bodily system. Because of this, the work continues even when the original purpose ceases to exist.

Once when I was on a visit to a small Bengal village, mostly inhabited by Mahomedan cultivators, the villagers entertained me with an opera performance the literature of which belonged to an obsolete religious sect that had wide influence centuries ago. Though the religion itself is dead, its voice still continues preaching its philosophy to a people who in spite of their different culture are not tired of listening. It discussed according to its own doctrine the different elements, material and transcendental, that constitute human personality, comprehending the body, the self and the soul. Then came a dialogue during the course of which was related the incident of a person who wanted to make a journey to Brindavan, the Garden of Bliss, but was prevented by a watchman who startled him with an accusation of theft. The thieving was proved when it was shown that inside his clothes he was secretly trying to smuggle into the garden the self, passing it on as his own and not admitting that it is for his master. The culprit was caught with the incriminating bundle in his possession which barred for him his passage to the supreme goal. Under a tattered canopy held on bamboo poles and lighted by a few smoking kerosene lamps, the village crowd, occasionally interrupted by howls of jackals in the neighbouring paddy fields, attended with untired interest, till the small hours of the morning, the performance of a drama, that discussed the ultimate meaning of all things in a seemingly incongruous setting of dance, music and humorous dialogue.

These illustrations will show how naturally, in India, poetry and philosophy have walked hand in hand, only because the latter has claimed its right to guide men to the practical path of their life’s fulfilment. What is that fulfilment? It is our freedom in truth, which has for its prayer

Lead us from the unreal to Reality.” (Mother India, Oct. 2003 issue, p. 818-19, Publisher: Sri Aurobindo Ashram, Pondicherry)

This description is sufficient to give us a glimpse of how each and every thought and act of the people had been guided by the great life-motives of the Indian culture.‡

(i) The Two Main Truths of Human Existence

The Indian mind kept always in sight two main truths of existence. First, man’s being in its growth has stages through which it must pass. Second, life is complex and the nature of man is also complex; “...in each life man has to figure a certain sum of its complexity and put that into some kind of order. But the initial movement of life is that form of it which develops the powers of the natural ego in man; self-interest and hedonistic desire are the original human motives, – kāma, artha. Indian culture gave a large recognition to this primary turn of our nature. These powers have to be accepted and put in order; for the natural ego-life must be lived and the forces it evolves in the human being must be brought to fullness. But this element must be kept from making any too unbridled claim or heading furiously towards its satisfaction; only so can it get its full results without disaster and only so can it be inspired eventually to go beyond itself and turn in the end to a greater spiritual Good and Bliss. An internal or external anarchy cannot be the rule; a life governed in any absolute or excessive degree by self-will, passion, sense-attraction, self-interest and desire cannot be the natural whole of a human or a humane existence. The tempting imagination that it can and that this is the true law is a lure with which the Western mind has played in characteristic leanings or outbursts; but this turn unjustly called Paganism, – for the Greek or Pagan intelligence had a noble thought for law and harmony and self-rule, – is alien to the Indian spirit. India has felt the call of the senses not less than Greece, Rome or modern Europe; she perceived very well the possibility of a materialistic life and its attraction worked on certain minds and gave birth to the philosophy of the Charvakas: but this could not take full hold or establish even for a time any dominant empire. Even if we can see in it, when lived on a grand scale, a certain perverse greatness, still a colossal egoism indulgent of the sole life of the mind and the senses was regarded by her as the nature of the Asura and Rakshasa. It is the Titanic, gigantic or demoniac type of spirit, permitted in its own plane, but not the proper law for a human life. Another power claims man and overtops desire and self-interest and self-will, the power of the Dharma.”29

‡ To understand the significance and true place of desire (kāma) and artha (self-interest) in human existence, we have to turn to the fundamental idea of the Indian culture which holds that the One Sole Reality constitutes all that there is, all existence is the existence of the one Eternal and Infinite – Ekamevadvitiyam, – there is the One without a second and there can be nothing else at any time or anywhere. The whole effort of the terrestrial creation seems to be to progressively manifest that Sole Reality. The unfolding in this terrestrial evolutionary Nature has a double process: there is an outward visible process of physical evolution with birth as its machinery and there is an invisible process of soul evolution. Due to its emerging out of the Subconscience and the Nescience, there is in this evolution a constant downward pull of gravitation towards the original Inertia and Nescience which tries to dissolve all the formations that life and mind build, swallow all things and disintegrate them into the original matter. To counter this downward pull and provide a secure basis for the evolution of increasingly complex physical forms capable of housing ever higher and greater levels of consciousness, the first impulse of nature has been towards establishing firmly the principle of life in this terrestrial evolution. Therefore, for the maintenance and perpetuation of life and also to tread the hard ground of Matter – for, without it there would be no manifestation possible – nature deeply implants fear and desire. Had this deep-rooted element of desire – which blindly seeks its own satisfaction in the form of various physical and vital hungers, cravings and lusts – not been there, it would hardly have been possible to carry out smoothly even those basic acts of ingestion, procreation, and various others so indispensable for the survival of life and, therefore, there would be no secure basis left for the life to establish itself in the terrestrial conditions. Besides, there is a yet deeper and fundamental reason behind desire and self-interest. In the truth of its being, the Sole Reality is a completely unified consciousness but for it to be able to express itself in an innumerable multitude, a sense of separate existence is imperative. Therefore, according to the Sankhya philosophy, the first fundamental principle that initiates this whole phenomenal creation, is the divisional principle, Ahankara, the sense of a separate self-existence. But this sense of self and non-self brings with it the fear of losing one’s separate self, and therefore, a spontaneous urge to appropriate and possess things for one’s own self. This sense of a separate self carries with it a sense of insufficiency and gives rise to desire. In its long process of evolving ever more complex types and forms for a firm foundation of life, Nature, with the appearance of man, the mental being, seems for the first time to have reached a stage where conscious volition comes into play. It is only at the level of human consciousness that the infinite possibilities of a conscious evolution are unveiled.

At present we can see how the entire materialistic culture of the West, including its physical science, is grossly centered around the satisfaction of the hedonistic and egoistic parts of the being. This exclusive concentration on the ego beyond a point – after its significant role in developing an individual personality is over – becomes a hindrance in our progress. If left unbridled, without subjecting it to some higher discipline, it could hardly escape the stumbles or even the disasters which so often accompany any excessively egoistic pursuits. For, the forces working behind ego, desire, selfishness, etc. always impel one to turn back upon oneself and ignore the aspect of collectivity. Even if one accepts the collectivity, it is only as an aggrandized form of one’s small ego and as a means for one’s enlarged satisfaction. But there could be no success for an orchestra in which individual musicians played according to their own fancy and refused to follow the directions of the conductor. Therefore, just as even while being under the strict discipline of an experienced master, a disciple gets the fullest possible chance to grow freely and learns even by making his own experiments and mistakes, the Indian culture, tried to cultivate, refine, and turn even the hedonistic and egoistic parts godwards by giving them their due chance of expression and fulfilment while keeping them under the yoke of its high fundamental motive. For, the Indian culture knew that the strictness of training, the habit of discipline and obedience is not inconsistent with freedom; rather it is often the necessary condition for its right use. Thus, the whole movement of the Indian culture has been towards transmuting all the various parts of the being – not by suppression, but by proper cultivation in the light of its highest ideal – into effective instruments of the soul for its self-expression. ‡

(ii) The Workings of Dharma – the Religious Law of Action and the Deepest Law of Our Nature

In the Indian conception, Dharma, “...is not, as in the Western idea, a creed, cult or ideal inspiring an ethical and social rule; it is the right law of functioning of our life in all its parts. The tendency of man to seek after a just and perfect law of his living finds its truth and its justification in the Dharma. Every thing indeed has its dharma, its law of life imposed on it by its nature; but for man the dharma is the conscious imposition of a rule of ideal living on all his members. Dharma is fixed in its essence, but still it develops in our consciousness and evolves and has its stages; there are gradations of spiritual and ethical ascension in the search for the highest law of our nature. All men cannot follow in all things one common and invariable rule. Life is too complex to admit of the arbitrary ideal simplicity which the moralising theorist loves. Natures differ; the position, the work we have to do has its own claims and standards; the aim and bent, the call of life, the call of the spirit within is not the same for everyone: the degree and turn of development and the capacity, adhikāra, are not equal. Man lives in society and by society, and every society has its own general dharma, and the individual life must be fitted into this wider law of movement. But there too the individual’s part in society and his nature and the needs of his capacity and temperament vary and have many kinds and degrees: the social law must make some room for this variety and would lose by being rigidly one for all. The man of knowledge, the man of power, the productive and acquisitive man, the priest, scholar, poet, artist, ruler, fighter, trader, tiller of the soil, craftsman, labourer, servant cannot usefully have the same training, cannot be shaped in the same pattern, cannot all follow the same way of living. All ought not to be put under the same tables of the law; for that would be a senseless geometric rigidity that would spoil the plastic truth of life. Each has his type of nature and there must be a rule for the perfection of that type; each has his own proper function and there must be a canon and ideal for the function. There must be in all things some wise and understanding standard of practice and idea of perfection and living rule, – that is the one thing needful for the Dharma. A lawless impulsion of desire and interest and propensity cannot be allowed to lead human conduct; even in the frankest following of desire and interest and propensity there must be a governing and restraining and directing line, a guidance. There must be an ethic or a science, a restraint as well as a scope arising from the truth of the thing sought, a standard of perfection, an order. Differing with the type of the man and the type of the function these special dharmas would yet rise towards the greater law and truth that contains and overtops the others and is universally effective. This then was the Dharma, special for the special person, stage of development, pursuit of life or individual field of action, but universal too in the broad lines which all ought to pursue.

The universal embracing dharma in the Indian idea is a law of ideal perfection for the developing mind and soul of man; it compels him to grow in the power and force of certain high or large universal qualities which in their harmony build a highest type of manhood. In Indian thought and life this was the ideal of the best, the law of the good or noble man, the discipline laid down for the self-perfecting individual, ārya, śreṣṭha, sajjana, sādhu. This ideal was not a purely moral or ethical conception, although that element might predominate; it was also intellectual, religious, social, aesthetic, the flowering of the whole ideal man, the perfection of the total human nature. The most varied qualities met in the Indian conception of the best, śreṣṭha, the good and noble man, ārya. In the heart benevolence, beneficence, love, compassion, altruism, long-suffering, liberality, kindliness, patience; in the character courage, heroism, energy, loyalty, continence, truth, honour, justice, faith, obedience and reverence where these were due, but power too to govern and direct, a fine modesty and yet a strong independence and noble pride; in the mind wisdom and intelligence and love of learning, knowledge of all the best thought, an openness to poetry, art and beauty, an educated capacity and skill in works; in the inner being a strong religious sense, piety, love of God, seeking after the Highest, the spiritual turn; in social relations and conduct a strict observance of all the social dharmas, as father, son, husband, brother, kinsman, friend, ruler or subject, master or servant, priest or warrior or worker, king or sage, member of clan or caste: this was the total ideal of the Arya, the man of high upbringing and noble nature. The ideal is clearly portrayed in the written records of ancient India during two millenniums and it is the very life-breath of Hindu ethics. It was the creation of an at once ideal and rational mind, spirit-wise and worldly-wise, deeply religious, nobly ethical, firmly yet flexibly intellectual, scientific and aesthetic, patient and tolerant of life’s difficulties and human weakness, but arduous in self-discipline. This was the mind that was at the base of the Indian civilisation and gave its characteristic stamp to all the culture.”30

‡ What after all is dharma, what is its true nature and its determining factors? It is evident that each thing or element in nature has its particular properties and characteristics. Accordingly, there is a right way of dealing with it, which grows more complex with the evolution of ever more advanced and complex forms in nature. The fundamental change in the evolution with the coming of man is the development of the faculty of self-observation, with the help of which man discovers that he is comprised of various parts – ranging from the most material and objective to the most subtle and subjective – each of which contributes something to the total movement of his consciousness, thought, will, sensation, feeling, and action. Therefore, the dharma or the rule of ideal living for an individual can be effectively laid down only by taking into account the stage of his own inner and outer development as well as of those collectivities of which he is a part. Meditating upon the particularity with which the Indian culture laid down the detailed dharmas for each and everything, not only gives us a deeper insight into the fundamental structure of this culture but helps us to grow even more conscious of the truths of our own being and its working.

Firstly, the mission of this culture has been to purge barbarism (mlecchahood) out of the natural man and Aryanise him. ‘Mleccha’ is one who regards the fulfilment of his desire and self-interest to be the sole purpose of life and, therefore, his life is indiscriminately devoted to the gratification of his physical and vital propensities. He is preoccupied solely with devising ever more efficient systems for arranging all the resources and energies at hand so as to get the maximum possible opportunities of satisfying his animalistic and egoistic tendencies. As opposed to this, according to Sri Aurobindo, “The Aryan is he who strives and overcomes all outside him and within him that stands opposed to the human advance. Self-conquest is the first law of his nature. He overcomes earth and the body and does not consent like ordinary men to their dullness, inertia, dead routine and tamasic limitations. He overcomes life and its energies and refuses to be dominated by their hungers and cravings or enslaved by their rajasic passions. He overcomes the mind and its habits, he does not live in a shell of ignorance, inherited prejudices, customary ideas, pleasant opinions, but knows how to seek and choose, to be large and flexible in intelligence even as he is firm and strong in his will. For in everything he seeks truth, in everything right, in everything height and freedom.

Self-perfection is the aim of his self-conquest. Therefore what he conquers he does not destroy, but ennobles and fulfils. He knows that the body, life and mind are given him in order to attain to something higher than they; therefore they must be transcended and overcome, their limitations denied, the absorption of their gratifications rejected. But he knows also that the Highest is something which is no nullity in the world, but increasingly expresses itself here, – a divine Will, Consciousness, Love, Beatitude which pours itself out, when found, through the terms of the lower life on the finder and on all in his environment that is capable of receiving it. Of that he is the servant, lover and seeker. When it is attained, he pours it forth in work, love, joy and knowledge upon mankind. For always the Aryan is a worker and warrior. He spares himself no labour of mind or body whether to seek the Highest or to serve it. He avoids no difficulty, he accepts no cessation from fatigue. Always he fights for the coming of that kingdom within himself and in the world.”(CWSA 13, 442-43) According to the Indian culture, the canon of dharma is applicable only to an Aryan, and not to a mleccha. Therefore, in its all-embracing spirit, this culture did not seek to raise only a few elect to the state of Aryahood, but called upon each and every one to this ideal and even assisted him in its attainment. For an effective building of a nationwide atmosphere where each and every thought and act of an individual could be regulated by the law of Dharma, stress was always laid on the development of high moral, ethical and spiritual virtues. The plethora of living examples, taking each virtue almost to its extreme, inspired the whole country to cultivate and abide by those high moral standards and qualities. How deep-rooted and all-pervasive this idea of Aryan and un-Aryan conduct was in this culture becomes evident from an example we find in the Gita in the second verse of the second chapter, where Lord Sri Krishna rebukingly says to Arjuna, “Whence has come to thee this dejection, O Arjuna, in this hour of difficulty and peril. It is not cherished by Aryan men; it leads neither to heaven nor to glory.” Time and again we find this note of Dharma recurring in the old Indian literature. But the Indian conception of dharma or the right law of functioning must not be confused with those rigid and unchanging moral principles of the West which are to be imposed indiscriminately on all alike, without taking into account the varying capacities, stages and degrees of development and the bent of the nature of each individual and are, therefore, found in practice to be more or less ineffective and limited to vocal adherence. The Indian culture, on the contrary, looked upon each individual as essentially identical with the Divine and an expression of one of His infinite attributes. It held that each individual soul has its own essential nature and self-principle of being, swabhava, which is the primary determinant and underlies all the outer dispositions. It is primarily in view of this fundamental truth of our being, swabhava, that four broad divisions of varnas were made, namely, Brahmin, Kshatriya, Vaishya and Shudra. These are four distinct orders of the active nature, or four fundamental types of the soul in nature, and the proper work and proper function of each human being was that which corresponded to his type of nature. Therefore, not only detailed dharmas for each type of nature were laid down, but even a great emphasis was always kept on carrying out actions ordained by and in harmony with the truth of one’s being, governed by the Swabhava, swabhava-niyata karma. In the Gita, one gets a glimpse of how all-pervasive and binding the dharmas had been in the old Indian society, when it says, “Better is one’s own law of works, svadharma, though in itself faulty than an alien law well wrought out; death in one’s own law of being is better, perilous is it to follow an alien law.” (3:35) Reiterating the same thing in its final chapter, it says, “Better is one’s Swadharma (own law of works) though in itself faulty, than an alien law well carried out; one does not incur sin when one does the work regulated by one’s self-nature.” (18:47) Even within a particular varna, with its own well-defined outline of dharma, the dharma for each individual would vary depending on the stage of his development. For evidently, the same ideal rule of conduct could not be indiscriminately applied to a Brahmachari and a householder, or to an adult and a child. Even for any two Brahmacharis the actual determination of dharmas for both must take into account their preference for or inclination towards one of the fourfold objects or Purusharthas of life. Thus, based on the four broad divisions of the triple quartette of Varnas, Ashramas and Purusharthas and their interrelationships, the Indian culture categorised human nature into sixty-four divisions.

A colossal effort was made by the Indian Rishis to provide, in the form of shastras, a detailed and systematised teaching and science for each department of life, each line of activity, each subject of knowledge in order to enable man and society to regulate their whole life in the light of a higher dharma and to act with the security of right knowledge rather than being driven obscurely by their lower propensities. Just as any individual soul, each class, each race, each nation, and even the entire humanity has its own separate collective being with a unique truth of its own to manifest. All these collectivities too have their own general dharma, their ideal law of functioning and perfection. ‡

(iii) The Exceeding of Dharma – The Ideal of Moksha or Mukti

“Indian culture raised the crude animal life of desire, self-interest and satisfied propensity beyond its first intention to a noble self-exceeding and shapeliness by infusing into it the order and high aims of the Dharma. But its profounder characteristic aim – and in this it was unique – was to raise this nobler life too of the self-perfecting human being beyond its own intention to a mightiest self-exceeding and freedom; it laboured to infuse into it the great aim of spiritual liberation and perfection, mukti, mokṣa. The Law and its observance are neither the beginning nor the end of man; there is beyond the field of the Law a larger realm of consciousness in which, climbing, he emerges into a great spiritual freedom. Not a noble but ever death-bound manhood is the highest height of man’s perfection: immortality, freedom, divinity are within his grasp. Ancient Indian culture held this highest aim constantly before the inner eye of the soul and insistently inspired with its prospect and light the whole conception of existence. The entire life of the individual was ennobled by this aim; the whole ordering of society was cast into a scale of graduated ascension towards this supreme summit.

A well-governed system of the individual and communal existence must be always in the first instance an ordering of the three first powers recognised by Indian thought. The claim of the natural functionings must be recognised in it to the full; the pursuit of personal and communal interest and the satisfaction of human desires as of human needs must be amply admitted and there must be an understanding combination of knowledge and labour towards these ends. But all must be controlled, uplifted and widened to greater aims by the ideal of the Dharma. And if, as India believes, there is a higher spiritual consciousness towards which man can rise, that ascent must be kept throughout in view as the supreme goal of life. The system of Indian culture at once indulged and controlled man’s nature; it fitted him for his social role; it stamped on his mind the generous ideal of an accomplished humanity refined, harmonised in all its capacities, ennobled in all its members; but it placed before him too the theory and practice of a highest change, familiarised him with the conception of a spiritual existence and sowed in him a hunger for the divine and the infinite. The symbols of his religion were filled with suggestions which led towards it; at every step he was reminded of lives behind and in front and of worlds beyond the material existence; he was brought close to the nearness, even to the call and pressure of the Spirit who is greater than the life it informs, of the final goal, of a high possible immortality, freedom, God-consciousness, divine Nature. Man was not allowed to forget that he had in him a highest self beyond his little personal ego and that always he and all things live, move and have their being in God, in the Eternal, in the Spirit. There were ways and disciplines provided in number by which he could realise this liberating truth or could at least turn and follow at a distance this highest aim according to his capacity and nature, adhikāra. Around him he saw and revered the powerful practicants and the mighty masters of these disciplines. These men were in early times the teachers of his youth, the summits of his society, the inspirers and fountain-heads of his civilisation, the great lights of his culture. Spiritual freedom, spiritual perfection were not figured as a far-off intangible ideal, but presented as the highest human aim towards which all must grow in the end, and were made near and possible to his endeavour from a first practicable basis of life and the Dharma. The spiritual idea governed, enlightened and gathered towards itself all the other life-motives of a great civilised people.”31

“These are the principal lines upon which the structure of Indian civilisation was founded and they constitute the power of its conception of life. I do not think it can be said that there is here any inferiority to other human cultures or to any established conception of life that has ever held sway over the mind of man in historic times. There is nothing here that can be said to discourage life and its flowering or to deprive it of impetus and elevation and a great motive. On the contrary there is a full and frank recognition and examination of the whole of human existence in all its variety and range and power, there is a clear and wise and noble idea for its right government and there is an ideal tendency pointing it upward and a magnificent call to a highest possible perfection and greatness. These are the serious uses of culture, these are the things that raise the life of man above a crude, primitive barbarism. If a civilisation is to be judged by the power of its ideas, their power for these great uses, Indian civilisation was inferior to none. Certainly, it was not perfect or final or complete; for that can be alleged of no past or present cultural idea or system. Man is in his inmost self an infinite being, in his mind and life too he is continually growing, with whatever stumblings and long relapses, and he cannot be permanently bound in any one system of ideas or frame of living. The structures in which he lives are incomplete and provisional; even those which seem the most comprehensive lose their force to stand and are convicted by time of insufficiency and must be replaced or change. But this at least can be said of the Indian idea that it seized with a remarkable depth and comprehensiveness on the main truths and needs of the whole human being, on his mind and life and body, his artistic and ethical and intellectual parts of nature, his soul and spirit, and gave them a subtle and liberal, a profoundly large and high and wise, a sympathetic and yet nobly arduous direction. More cannot be said for any past or any existing culture.”32

C. The Power of the Forms, Types and Rhythms That the Indian Culture Has Given to Life

In any culture aiming at completeness there must be “...not only great and noble governing and inspiring ideas, but a harmony of forms and rhythms, a mould into which the ideas and the life can run and settle. Here we must be prepared for a lesser perfection, a greater incompleteness. And the reason is that just as the spirit is vaster than its ideas, the ideas too are larger than their forms, moulds and rhythms. Form has a certain fixity which limits; no form can exhaust or fully express the potentialities of the idea or force that gave it birth. Neither can any idea, however great, or any limited play of force or form bind the infinite spirit: that is the secret of earth’s need of mutation and progress. The idea is only a partial expression of the spirit. Even within its own limits, on its own lines it ought always to become more supple, to fill itself out with other views, to rise and broaden to new applications, and often it has to lose itself in uplifting transformations of its own meaning into vaster significances or fuse itself into new and richer syntheses.”33

(i) The Three Stages or Periods in the History of the Indian Culture

“In the history of all great cultures therefore we find a passage through three periods, for this passage is a necessary consequence of this truth of things. There is a first period of large and loose formation; there is a second period in which we see a fixing of forms, moulds and rhythms; and there is a closing or a critical period of superannuation, decay and disintegration. This last stage is the supreme crisis in the life of a civilisation; if it cannot transform itself, it enters into a slow lingering decline or else collapses in a death agony brought about by the rapid impact of stronger and more immediately living though not necessarily greater or truer powers or formations. But if it is able to shake itself free of limiting forms, to renovate its ideas and to give a new scope to its spirit, if it is willing to understand, master and assimilate novel growths and necessities, then there is a rebirth, a fresh lease of life and expansion, a true renascence.

Indian civilisation passed in its own large and leisurely manner through all these stages. Its first period was that of a great spiritual out-flowering in which the forms were supple, flexible and freely responsive to its essential spirit. That fluid movement passed away into an age of strong intellectuality in which all was fixed into distinct, sufficiently complex, but largely treated and still supple forms and rhythms. There came as a consequence a period of richly crystallised fixity shaken by crises which were partly met by a change of ideas and a modification of forms. But the hard binding of set forms triumphed at last and there was a decline of the inspiring spirit, a stagnation of living force, a progressive decay of the outward structure. This decay was accompanied and at once arrested for a moment and hastened in the end by the impact of other cultures. Today we are in the midst of a violent and decisive crisis brought about by the inflooding of the West and of all for which it stands. An upheaval resulted that began with the threat of a total death and irretrievable destruction of the culture; but its course is now uplifted on the contrary by the strong hope of a great revival, transmutation and renascence. Each of these three stages has its special significance for the student of culture. If we would understand the essential spirit of Indian civilisation, we must go back to its first formative period, the early epoch of the Veda and the Upanishads, its heroic creative seed-time. If we would study the fixed forms of its spirit and discern the thing it eventually realised as the basic rhythm of its life, we must look with an observing eye at the later middle period of the Shastras and the classic writings, the age of philosophy and science, legislation and political and social theory and many-sided critical thought, religious fixation, art, sculpture, painting, architecture. If we would discover the limitations, the points at which it stopped short and failed to develop its whole or its true spirit, we must observe closely the unhappy disclosures of its period of decline. If, finally, we would discover the directions it is likely to follow in its transformation, we must try to fathom what lies beneath the still confused movements of its crisis of renascence. None of these can indeed be cut clean apart from each other; for what developed in one period is already forecast and begun in the preceding age: but still on a certain large and imprecise scale we can make these distinctions and they are necessary for a discerning analytic view. But at present we are only concerned with the developed forms and the principal rhythms which persisted through its greater eras.”34

(ii) The Firm Outward Basis for the Founding of the Practical Development of the Spirit of Indian Culture and Its Idea in Life – The Fourfold Varnasram System

“The problem which Indian culture had to solve was that of a firm outward basis on which to found the practical development of its spirit and its idea in life. How are we to take the natural life of man and, while allowing it sufficient scope and variety and freedom, yet to subject it to a law, canon, dharma, a law of function, a law of type, a law of each actual unideal human tendency and a law too of highest ideal intention? And how again are we to point that dharma towards its own exceeding by the fulfilment and cessation of its disciplinary purpose in the secure freedom of the spiritual life? Indian culture from an early stage seized upon a double idea for its own guidance which it threw into a basic system of the individual life in the social frame. This was the double system of the four Varnas and the four Asramas, – four graded classes of society and four successive stages of a developing human life.”35

(a) The Chaturvarnya System

“The ancient Chaturvarnya must not be judged by its later disintegrated degeneration and gross meaningless parody, the caste system. But neither was it precisely the system of the classes which we find in other civilisations, priesthood, nobility, merchant class and serfs or labourers. It may have had outwardly the same starting-point, but it was given a very different revealing significance. The ancient Indian idea was that man falls by his nature into four types. There are, first and highest, the man of learning and thought and knowledge; next, the man of power and action, ruler, warrior, leader, administrator; third in the scale, the economic man, producer and wealth-getter, the merchant, artisan, cultivator: these were the twice-born, who received the initiation, Brahmin, Kshatriya, Vaishya. Last came the more undeveloped human type, not yet fit for these steps of the scale, unintellectual, without force, incapable of creation or intelligent production, the man fit only for unskilled labour and menial service, the Shudra. The economic order of society was cast in the form and gradation of these four types. The Brahmin class was called upon to give the community its priests, thinkers, men of letters, legists, scholars, religious leaders and guides. The Kshatriya class gave it its kings, warriors, governors and administrators. The Vaishya order supplied it with its producers, agriculturists, craftsmen, artisans, merchants and traders. The Shudra class ministered to its need of menials and servants. As far as this went, there was nothing peculiar in the system except its extraordinary durability and, perhaps, the supreme position given to religion, thought and learning, not only at the top of the scale, – for that can be paralleled from one or two other civilisations, – but as the dominant power. The Indian idea in its purity fixed the status of a man in this order not by his birth, but by his capacities and his inner nature, and, if this rule had been strictly observed, that would have been a very clear mark of distinctness, a superiority of a unique kind. But even the best society is always something of a machine and gravitates towards the material sign and standard, and to found truly the social order upon this finer psychological basis would have been in those times a difficult and vain endeavour. In practice we find that birth became the basis of the Varna. It is elsewhere that we must look for the strong distinguishing mark which has made of this social structure a thing apart and sole in its type.

At no time indeed was the adherence to the economic rule quite absolute. The early ages show a considerable flexibility which was not quite lost in the process of complex crystallisation into a fixed form. And even in the greater rigidity of the latter-day caste system there has been in practice a confusion of economic functions. The vitality of a vigorous community cannot obey at every point the indications of a pattern and tradition cut by the mechanising mind. Moreover there was always a difference between the ideal theory of the system and its rougher unideal practice. For the material side of an idea or system has always its weaknesses even in its best times, and the final defect of all systems of this kind is that they stiffen into a fixed hierarchy which cannot maintain permanently its purity or the utility it was meant to serve. It becomes a soulless form and prolongs itself in a state of corruption, degeneracy or oppressive formalism when the uses that justified it are no longer in existence. Even when its ways can no longer be made consistent with the developing needs of the growth of humanity, the formal system persists and corrupts the truth of life and blocks progress. Indian society did not escape this general law; it was overtaken by these deficiencies, lost the true sense of the thing which it set out to embody and degenerated into a chaos of castes, developing evils which we are now much embarrassed to eliminate. But it was a well-devised and necessary scheme in its time; it gave the community the firm and nobly built stability it needed for the security of its cultural development, – a stability hardly paralleled in any other culture. And, as interpreted by the Indian genius, it became a greater thing than a mere outward economic, political and social mechanism intended to serve the needs and convenience of the collective life.

For the real greatness of the Indian system of the four varnas did not lie in its well-ordered division of economic function; its true originality and permanent value was in the ethical and spiritual content which the thinkers and builders of the society poured into these forms. This inner content started with the idea that the intellectual, ethical and spiritual growth of the individual is the central need of the race. Society itself is only the necessary framework for this growth; it is a system of relations which provides it with its needed medium, field and conditions and with a nexus of helpful influences. A secure place had to be found in the community for the individual man from which he could at once serve these relations, helping to maintain the society and pay it his debt of duty and assistance, and proceed to his own self-development with the best possible aid from the communal life. Birth was accepted in practice as the first gross and natural indicator; for heredity to the Indian mind has always ranked as a factor of the highest importance: it was even taken in later thought as a sign of the nature and as an index to the surroundings which the individual had prepared for himself by his past soul-development in former existences. But birth is not and cannot be the sole test of Varna. The intellectual capacity of the man, the turn of his temperament, his ethical nature, his spiritual stature, these are the important factors. There was erected therefore a rule of family living, a system of individual observance and self-training, a force of upbringing and education which would bring out and formulate these essential things. The individual man was carefully trained in the capacities, habits and attainments, and habituated to the sense of honour and duty necessary for the discharge of his allotted function in life. He was scrupulously equipped with the science of the thing he had to do, the best way to succeed in it as an interest, artha, and to attain to the highest rule, canon and recognised perfection of its activities, economic, political, sacerdotal, literary, scholastic or whatever else they might be. Even the most despised pursuits had their education, their law and canon, their ambition of success, their sense of honour in the discharge and scruple of well-doing, their dignity of a fixed standard of perfection, and it was because they had these things that even the lowest and least attractive could be in a certain degree a means of self-finding and ordered self-satisfaction. In addition to this special function and training there were the general accomplishments, sciences, arts, graces of life, those which satisfy the intellectual, aesthetic and hedonistic powers of human nature. These in ancient India were many and various, were taught with minuteness, thoroughness and subtlety and were available to all men of culture.

But while there was provision for all these things and it was made with a vivid liberality of the life-spirit and a noble sense of order, the spirit of Indian culture did not, like other ancient cultures, stop here.”36

(b) The Chaturvarnya Only a Substructure for the Higher Object to be Served by It

“It said to the individual: ‘This is only the substructure; it is of a pressing importance indeed, but still not the last and greatest thing. When you have paid your debt to society, filled well and admirably your place in its life, helped its maintenance and continuity and taken from it your legitimate and desired satisfactions, there still remains the greatest thing of all. There is still your own self, the inner you, the soul which is a spiritual portion of the Infinite, one in its essence with the Eternal. This self, this soul in you you have to find, you are here for that, and it is from the place I have provided for you in life and by this training that you can begin to find it. For to each Varna I have supplied its highest ideal of manhood, the highest ideal way of which your nature is capable. By directing your life and nature in its own law of being towards that perfection, you can not only grow towards the ideal and enter into harmony with universal nature but come also into nearness and contact with a greater nature of divinity and move towards transcendence. That is the real object before you. From the life-basis I give you you can rise to the liberating knowledge which brings a spiritual release, mokṣa. Then you can grow out of all these limitations in which you are being trained; you can grow through the fulfilled Dharma and beyond it into the eternity of your self, into the fullness, freedom, greatness and bliss of the immortal spirit; for that is what each man is behind the veils of his nature. When you have done that you are free. Then you have gone beyond all the dharmas; you are then a universal soul, one with all existence, and you can either act in that divine liberty for the good of all living things or else turn to enjoy in solitude the bliss of eternity and transcendence.’ ”37

‡ Qs. What after all is the Chaturvarnya system and what is the fundamental rationale behind it? How did the four Varnas come into existence?

Ans. This entire creation is nothing but the manifestation of the Divine Transcendent Mother. She has infinite attributes and powers, but only four of her great Aspects, four of her leading Powers and Personalities – Maheshwari, Mahakali, Mahalakshmi and Mahasaraswati – have stood in front in her guidance of this universe and in her dealings with the terrestrial play. It is these aspects that we find being alluded to at various places in the old Indian literature as the fourfold presence of the Divine. Each individual soul or Jiva possesses in his spiritual nature the action of all these four aspects but in action and expressive spirit one or the other aspect predominates and constitutes the inherent nature, Swabhava, of the individual.

Therefore, the central motive of this culture has been to make an individual soul grow conscious of this inherent nature, so that instead of being mechanically driven by the surface nature, it may increasingly express the inner nature in its life. The outer acts should be such as to facilitate an increasing expression of the inner Swabhava. Without taking into account his inner nature, if a person was asked to engage in a work inconsistent with his nature, not only would he not be able to truly perform it but, if pressed beyond a point, it may even have undesirable consequences on the inner psychology of the person. This is why in this culture great stress has always been laid on performing ‘swabhava niyata karma’, that is, carrying out action evolved from within, in harmony with the truth of one’s being, regulated by one’s self-nature. Corresponding to the inner-nature, four broad divisions of human nature were made each with its characteristic function and ideal rule of work. The first came the Brahmin, the man with a turn for knowledge, who brings thought, reflection, the seeking for truth and an intelligent or at the highest a spiritual rule into life and illumines by it his conception and mode of existence. Next came the Kshatriya, the man with the predominance of the aspect of power. Not self-pleasing and domestic happiness and a life of comfort and peaceful joy with friends and relatives, but to battle for the right, to protect justice, was his true object of life and to find a cause for which he could lay down his life or by victory win the crown and glory of the hero’s existence was his greatest happiness. Thirdly came the Vaishya, with the predominance of the action of Mahalakshmi in his nature. He had a sense of proportion, of order, of harmony between things and their interrelationships, and also a skill in arrangement and management. His nature is endowed with dexterity and skill in arranging the means, the equipment, the action so as to produce the greatest results possible. It is this power of Mahalakshmi that gives the sense of the right law, proper order or arrangement of any given work or thing, say, of how to efficiently run a business, or go about farming, or cooking, or carrying out any other work. Lastly, the Shudra, is the man with the action of Mahasaraswati power prominent in his nature endowed with the capacity of self-giving, service and detailed perfection in work. All dexterity in hands is a reflection of the working of this power. One must keep in mind that any complete and perfect action involves the working of all these four powers, although the degree of the actual involvement and predominance of any one or more of these powers depends on the nature of the work at hand. Maheshwari is the eldest of them all, for it is her province to give a true sense of the right direction to advance and lay large lines for any given undertaking, without which no endeavour can truly commence. Then comes the action of Mahakali, to supply with the necessary power and energy for the execution of those large lines. But for the power and energy to be truly effective requires skill in the use of means and methods and their proper disposition in order to secure the end and also the knowledge of what is or is not possible to be gained by a particular means or method or a particular expense, this is the work of Mahalakshmi. And finally, it is Mahasaraswati who supplies the capacity of detailed perfection in execution without which no perfect manifestation is possible. Thus, it is by the power of all four of these that a complete action is possible. Shedding light on these four types of personality, Sri Aurobindo says, “None of these four types of personality can be complete even in its own field if it does not bring into it something of the other qualities. The man of knowledge cannot serve Truth with freedom and perfection, if he has not intellectual and moral courage, will, audacity, the strength to open and conquer new kingdoms, otherwise he becomes a slave of the limited intellect or a servant or at most a ritual priest of only an established knowledge, – cannot use his knowledge to the best advantage unless he has the adaptive skill to work out its truths for the practice of life, otherwise he lives only in the idea, – cannot make the entire consecration of his knowledge unless he has the spirit of service to humanity, to the Godhead in man and the Master of his being. The man of power must illumine and uplift and govern his force and strength by knowledge, light of reason or religion or the spirit, otherwise he becomes the mere forceful Asura, – must have the skill which will help him best to use and administer and regulate his strength and make it creative and fruitful and adapted to his relations with others, otherwise it becomes a mere drive of force across the field of life, a storm that passes and devastates more than it constructs, – must be capable too of obedience and make the use of his strength a service to God and the world, otherwise he becomes a selfish dominator, tyrant, brutal compeller of men’s souls and bodies. The man of productive mind and work must have an open inquiring mind and ideas and knowledge, otherwise he moves in the routine of his functions without expansive growth, must have courage and enterprise, must bring a spirit of service into his getting and production, in order that he may not only get but give, not only amass and enjoy his own life, but consciously help the fruitfulness and fullness of the surrounding life by which he profits. The man of labour and service becomes a helpless drudge and slave of society if he does not bring knowledge and honour and aspiration and skill into his work, since only so can he rise by an opening mind and will and understanding usefulness to the higher dharmas. But the greater perfection of man comes when he enlarges himself to include all these powers, even though one of them may lead the others, and opens his nature more and more into the rounded fullness and universal capacity of the fourfold spirit. Man is not cut out into an exclusive type of one of these dharmas, but all these powers are in him at work at first in an ill-formed confusion, but he gives shape to one or another in birth after birth, progresses from one to the other even in the same life and goes on towards the total development of his inner existence.”(CWSA 24, 748-49)

Qs. How was the Swabhava, the inherent nature, the Varna of a person determined in this Culture?

Ans. Without any deeper understanding and inner perception it is indeed not at all easy to determine the true nature of a person. Generally, the ordinary man lives upon his waking surface, ignorant of the self’s depths and vastnesses behind the veil. His surface outer nature, bound by the play of the three gunas, is nothing but a complex mass of mental, nervous and physical habits held together by a few ruling ideas, desires and associations where errors, perversions, falsehoods are so intertwined with the truth and light that he stumbles about in search of some sure footing. Although the Jiva, the soul inside is perfectly conscious of its swabhava, the surface nature, being completely ignorant of the self’s depths doesn’t share into this knowledge of the soul and has to pass through many vicissitudes and stumblings before it can have some glimpse of the depths inside. Even while supporting it, the inner nature remains undisturbed and unmoved by this lower working of the surface nature, and through these outer appearances, it keeps pointing and guiding towards the indwelling Divinity. As one awakes to that deeper presence inside, one increasingly grows aware of one’s true nature also. Among other indicators, birth was, in practice, one of the most important factors to determine the swabhava of a person, for it was based on this deeper truth that the individual soul chooses and prepares for itself the necessary outer surroundings for its self-expression. The intellectual capacity of the person, the turn of his temperament, his ethical nature, his spiritual stature are some of the other important factors that somewhat indicate the inherent nature. A keen observer can see how even in ordinary life these factors greatly influence and determine the outer acts of an individual. Also, one must not lose sight of the fact that the whole culture was surrounded by the living presence of spiritual masters and experienced teachers who by their deeper perception could, without having to depend much on the outer indicators, determine the true nature of a person and also guide and help him to move towards it. Earlier we have had a vivid discussion of how the most profound spiritual truths were brought to the door of even the lowest of the classes, of those who could never have the leisure and training to pursue these thoughts to their fountainhead. Indeed, it was this presence of spiritual masters throughout the country that animated this culture and each and every aspect of its life and guided it on the path of the soul.

Qs. If in their original purity the Varnas were based on and determined by the inner nature then how did birth come to be regarded as the indicator of Varna? Can even the qualities be transferred by heredity?

Ans. It is too complex a subject to be reduced to some arbitrary generalisations. As far as the hereditary transference of qualities is concerned, this much at least, with certainty, can be said that even though the workings of our psychology are as yet ill-understood and we do not know precisely by what means or forces the subconscious operations of mentality are conducted, but physical heredity is certainly one of those processes used by the universal nature in her more secret works. This justifies the peculiar personality traits, types of mentality, and mental tendencies of different races and social orders. But most often it is some economic division or outer profession that is confused with the Varna of a person, whereas the basis of the Varna is not superficial but spiritual. This fact becomes quite obvious when in Mahabharata and at other places in the ancient Indian literature we find not only certain individuals, but even an entire class of society engaging in the occupation or outer work prescribed for a different order. Though with time, due to intermarriage and other processes of amalgamation, the structure of the fourfold order could not retain its original purity, the law of different swabhavas of individuals was still recognised and effective. One must keep in mind that the Indian Chaturvarnya system was applicable to only an Aryan society where each individual strove to ascend, from whatever his immediate status, to a higher level of consciousness. In such a society, moved by the spiritual ideal, there could be no essential difference between a Brahmin and a Shudra, for it was well established that each one had some characteristic principle and inborn power of his nature and to act by the law of his being, the truth of his nature was the most effective means of expressing that truth and attaining spiritual liberation and perfection. Therefore, a Shudra aspiring to self-exceed would be regarded as superior even to a self-satisfied Brahmin. As regarding heredity, each class had its well-defined dharmas – its religious customs, its laws of honour, ethical rules, suitable education and training, family ideals and disciplines – which were duly binding on each and everyone in the class. The possible disparity between the hereditary function and the individual’s real inborn character and capacity was made up or minimised by education and training. For example, someone born in the Kshatriya order would be surrounded from his very childhood by the necessary education, training, injunction and discipline to get the most suitable conditions for and the best possible chances of growing in his Varna. Not only every Varna but even every outer profession and work had its own detailed and comprehensive dharmas so as to guide an individual at each step to act according to the ideal rules of conduct. But, even though binding, the application of this system was not arbitrary. In practice, it was flexible enough to leave enough room for one who had the supreme opportunity of being under the guidance of a spiritual master, or one who had received the inner call of one’s soul to follow after a deeper law. Also, the dharma of the Varna would prevail over that of the birth in cases with a clearly marked inner nature. Above all, the infallibility of such an intricate and highly evolved psychological and spiritual system, where there could be ordinarily little or no room for any errors, depended on the supreme authority and presence of the Rishi, the man of a higher spiritual experience and knowledge, born in any of the classes but generally a Brahmin or a Kshatriya, who would discover and interpret the ideal law, the dharma, and its practical meaning, and even initiate a new dharma according to the time and place. With changing time and circumstances, the hereditary convention came to be taken as the sole basis for the identification – which never had been easy even in the earlier periods – of the swabhava, for the external signs were the only ones which were easily and conveniently determinable and birth was the most handy and manageable in an increasingly mechanised, complex and conventional social order. The possible disparities or errors in the identification of the real inborn nature of a person on the basis of birth were made up or reduced to the very minimum by the above-mentioned system of laying down detailed dharmas for each Varna and by intelligently and judiciously establishing a structure of the physical, emotional and mental system of training and education, and also by the recognition of the possibility of hereditary transference of qualities. Even though it could not have been a very perfect and flawless system, it did for a long time and to a large extent serve to prevent gross distortions and corruptions from entering into the Varna system. Also, the hereditary convention was founded on this deep occult truth that the soul (the psychic being) chooses, even before birth, the surroundings, the instrumentality of mind, life and body, its qualities, faculties etc. most suitable for its growth and manifestation. And for the developing souls, there are some guardian beings that assist them in their choice.

Qs. What does it really mean when it is said that essentially there was no difference between a Brahmin and a Shudra, and the latter need not aspire to enter into the Varna of the former, for even by following and acting by the characteristic principle and truth of his nature a Shudra could move towards and attain to the highest spiritual liberation and perfection and realise the Divine? Yet, there are too many confusions and controversies that go by the term ‘Shudra’. So, what is the truth of this whole thing?

Ans. Actually, such confusions arise only when one is ignorant of the true meaning of the contextual use of this term bearing multiple significances. Being primarily concerned with an ever more vivid and faultless expression of the deeper truth, the Vedic Rishis used time and again, as need be, the same symbol or term in different contexts and with different significances. So, one may find the term ‘Shudra’ being used to denote a particular Varna, or the inner nature of a person, and the very same being used in a different context to denote the state of the unregenerate small surface consciousness.

When used in the context of the Chaturvarna system – based on the spiritual classification of our innate nature made purely from the point of view of sadhana – the term Shudra would mean the particular Swabhava or the self-nature an embodied soul uses for its self-manifestation, and could in no way carry with it the sense of any essential inferiority of a person. It is only a surface egoistic consciousness that can indulge in such ideas of caste superiority or take pride in it and look highly upon any pursuit of knowledge while looking down upon the work of hired labour and service. When it is the soul (the psychic being) itself that chooses a particular Swabhava for its terrestrial evolution and for its special manifestation, how can there possibly be an essential distinction or any actual superiority of one Swabhava over the other? And since the soul itself chooses a particular course or process of its evolution, that becomes for it also the path through which it can reach its true nature. Moreover, from a deeper view, a true spirit of service is the sure sign of the emergence of the soul. Any one-sided pursuit of self-knowledge (Atmajnana) can at best make a person sattwik, but can never lead to any real attainment. On the contrary, in any such pursuit there remains the danger of the increase of self-centeredness and the pride of knowledge which may prove to be great hindrances in one’s way to the Divine. It is, as pointed out by Yogi Sri Krishnaprem, only the sewa of Mukund, the true service of Sri Krishna, that is Nistraigunya that surpasses everything and takes one beyond all lower workings and determinisms. Therefore, from a deeper spiritual viewpoint, the shudra-bhava, the innate nature of self-giving and service, far from being an inferior movement, is rather the greatest among the four Varnas, for this nature goes straight towards complete self-surrender.

But when used within the scheme of a progressive evolution of consciousness, the term ‘Shudra’ would mean the small surface physical consciousness. It has been well-known in our culture that, except those specially gifted or endowed, men, no matter what their inner Varna may be, are generally born as ‘shudras’ with dominant unregenerate animalistic surface nature grossly occupied with the lower satisfactions of physical and vital propensities. Thus, by birth all are ‘Shudras’. Even in the course of the life of a person a discerning eye can very well see how in the beginning he is subject to the domination of Tamas and ignorance and bound to a small self-centered consciousness. As the consciousness emerges from this gross tamasic to a rajaso-tamasic state, there comes some loosening of the knot of the acute self-centeredness and, along with it, a growing sense of mutuality, interrelationship and interchange between creature and creature as the law of Life without which one could not for one moment endure. This spirit of mutuality, acquisition and accumulation is termed as Vaishya. At a higher elevation of the rajasic or kinetic quality of our nature we get the active man with a more dominant will capable of undertaking works of heroism and force. Such a person of dominant higher vital force is termed as Kshatriya. Such a nature is devoted to the pursuit of what it considers to be right or just. The emergence from Rajas to the principle of Sattwa, which has its strongest hold in the mind, makes itself manifest in a mind of reason and balance disinterestedly trying to seek the truth and the right law of things. The accomplished types of such sattwic tendency are termed as a Sadhu, or a Dwij, the twice-born, on the way to become a Vipra, the enlightened one. All these have their vitality subdued and governed by a progressively enlightened intelligence. There can possibly be no doubt that this whole scheme of division or classification of human nature is essentially psychological and qualitative based on the fundamental truth of our being and represents a gradual evolution of human consciousness. It is in view of this fundamental truth that it has always been held that all men are born in their lower nature as Shudras but in their highest inner self are Brahmanas capable of the full spirit and godhead. This psychological and qualitative classification of nature, a scheme altogether different from the Indian Chaturvarnya system, and therefore should in no way be confused with it, doesn’t pertain to Indian culture only. It is a fundamental fact of human nature universally applicable to all cultures and societies. When used in this context, the term Shudra is not representative of any particular Varna but is only meant to signify the preliminary undeveloped state of human psychology through which almost all have to pass. Therefore, it is only proper that an undeveloped physical-minded (shudra) consciousness must evolve in consciousness before it can profitably open to and make use of the deeper truths of existence. Any premature attempt at entry and handling of these truths is likely to have more or less undesirable consequences both for the person and for others. It is in this sense that the saying, ‘Janmanā Jāyate Shūdrah’, which means, ‘Everyone is born a shudra’, stays as relevant today as at the time of its inception. This is evident enough even in ordinary life how the integrity, fittingness or propriety of a person is brought into consideration before entrusting him some responsibility or when sharing with him some confidential or sensitive information, so as to safeguard the thing from any misuse by unfit hands. When placed according to this scheme of a gradual evolution of consciousness, the great majority never go beyond the two first stages. Only the rare few can ever attain the state of Dwij, that is, the state of being reborn in the spirit. Thus, in this evolutionary scheme of consciousness, all men, being shudras in their lower nature but Dwij in their inner self, begin in life with a very small (shudra) consciousness and have to evolve and ascend higher by self-culture. Moreover, the more developed the inner being, the more power it has to exert over and cultivate the outer surface nature. This has been the deeper sense of the saying ‘Sanskārāt Dwij Uchyate’, which means, ‘it is only by the inner culture that one is regenerated in a Dwij’. But mind you, the term used is not Brahmin but Dwij, the twice-born, capable of entering into the second birth by initiation and to whom alone the Vedic education can be given without danger. Even this new birth, this new opening of divine illumination in man’s consciousness recurs with the growth of the person, symbolised as the continuous succession of the Dawns in the Vedas. This is a truth clearly and incontrovertibly revealed, time and again, even in the Bhagavad Gita which declares the carrying out of the works proceeding from and determined by one’s own innate nature (swabhava) as the one road by which one can rise towards the highest inner greatness and spiritual freedom and perfection. But if only the one of Brahmin birth (varna) were fit for the initiation in integral Vedic knowledge, as contended by the advocates of the caste system, then no following of Gita’s swadharma could prevent a shudra from getting permanently debarred from this initiation and, therefore, from the highest status and perfection. Nowhere does the Gita seem to indulge in any such absurdity of contradicting its own teaching by prohibiting anyone the entry into the divine doors merely on the basis of any external distinctions. On the contrary, it declares that “If even a man of very evil conduct turns to Me with a sole and entire love, he must be regarded as a saint, for the settled will of endeavour in him is a right and complete will.” (Gita 9:30) In the light of all this discussion, this aspect or truth of the Indian culture should be deeply and clearly understood that not only a Brahmin, but every other varna too was capable of attaining the status of Dwij. This is evident enough from the examples of those spiritually attained individuals, even when of inferior birth, being revered by the whole community and readily accepted as spiritual mentors or Gurus even by those of superior lineage. Thus, the basis and the sense of the term ‘Shudra’ pertains to the essential spiritual truth of our being when it is used to denote the inner varna of a person, whereas, the very same term bears an entirely psychological sense when used to denote the stage of an unregenerate physical-minded consciousness concentrated exclusively on the surface physical self and its gross satisfactions. It is only when one fails to understand the multiple significances and their contextual use of this term that such controversies, as we find associated with it, arise. A right understanding not only reconciles any such misapprehensions but, even more, helps us grow aware of how even those aspects of this culture which at first sight may seem to be superficial, local or temporal, assume a deep, profound and universal significance and meaning when approached through a deeper perspective. ‡

(c) The System of Four Ashrams and Its Object

“The whole system of society, founded on the four varnas, was made a harmonious means for the elevation and progress of the soul, mind and life from the natural pursuit of interest and desire first to the perfection of the law of our being, Dharma, and at the end to a highest spiritual freedom. For man’s true end in life must be always this realisation of his own immortal self, this entry in its secret of an infinite and eternal existence.

The Indian system did not entirely leave this difficult growth to the individual’s unaided inner initiative. It supplied him with a framework; it gave him a scale and gradation for his life which could be made into a kind of ladder rising in that sense. This high convenience was the object of the four Asramas. Life was divided into four natural periods and each of them marked out a stage in the working out of this cultural idea of living. There was the period of the student, the period of the householder, the period of the recluse or forest-dweller, the period of the free supersocial man, parivrājaka. The student life was framed to lay the groundwork of what the man had to know, do and be. It gave a thorough training in the necessary arts, sciences, branches of knowledge, but it was still more insistent on the discipline of the ethical nature and in earlier days contained as an indispensable factor a grounding in the Vedic formula of spiritual knowledge. In these earlier days this training was given in suitable surroundings far away from the life of cities and the teacher was one who had himself passed through the round of this circle of living and, very usually, even, one who had arrived at some remarkable realisation of spiritual knowledge. But subsequently education became more intellectual and mundane; it was imparted in cities and universities and aimed less at an inner preparation of character and knowledge and more at instruction and the training of the intelligence. But in the beginning the Aryan man was really prepared in some degree for the four great objects of his life, artha, kāma, dharma, mokṣa. Entering into the householder stage to live out his knowledge, he was able to serve there the three first human objects; he satisfied his natural being and its interests and desire to take the joy of life, he paid his debt to the society and its demands and by the way he discharged his life functions he prepared himself for the last greatest purpose of his existence. In the third stage he retired to the forest and worked out in a certain seclusion the truth of his spirit. He lived in a broad freedom from the stricter social bonds; but if he so willed, gathering the young around him or receiving the inquirer and seeker, he could leave his knowledge to the new rising generation as an educator or a spiritual teacher. In the last stage of life he was free to throw off every remaining tie and to wander over the world in an extreme spiritual detachment from all the forms of social life, satisfying only the barest necessities, communing with the universal spirit, making his soul ready for eternity. This circle was not obligatory on all. The great majority never went beyond the two first stages; many passed away in the vānaprastha or forest stage. Only the rare few made the last extreme venture and took the life of the wandering recluse. But this profoundly conceived cycle gave a scheme which kept the full course of the human spirit in its view; it could be taken advantage of by all according to their actual growth and in its fullness by those who were sufficiently developed in their present birth to complete the circle.”38

IV. The Greatest Accomplishment of Indian Culture – the Web of the Sanatana Dharma

The above was the description of the framework of Indian culture from the outlook of an intellectual criticism because that is the standpoint of the critics who try to disparage its value. It has been shown above that, “...Indian culture must be adjudged even from this alien outlook to have been the creation of a wide and noble spirit. Inspired in the heart of its being by a lofty principle, illumined with a striking and uplifting idea of individual manhood and its powers and its possible perfection, aligned to a spacious plan of social architecture, it was enriched not only by a strong philosophic, intellectual and artistic creativeness but by a great and vivifying and fruitful life-power. But this by itself does not give an adequate account of its spirit or its greatness. One might describe Greek or Roman civilisation from this outlook and miss little that was of importance; but Indian civilisation was not only a great cultural system, but an immense religious effort of the human spirit.”39

‡ A deeper contemplation of this apparently simple and straightforward passage makes evident the infinite number of profound suggestions and meanings with which it is pregnant. To begin with, it is indeed curious to note that even after having said so much about the greatness of the Indian culture Sri Aurobindo here says that ‘this by itself does not give an adequate account of its spirit or its greatness’, what then could it be that still needs to be brought to light? Also, if, unlike Greek and Roman culture, the greatness of the Indian culture consisted not only in its ‘strong philosophic, intellectual and artistic creativeness and its great and vivifying and fruitful life-power’, but even more, in its being an immense religious effort of the human spirit, what then is the difference between a great cultural system and an immense religious effort of the human spirit? But we must bear in mind that all this comparison is in no way an attempt to equate the greatness of Indian culture to that of any other culture, for as has been discussed time and again, it has been established by Sri Aurobindo how in all possible fields of human thought and endeavour the achievements of this culture have been incomparably greater – both quantitatively and qualitatively – than any of the other known cultures, and even what it had in common with other cultures got from its spiritual turn a stamp of striking originality and solitary greatness. The point that needs to be emphasised here is that more than any of its other cultural achievements, the true peculiarity of the Indian culture lay in its structure of the Sanatana Dharma. It is therefore of primary importance to at least get some sense of the immense religious effort of this culture, the true role of religion, the relation between spirituality and religion, and the peculiarity of the Sanatana Dharma that makes it stand out as the most remarkable of all religious systems. As pointed out by Sri Aurobindo, the description of the fundamental aspects and motives of the Indian culture so far has been made as a response to intellectual criticism and to assert the greatness of this culture even from that outlook by refuting all misconceptions, hostile and adverse opinions and other disparagements. But the coming discussion will move more towards entering into and revealing the heart of this culture. Talking about the blessed land of India, Swami Vivekananda said, “If there is any land on this earth that can lay claim to be the blessed Punya Bhumi, to be the land to which all souls on this earth must come to account for Karma, the land to which every soul that is wending its way Godward must come to attain its last home, the land where humanity has attained its highest towards gentleness, towards generosity, towards purity, towards calmness, above all, the land of introspection and of spirituality — it is India. Hence have started the founders of religions from the most ancient times, deluging the earth again and again with the pure and perennial waters of spiritual truth. Hence have proceeded the tidal waves of philosophy that have covered the earth, East or West, North or South, and hence again must start the wave which is going to spiritualise the material civilisation of the world. Here is the life-giving water with which must be quenched the burning fire of materialism which is burning the core of the hearts of millions in other lands. Believe me, my friends, this is going to be.” (CWSV 3: 104-05)

Indian philosophy is founded on deep spiritual intuition and spiritual revelation, and Indian religion is, essentially, Indian spiritual philosophy put into action and experience. The keynote of that philosophy is this mighty ever-memorable formula, ‘Aham Brahmasmi, Tattvamasi, sarvam khalu idam Brahma’, which means ‘I am Brahman, Thou are Brahman, Verily, all that there is is Brahman’. Not only all that there is in this phenomenal universe is Brahman, but even all that is not there or even beyond this manifestation, that too is Brahman alone. The being of the Brahman is so Absolute that It cannot in its essentiality be limited to even the highest of the human conceptions and surpasses all the various autonomies – of Being and Non-being, Personality or Impersonality, and various others – attributed to It by the human mind. But a thing of yet greater significance lies in this fundamental realisation that in one’s own true being one is none other than That All-Pervading Transcendent Brahman, or rather say, Brahman is one’s very own true self. Furthermore, even all that appears to be other than one’s individual self – a perception resulting from a sense of separate individual personality in this terrestrial manifestation – that too is verily Brahman. When religion tries to put into practice such a sublime spiritual revelation, the thing of primary concern for it is to try to see, recognise and establish contact with that Omnipresent Brahman in each thing, every movement, each and every part of our being. The least little thing, or act or form – even when apparently a complete negation of the Divine – in which one fails to see and accept the Divine is as though one were missing the opportunity of establishing contact with the Divine to that extent. The Puranas and other ancient Indian literature has always insisted upon growing conscious of and turning towards the Divine manifested in this whole universe. The Bhagavat puts it beautifully, “that you must turn all your senses Godward: words must be used to sing His praises; eyes directed to the saints in whom He presides; the ears dedicated to hear them; hands taught to worship His feet and, lastly, your head must bow down in reverence to the world throbbing with His consciousness; that is called jagat-pranam.” (Bhagavat 10.10.38) Even an authoritative scripture like the Gita reiterates the very same truth in the Yoga of Vibhuti that verily, all that there is is the Divine Himself and there can be nothing other than Him, but he is especially apparent to us in whatever is of a pre-eminent value or seems to act with a powerful and pre-eminent force. It is for this reason that a special significance has always been given to the person or the thing in or through which the Divine has chosen to reveal Himself most effectively. But as revealed by the Lord Himself in the Gita, this phenomenon of Vibhuti or the special manifestation of the Divine is not confined to Gods or human beings only, but can be found in the Titans, demons and animals, even in all the elements in nature, in human qualities, in each and every movement of human psychology, in fact, in all that there is in this manifestation. Once having recognised the presence of the Divine in each and everything, the work of religion then is to help in establishing a contact and relation with that Divine in all the parts of our being. However seemingly high, sublime and distant this aim may be, still one has to start moving towards it from whatever one’s immediate position.

As has been incidentally discussed earlier also, an individual being is a sum of infinite complexity – such as, various parts of the being, various levels of consciousness, different stages of inner and outer development, various traits of subjective nature, and so on, – therefore, in its pursuit of bringing the whole being into contact with the Divine, religion must take into account this infinite complexity, the sum of which not only varies from person to person but even in one person the balance changes from time to time. Also, as compared to the higher parts it is way too difficult to bring the lower recalcitrant members, the mechanical and hedonistic parts of our being into light and turn them towards the Divine. But even their claim was not ignored but given its due importance. For it was understood that they too had a deeper truth of their own and only by finding that truth, by realising the Divine in their own manner, can they attain their true fulfilment. Therefore, the whole effort of the Tantra, the Vaishnava religion, and numerous other systems in this culture, has been to somehow bring the entire being of man, all his subjective and objective movements, each and every stage of his inner and outer development into contact with the Divine and unite with him. It was with this end in view that the whole atmosphere of the society was so surrounded by a mass of suggestive ceremonies, effective rituals, strict outward rules and injunctions, and other such symbols that would at each step remind a person of and help him to come into contact with the Divine presence behind all that there is in, or even beyond, this terrestrial manifestation. ‡

A. The Whole Root of Difference between Indian and European Culture

“The whole root of difference between Indian and European culture springs from the spiritual aim of Indian civilisation. It is the turn which this aim imposes on all the rich and luxuriant variety of its forms and rhythms that gives to it its unique character. For even what it has in common with other cultures gets from that turn a stamp of striking originality and solitary greatness. A spiritual aspiration was the governing force of this culture, its core of thought, its ruling passion. Not only did it make spirituality the highest aim of life, but it even tried, as far as that could be done in the past conditions of the human race, to turn the whole of life towards spirituality. But since religion is in the human mind the first native, if imperfect form of the spiritual impulse, the predominance of the spiritual idea, its endeavour to take hold of life, necessitated a casting of thought and action into the religious mould and a persistent filling of every circumstance of life with the religious sense; it demanded a pervadingly religio-philosophic culture. The highest spirituality indeed moves in a free and wide air far above that lower stage of seeking which is governed by religious form and dogma; it does not easily bear their limitations and, even when it admits, it transcends them; it lives in an experience which to the formal religious mind is unintelligible. But man does not arrive immediately at that highest inner elevation and, if it were demanded from him at once, he would never arrive there. At first he needs lower supports and stages of ascent; he asks for some scaffolding of dogma, worship, image, sign, form, symbol, some indulgence and permission of mixed half-natural motive on which he can stand while he builds up in him the temple of the spirit. Only when the temple is completed, can the supports be removed, the scaffolding disappear. The religious culture which now goes by the name of Hinduism not only fulfilled this purpose, but, unlike certain credal religions, it knew its purpose. It gave itself no name, because it set itself no sectarian limits; it claimed no universal adhesion, asserted no sole infallible dogma, set up no single narrow path or gate of salvation; it was less a creed or cult than a continuously enlarging tradition of the Godward endeavour of the human spirit. An immense many-sided many-staged provision for a spiritual self-building and self-finding, it had some right to speak of itself by the only name it knew, the eternal religion, sanātana dharma. It is only if we have a just and right appreciation of this sense and spirit of Indian religion that we can come to an understanding of the true sense and spirit of Indian culture.

Now just here is the first baffling difficulty over which the European mind stumbles; for it finds itself unable to make out what Hindu religion is. Where, it asks, is its soul? where is its mind and fixed thought? where is the form of its body? How can there be a religion which has no rigid dogmas demanding belief on pain of eternal damnation, no theological postulates, even no fixed theology, no credo distinguishing it from antagonistic or rival religions? How can there be a religion which has no papal head, no governing ecclesiastic body, no church, chapel or congregational system, no binding religious form of any kind obligatory on all its adherents, no one administration and discipline? For the Hindu priests are mere ceremonial officiants without any ecclesiastical authority or disciplinary powers and the Pundits are mere interpreters of the Shastra, not the lawgivers of the religion or its rulers. How again can Hinduism be called a religion when it admits all beliefs, allowing even a kind of high-reaching atheism and agnosticism and permits all possible spiritual experiences, all kinds of religious adventures? The only thing fixed, rigid, positive, clear is the social law, and even that varies in different castes, regions, communities. The caste rules and not the Church; but even the caste cannot punish a man for his beliefs, ban heterodoxy or prevent his following a new revolutionary doctrine or a new spiritual leader. If it excommunicates Christian or Muslim, it is not for religious belief or practice, but because they break with the social rule and order. It has been asserted in consequence that there is no such thing as a Hindu religion, but only a Hindu social system with a bundle of the most disparate religious beliefs and institutions. The precious dictum that Hinduism is a mass of folk-lore with an ineffective coat of metaphysical daubing is perhaps the final judgment of the superficial occidental mind on this matter.

This misunderstanding springs from the total difference of outlook on religion that divides the Indian mind and the normal Western intelligence. The difference is so great that it could only be bridged by a supple philosophical training or a wide spiritual culture; but the established forms of religion and the rigid methods of philosophical thought practised in the West make no provision and even allow no opportunity for either. To the Indian mind the least important part of religion is its dogma; the religious spirit matters, not the theological credo. On the contrary to the Western mind a fixed intellectual belief is the most important part of a cult; it is its core of meaning, it is the thing that distinguishes it from others. For it is its formulated beliefs that make it either a true or a false religion, according as it agrees or does not agree with the credo of its critic. This notion, however foolish and shallow, is a necessary consequence of the Western idea which falsely supposes that intellectual truth is the highest verity and, even, that there is no other. The Indian religious thinker knows that all the highest eternal verities are truths of the spirit. The supreme truths are neither the rigid conclusions of logical reasoning nor the affirmations of credal statement, but fruits of the soul’s inner experience. Intellectual truth is only one of the doors to the outer precincts of the temple. And since intellectual truth turned towards the Infinite must be in its very nature many-sided and not narrowly one, the most varying intellectual beliefs can be equally true because they mirror different facets of the Infinite. However separated by intellectual distance, they still form so many side-entrances which admit the mind to some faint ray from a supreme Light. There are no true and false religions, but rather all religions are true in their own way and degree. Each is one of the thousand paths to the One Eternal.”40

B. The Four Necessities of Human Life

“Indian religion placed four necessities before human life. First, it imposed upon the mind a belief in a highest consciousness or state of existence universal and transcendent of the universe, from which all comes, in which all lives and moves without knowing it and of which all must one day grow aware, returning towards that which is perfect, eternal and infinite. Next, it laid upon the individual life the need of self-preparation by development and experience till man is ready for an effort to grow consciously into the truth of this greater existence. Thirdly, it provided it with a well-founded, well-explored, many-branching and always enlarging way of knowledge and of spiritual or religious discipline. Lastly, for those not yet ready for these higher steps it provided an organisation of the individual and collective life, a framework of personal and social discipline and conduct, of mental and moral and vital development by which they could move each in his own limits and according to his own nature in such a way as to become eventually ready for the greater existence. The first three of these elements are the most essential to any religion, but Hinduism has always attached to the last also a great importance; it has left out no part of life as a thing secular and foreign to the religious and spiritual life. Still the Indian religious tradition is not merely the form of a religio-social system, as the ignorant critic vainly imagines. However greatly that may count at the moment of a social departure, however stubbornly the conservative religious mind may oppose all pronounced or drastic change, still the core of Hinduism is a spiritual, not a social discipline. Actually we find religions like Sikhism counted in the Vedic family although they broke down the old social tradition and invented a novel form, while the Jains and Buddhists were traditionally considered to be outside the religious fold although they observed Hindu social custom and intermarried with Hindus, because their spiritual system and teaching figured in its origin as a denial of the truth of Veda and a departure from the continuity of the Vedic line. In all these four elements that constitute Hinduism there are major and minor differences between Hindus of various sects, schools, communities and races; but nevertheless there is also a general unity of spirit, of fundamental type and form and of spiritual temperament which creates in this vast fluidity an immense force of cohesion and a strong principle of oneness.”41

C. The Fundamental Idea and the Core of Indian Religion

“...Indian religion is founded upon three basic ideas or rather three fundamentals of a highest and widest spiritual experience. First comes the idea of the One Existence of the Veda to whom sages give different names, the One without a second of the Upanishads who is all that is and beyond all that is, the Permanent of the Buddhists, the Absolute of the Illusionists, the supreme God or Purusha of the Theists who holds in his power the soul and Nature, – in a word the Eternal, the Infinite. This is the first common foundation; but it can be and is expressed in an endless variety of formulas by the human intelligence. To discover and closely approach and enter into whatever kind or degree of unity with this Permanent, this Infinite, this Eternal, is the highest height and last effort of its spiritual experience. That is the first universal credo of the religious mind of India.

Admit in whatever formula this foundation, follow this great spiritual aim by one of the thousand paths recognised in India or even any new path which branches off from them and you are at the core of the religion. For its second basic idea is the manifold way of man’s approach to the Eternal and Infinite. The Infinite is full of many infinities and each of these infinities is itself the very Eternal. And here in the limitations of the cosmos God manifests himself and fulfils himself in the world in many ways, but each is the way of the Eternal. For in each finite we can discover and through all things as his forms and symbols we can approach the Infinite; all cosmic powers are manifestations, all forces are forces of the One. The gods behind the workings of Nature are to be seen and adored as powers, names and personalities of the one Godhead. An infinite Conscious-Force, executive Energy, Will or Law, Maya, Prakriti, Shakti or Karma, is behind all happenings, whether to us they seem good or bad, acceptable or inacceptable, fortunate or adverse. The Infinite creates and is Brahma; it preserves and is Vishnu; it destroys or takes to itself and is Rudra or Shiva. The supreme Energy beneficent in upholding and protection is or else formulates itself as the Mother of the worlds, Luxmi or Durga. Or beneficent even in the mask of destruction, it is Chandi or it is Kali, the dark Mother. The One Godhead manifests himself in the form of his qualities in various names and godheads. The God of divine love of the Vaishnava, the God of divine power of the Shakta appear as two different godheads; but in truth they are the one infinite Deity in different figures.[6] One may approach the Supreme through any of these names and forms, with knowledge or in ignorance; for through them and beyond them we can proceed at last to the supreme experience.

One thing however has to be noted that while many modernised Indian religionists tend, by way of an intellectual compromise with modern materialistic rationalism, to explain away these things as symbols, the ancient Indian religious mentality saw them not only as symbols but as world-realities, – even if to the Illusionist realities only of the world of Maya. For between the highest unimaginable Existence and our material way of being the spiritual and psychic knowledge of India did not fix a gulf as between two unrelated opposites. It was aware of other psychological planes of consciousness and experience and the truths of these supraphysical planes were no less real to it than the outward truths of the material universe. Man approaches God at first according to his psychological nature and his capacity for deeper experience, svabhāva, adhikāra. The level of Truth, the plane of consciousness he can reach is determined by his inner evolutionary stage. Thence comes the variety of religious cult, but its data are not imaginary structures, inventions of priests or poets, but truths of a supraphysical existence intermediate between the consciousness of the physical world and the ineffable superconscience of the Absolute.

The third idea of strongest consequence at the base of Indian religion is the most dynamic for the inner spiritual life. It is that while the Supreme or the Divine can be approached through a universal consciousness and by piercing through all inner and outer Nature, That or He can be met by each individual soul in itself, in its own spiritual part, because there is something in it that is intimately one or at least intimately related with the one divine Existence. The essence of Indian religion is to aim at so growing and so living that we can grow out of the Ignorance which veils this self-knowledge from our mind and life and become aware of the Divinity within us. These three things put together are the whole of Hindu religion, its essential sense and, if any credo is needed, its credo.”42

‡ Indian religion founded itself on this fundamental spiritual truth that the One Supreme Transcendent, Eternal Being is the origin and basis of everything. The whole web of Sanatana Dharma is an out-flowering and an expression of this fundamental truth in various forms. Since there can be no separate independent existence other than this One Supreme Being, therefore all that one comes into or can ever come into contact with or experience in one’s subjective or objective being is that One Supreme Being. Moreover, all the innumerable forms that one comes across in this terrestrial manifestation are but forms and parts of that Being alone and each of these forms perceives, experiences and comes into contact with the Divine in its own way which has a deep truth in it and cannot therefore be ignored. Such catholicity of approach that admits all possible ways of realising and expressing the Divine leaves no room for any kind of one-sidedness or intolerance in the religion. And since everything in its spiritual reality is the very Divine, therefore it is only proper that each one of his infinite manifestations, however partial its actual manifestation in Nature, should be approached and dealt with in that spirit only. Therefore, the only kartavyam karma in life, the only thing worthwhile to be done is to realise that Divine presence within oneself and in the entire manifestation, increasingly come into contact with it and express it. It is when viewed with this perspective that it becomes evident how the Indian religion has been an immense effort of putting this one fundamental truth into practice. The profound truth and deep rationale behind all the various forms – whether they be of inner spiritual nature, ideative or intellectual, or even ritualistic or ceremonial – that the Sanatana Dharma developed in the course of its unfolding, become more and more clear in the light of this truth. ‡

“Indian religion never considered intellectual or theological conceptions about the supreme Truth to be the one thing of central importance. To pursue that Truth under whatever conception or whatever form, to attain to it by inner experience, to live in it in consciousness, this it held to be the sole thing needful. One school or sect might consider the real self of man to be indivisibly one with the universal Self or the supreme Spirit. Another might regard man as one with the Divine in essence but different from him in Nature. A third might hold God, Nature and the individual soul in man to be three eternally different powers of being. But for all the truth of Self held with equal force; for even to the Indian dualist God is the supreme self and reality in whom and by whom Nature and man live, move and have their being and, if you eliminate God from his view of things, Nature and man would lose for him all their meaning and importance.... Differences of credal belief are to the Indian mind nothing more than various ways of seeing the one Self and Godhead in all. Self-realisation is the one thing needful; to open to the inner Spirit, to live in the Infinite, to seek after and discover the Eternal, to be in union with God, that is the common idea and aim of religion, that is the sense of spiritual salvation, that is the living Truth that fulfils and releases. This dynamic following after the highest spiritual truth and the highest spiritual aim are the uniting bond of Indian religion and, behind all its thousand forms, its one common essence.

‡ The peculiarity of the Indian religion has been that it has always given primary importance to the deeper motive, the spirit in the act, and only a secondary value to any intellectual speculations. Even in our Purana literature one may find this truth revealed through various stories, anecdotes and other references that the spirit of love, devotion, faith and total consecration – even when directed ignorantly and to a limited or small object of worship – is far more effective than all philosophisings and can lead the aspirant straight to some highest experience and realisation. Therefore, the one thing truly important is to find a way of realising that truth, pursue it, attain it and live in it. Deliberating on how the intellectual representation of the spiritual truths has taken two completely divergent lines in the East and the West, Sri Aurobindo writes at one place that unlike the philosophy in Europe which, being detached from its deeper roots, has been more of a purely mental gymnastic of speculative logic in the air, the Indian philosophy has always had its roots in deep spiritual experience and therefore has always been influenced by it. He says, “When, somewhere between the seventh and fifth centuries B.C., men began both in the East and West to intellectualise knowledge, this Truth survived in the East; in the West, where the intellect began to be accepted as the sole or highest instrument for the discovery of Truth, it began to fade. But still it has there too tried constantly to return; the Neo-Platonists brought it back, and now, it appears, the Neo-Hegelians and others (e.g., the Russian Ouspensky and one or two German thinkers, I believe) seem to be reaching after it. But still there is a difference.

In the East, especially in India, the metaphysical thinkers have tried, as in the West, to determine the nature of the highest Truth by the intellect. But, in the first place, they have not given mental thinking the supreme rank as an instrument in the discovery of Truth, but only a secondary status. The first rank has always been given to spiritual intuition and illumination and spiritual experience; an intellectual conclusion that contradicts this supreme authority is held invalid. Secondly, each philosophy has armed itself with a practical way of reaching to the supreme state of consciousness, so that even when one begins with Thought, the aim is to arrive at a consciousness beyond mental thinking. Each philosophical founder (as also those who continued his work or school) has been a metaphysical thinker doubled with a Yogi. Those who were only philosophic intellectuals were respected for their learning but never took rank as truth discoverers. And the philosophies that lacked a sufficiently powerful means of spiritual experience died out and became things of the past because they were not dynamic for spiritual discovery and realisation.

In the West it was just the opposite that came to pass. Thought, intellect, the logical reason came to be regarded more and more as the highest means and even the highest end; in philosophy, Thought is the be-all and the end-all. It is by intellectual thinking and speculation that the truth is to be discovered; even spiritual experience has been summoned to pass the tests of the intellect, if it is to be held valid — just the reverse of the Indian position.” (CWSA 28, 353-54)

Certainly, one finds a tendency to serious debates and metaphysical thinking in India in the period of intellectual and mental representation of spiritual truths. But even there, a careful study of the account of the great logicians — and to take for this purpose only three striking ones among a multitude, Shankaracharya, Ramanujacharya and Chaitanya Mahaprabhu — testifies how all their metaphysical disquisition and debate was in most part not dry mental logic devoid of any deeper truth, but was always based on a deep spiritual experience completely in agreement with the Vedic tradition. Take for instance the example of Sri Prakashananda Saraswati, a great Vedantist and scholar, whose erudition was highly reputed throughout India and who had a large number of disciples. After having met and conversed with Sri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu he realized that Sri Chaitanya was not of ordinary humankind and the divinity manifesting through him was more sublime and far superior to any mental reasonings and philosophies. Being deeply moved by this, he relinquished without any delay his all – monastery, disciples, position, fame, etc. – and readily accepted Sri Chaitanya Mahaprabhu as his guru and became his disciple. Even the account available in Indian history of the various grand metaphysical debates shows how a debate moves not by logic and almost always at the end of the discussion the one through whom the spirit has chosen to express itself more potently and the one whose knowledge and experience prove to be deeper than his adversary’s, is the conqueror and is gladly and reverentially accepted by the opponent as his superior. ‡

If there were nothing else to be said in favour of the spiritual genius of the Indian people or the claim of Indian civilisation to stand in the front rank as a spiritual culture, it would be sufficiently substantiated by this single fact that not only was this greatest and widest spiritual truth seen in India with the boldest largeness, felt and expressed with a unique intensity, and approached from all possible sides, but it was made consciously the grand uplifting idea of life, the core of all thinking, the foundation of all religion, the secret sense and declared ultimate aim of human existence. The truth announced is not peculiar to Indian thinking; it has been seen and followed by the highest minds and souls everywhere. But elsewhere it has been the living guide only of a few thinkers, or of some rare mystics or exceptionally gifted spiritual natures. The mass of men have had no understanding, no distant perception, not even a reflected glimpse of this something Beyond; they have lived only in the lower sectarian side of religion, in inferior ideas of the Deity or in the outward mundane aspects of life. But Indian culture did succeed by the strenuousness of its vision, the universality of its approach, the intensity of its seeking in doing what has been done by no other culture. It succeeded in stamping religion with the essential ideal of a real spirituality; it brought some living reflection of the very highest spiritual truth and some breath of its influence into every part of the religious field. Nothing can be more untrue than to pretend that the general religious mind of India has not at all grasped the higher spiritual or metaphysical truths of Indian religion. It is a sheer falsehood or a wilful misunderstanding to say that it has lived always in the externals only of rite and creed and shibboleth. On the contrary, the main metaphysical truths of Indian religious philosophy in their broad idea-aspects or in an intensely poetic and dynamic representation have been stamped on the general mind of the people. The ideas of Maya, Lila, divine Immanence are as familiar to the man in the street and the worshipper in the temple as to the philosopher in his seclusion, the monk in his monastery and the saint in his hermitage. The spiritual reality which they reflect, the profound experience to which they point, has permeated the religion, the literature, the art, even the popular religious songs of a whole people. It is true that these things are realised by the mass of men more readily through the fervour of devotion than by a strenuous effort of thinking; but that is as it must and should be since the heart of man is nearer to the Truth than his intelligence.

It is true, too, that the tendency to put too much stress on externals has always been there and worked to overcloud the deeper spiritual motive; but that is not peculiar to India, it is a common failing of human nature, not less but rather more evident in Europe than in Asia. It has needed a constant stream of saints and religious thinkers and the teaching of illuminated Sannyasins to keep the reality vivid and resist the deadening weight of form and ceremony and ritual. But the fact remains that these messengers of the spirit have never been wanting. And the still more significant fact remains that there has never been wanting either a happy readiness in the common mind to listen to the message. The ordinary materialised souls, the external minds are the majority in India as everywhere. How easy it is for the superior European critic to forget this common fact of our humanity and treat this turn as a peculiar sin of the Indian mentality! But at least the people of India, even the “ignorant masses” have this distinction that they are by centuries of training nearer to the inner realities, are divided from them by a less thick veil of the universal ignorance and are more easily led back to a vital glimpse of God and Spirit, self and eternity than the mass of men or even the cultured elite anywhere else. Where else could the lofty, austere and difficult teaching of a Buddha have seized so rapidly on the popular mind? Where else could the songs of a Tukaram, a Ramprasad, a Kabir, the Sikh gurus and the chants of the Tamil saints with their fervid devotion but also their profound spiritual thinking have found so speedy an echo and formed a popular religious literature? This strong permeation or close nearness of the spiritual turn, this readiness of the mind of a whole nation to turn to the highest realities is the sign and fruit of an age-long, a real and a still living and supremely spiritual culture.”43

[6] This explanation of Indian polytheism is not a modern invention created to meet Western reproaches; it is to be found explicitly stated in the Gita; it is, still earlier, the sense of the Upanishads; it was clearly stated in so many words in the first ancient days by the “primitive” poets (in truth the profound mystics) of the Veda.

D. The Liberty of Religious Practice and Complete Freedom of Thought in Indian Religion

“The endless variety of Indian philosophy and religion seems to the European mind interminable, bewildering, wearisome, useless; it is unable to see the forest because of the richness and luxuriance of its vegetation; it misses the common spiritual life in the multitude of its forms. But this infinite variety is itself, as Vivekananda pertinently pointed out, a sign of a superior religious culture. The Indian mind has always realised that the Supreme is the Infinite; it has perceived, right from its Vedic beginnings, that to the soul in Nature the Infinite must always present itself in an endless variety of aspects. The mentality of the West has long cherished the aggressive and quite illogical idea of a single religion for all mankind, a religion universal by the very force of its narrowness, one set of dogmas, one cult, one system of ceremonies, one array of prohibitions and injunctions, one ecclesiastical ordinance. That narrow absurdity prances about as the one true religion which all must accept on peril of persecution by men here and spiritual rejection or fierce eternal punishment by God in other worlds. This grotesque creation of human unreason, the parent of so much intolerance, cruelty, obscurantism and aggressive fanaticism, has never been able to take firm hold of the free and supple mind of India. Men everywhere have common human failings, and intolerance and narrowness especially in the matter of observances there has been and is in India. There has been much violence of theological disputation, there have been querulous bickerings of sects with their pretensions to spiritual superiority and greater knowledge, and sometimes, at one time especially in southern India in a period of acute religious differences, there have been brief local outbreaks of active mutual tyranny and persecution even unto death. But these things have never taken the proportions which they assumed in Europe. Intolerance has been confined for the most part to the minor forms of polemical attack or to social obstruction or ostracism; very seldom have they transgressed across the line to the major forms of barbaric persecution which draw a long, red and hideous stain across the religious history of Europe. There has played ever in India the saving perception of a higher and purer spiritual intelligence, which has had its effect on the mass mentality. Indian religion has always felt that since the minds, the temperaments, the intellectual affinities of men are unlimited in their variety, a perfect liberty of thought and of worship must be allowed to the individual in his approach to the Infinite.

India recognised authority of spiritual experience and knowledge, but she recognised still more the need of variety of spiritual experience and knowledge. Even in the days of decline when the claim of authority became in too many directions rigorous and excessive, she still kept the saving perception that there could not be one but must be many authorities. An alert readiness to acknowledge new light capable of enlarging the old tradition has always been characteristic of the religious mind in India. Indian civilisation did not develop to a last logical conclusion its earlier political and social liberties, – that greatness of freedom or boldness of experiment belongs to the West; but liberty of religious practice and a complete freedom of thought in religion as in every other matter have always counted among its constant traditions. The atheist and the agnostic were free from persecution in India. Buddhism and Jainism might be disparaged as unorthodox religions, but they were allowed to live freely side by side with the orthodox creeds and philosophies; in her eager thirst for truth she gave them their full chance, tested all their values, and as much of their truth as was assimilable was taken into the stock of the common and always enlarging continuity of her spiritual experience. That ageless continuity was carefully conserved, but it admitted light from all quarters. In latter times the saints who reached some fusion of the Hindu and the Islamic teaching were freely and immediately recognised as leaders of Hindu religion, – even, in some cases, when they started with a Mussulman birth and from the Mussulman standpoint. The Yogin who developed a new path of Yoga, the religious teacher who founded a new order, the thinker who built up a novel statement of the many-sided truth of spiritual existence, found no serious obstacle to their practice or their propaganda. At most they had to meet the opposition of the priest and pundit instinctively adverse to any change; but this had only to be lived down for the new element to be received into the free and pliant body of the national religion and its ever plastic order.”44

‡ There are a few points here that need to be viewed in the right perspective. First of all, we need to have a just understanding and right view of the failings or the lapses of this culture mentioned here by Sri Aurobindo, without which, one always runs a risk of falling prey to that exaggerated outlook of the West that arises from an utterly unsympathetic and adverse point of view, and even more, due to a mentality tainted with malicious and vested motives bent on representing these failings as the whole of the Indian culture. This adverse outlook on Indian culture has established its roots deeply even in the mentality of a lot of those Indians who, isolated from their native spiritual culture and its genius due to their English education, are enamoured of the Occidental culture and values which is increasingly reflected in our textbooks, media and all the other possible avenues of expression. A critical appraisal, even when it is made on sympathetic grounds, can be of any value only when it looks at the subject of its inquiry in its entirety and not in isolated parts. Therefore, when talking of the defects of this culture, such as the violence of theological disputation, querulous bickerings of sects with their pretensions to spiritual superiority and greater knowledge, acute religious differences, mutual tyranny of classes, etc., one must try to look at them from the perspective of Indian culture, only then one can hope to arrive at a just understanding and an appropriate view of them. Besides, it must be clearly understood that all such problems as mentioned here are not peculiar to this culture and religion but are common failings of the egoistic and unregenerate human nature which always tends towards appropriating and possessing things for its own narrow self and asserting as right and superior all that seems to it to belong to its ego – its own opinions, prejudices, its caste, class, sect, etc. But the peculiarity of the Indian culture lay in a greater regulation and sublimation of these tendencies than can be seen in any of the other known cultures of the world. This is why, being deeply pained and annoyed by the abuses incessantly hurled against the Indian religion by the West, Swami Vivekananda said, “What have the Hindus done to these disciples of Christ that every Christian child is taught to call the Hindus “vile”, and “wretches”, and the most horrible devils on earth? Part of the Sunday School education for children here consists in teaching them to hate everybody who is not a Christian, and the Hindus especially, so that, from their very childhood they may subscribe their pennies to the missions. If not for truth’s sake, for the sake of the morality of their own children, the Christian missionaries ought not to allow such things going on. Is it any wonder that such children grow up to be ruthless and cruel men and women? The greater a preacher can paint the tortures of eternal hell — the fire that is burning there, the brimstone — the higher is his position among the orthodox. A servant-girl in the employ of a friend of mine had to be sent to a lunatic asylum as a result of her attending what they call here the revivalist-preaching. The dose of hell-fire and brimstone was too much for her. Look again at the books published in Madras against the Hindu religion. If a Hindu writes one such line against the Christian religion, the missionaries will cry fire and vengeance.

My countrymen, I have been more than a year in this country. I have seen almost every corner of the society, and, after comparing notes, let me tell you that neither are we devils, as the missionaries tell the world we are, nor are they angels, as they claim to be. The less the missionaries talk of immorality, infanticide, and the evils of the Hindu marriage system, the better for them. There may be actual pictures of some countries before which all the imaginary missionary pictures of the Hindu society will fade away into light. But my mission in life is not to be a paid reviler. I will be the last man to claim perfection for the Hindu society. No man is more conscious of the defects that are therein, or the evils that have grown up under centuries of misfortunes. If, foreign friends, you come with genuine sympathy to help and not to destroy, Godspeed to you. But if by abuses, incessantly hurled against the head of a prostrate race in season and out of season, you mean only the triumphant assertion of the moral superiority of your own nation, let me tell you plainly, if such a comparison be instituted with any amount of justice, the Hindu will be found head and shoulders above all other nations in the world as a moral race.” (CWSV 4, 345-46) Similarly, when comparing the Indian and Western culture with regard to the freedom of thought or liberty of religious practice and the readiness to accept any change in the society, we find that each new change in the West had to make its way through much violence and bloodshed whereas, in India, no such serious obstacle is to be found. The most that one had to encounter here was that opposition of the tamasic human nature which instinctively resists any change and tries to perpetuate forever the old order of things. It has been characteristic of the religious mind of India that it has always been supple enough to take in new elements and give them their rightful place in the whole system. But truly speaking, all this flexibility and inclusiveness could persist because of her deep age-long fidelity to her spiritual ideal that has always held on firmly to the highest spiritual insight and which, in spite of all appearances, upholds this culture even to this day. What more evident proof of this spiritual element being active at the core and firmly upholding this culture could there be than the fact that it could triumphantly endure and survive such conditions of physical, psychological and cultural atrocities and sufferings imposed by foreign invaders as would have been hardly possible for any other culture to withstand and survive? Even when the very backbone of this culture was being attacked by foreign invaders, efforts were being made to systematically destroy and corrupt its very foundation – ‘the Vedas’ and other scriptures, the entire fabric of individual and collective life was being torn apart and exploited for their own self-interests, and the nakedness of country and the squalor of her poverty were being flung in her face as evidence of the worthlessness of her culture, to have firmly held on to its faith in its spiritual ideal even in the face of such grim conditions is a virtue the like of which is hardly to be seen in any other culture. Being deeply shaken by the atrocities of British Rule in India, Swami Vivekananda wrote in one of his letters, “There has been a reign of terror in India for some years. English soldiers are killing our men and outraging our women — only to be sent home with passage and pension at our expense. We are in a terrible gloom — where is the Lord?” (CWSV 8, 476-77) But indeed it is the Divine Mother herself who upholds this nation and its culture. At present, when mankind is undergoing an evolutionary crisis, and especially India, which has become the symbolic representation of all the difficulties of modern mankind, we need to have an unshakable faith in the Divine Mother, and call upon Her to save this nation and the entire human race and lead them to their true goal. ‡

E. The Combination of a Firm Spiritual Order with an Untrammelled Spiritual Freedom

“The necessity of a firm spiritual order as well as an untrammelled spiritual freedom was always perceived; but it was provided for in various ways and not in any one formal, external or artificial manner. It was founded in the first place on the recognition of an ever enlarging number of authorised scriptures. Of these scriptures some like the Gita possessed a common and widespread authority, others were peculiar to sects or schools: some like the Vedas were supposed to have an absolute, others a relative binding force. But the very largest freedom of interpretation was allowed, and this prevented any of these authoritative books from being turned into an instrument of ecclesiastical tyranny or a denial of freedom to the human mind and spirit. Another instrument of order was the power of family and communal tradition, kuladharma, persistent but not immutable. A third was the religious authority of the Brahmins; as priests they officiated as the custodians of observance, as scholars, acting in a much more important and respected role than the officiating priesthood could claim, – for to the priesthood no great consideration was given in India, – they stood as the exponents of religious tradition and were a strong conservative power. Finally, and most characteristically, most powerfully, order was secured by the succession of Gurus or spiritual teachers, paramparā, who preserved the continuity of each spiritual system and handed it down from generation to generation but were empowered also, unlike the priest and the Pundit, to enrich freely its significance and develop its practice. A living and moving, not a rigid continuity, was the characteristic turn of the inner religious mind of India. The evolution of the Vaishnava religion from very early times, its succession of saints and teachers, the striking developments given to it successively by Ramanuja, Madhwa, Chaitanya, Vallabhacharya and its recent stirrings of survival after a period of languor and of some fossilisation form one notable example of this firm combination of age long continuity and fixed tradition with latitude of powerful and vivid change. A more striking instance was the founding of the Sikh religion, its long line of Gurus and the novel direction and form given to it by Guru Govind Singh in the democratic institution of the Khalsa. The Buddhist Sangha and its councils, the creation of a sort of divided pontifical authority by Shankaracharya, an authority transmitted from generation to generation for more than a thousand years and even now not altogether effete, the Sikh Khalsa, the adoption of the congregational form called Samaj by the modern reforming sects indicate an attempt towards a compact and stringent order. But it is noteworthy that even in these attempts the freedom and plasticity and living sincerity of the religious mind of India always prevented it from initiating anything like the overblown ecclesiastical orders and despotic hierarchies which in the West have striven to impose the tyranny of their obscurantist yoke on the spiritual liberty of the human race.

The instinct for order and freedom at once in any field of human activity is always a sign of a high natural capacity in that field, and a people which could devise such a union of unlimited religious liberty with an always orderly religious evolution, must be credited with a high religious capacity, even as they cannot be denied its inevitable fruit, a great, ancient and still living spiritual culture. It is this absolute freedom of thought and experience and this provision of a framework sufficiently flexible and various to ensure liberty and yet sufficiently sure and firm to be the means of a stable and powerful evolution that have given to Indian civilisation this wonderful and seemingly eternal religion with its marvellous wealth of many-sided philosophies, of great scriptures, of profound religious works, of religions that approach the Eternal from every side of his infinite Truth, of Yoga-systems of psycho-spiritual discipline and self-finding, of suggestive forms, symbols and ceremonies which are strong to train the mind at all stages of development towards the Godward endeavour. Its firm structure capable of supporting without peril a large tolerance and assimilative spirit, its vivacity, intensity, profundity and multitudinousness of experience, its freedom from the unnatural European divorce between mundane knowledge and science on the one side and religion on the other, its reconciliation of the claims of the intellect with the claims of the spirit, its long endurance and infinite capacity of revival make it stand out today as the most remarkable, rich and living of all religious systems. The nineteenth century has thrown on it its tremendous shock of negation and scepticism but has not been able to destroy its assured roots of spiritual knowledge. A little disturbed for a brief moment, surprised and temporarily shaken by this attack in a period of greatest depression of the nation’s vital force, India revived almost at once and responded by a fresh outburst of spiritual activity, seeking, assimilation, formative effort. A great new life is visibly preparing in her, a mighty transformation and farther dynamic evolution and potent march forward into the inexhaustible infinities of spiritual experience.

The many-sided plasticity of Indian cult and spiritual experience is the native sign of its truth, its living reality, the unfettered sincerity of its search and finding; but this plasticity is a constant stumbling block to the European mind. The religious thinking of Europe is accustomed to rigid impoverishing definitions, to strict exclusions, to a constant preoccupation with the outward idea, the organisation, the form. A precise creed framed by the logical or theological intellect, a strict and definite moral code to fix the conduct, a bundle of observances and ceremonies, a firm ecclesiastical or congregational organisation, that is Western religion. Once the spirit is safely imprisoned and chained up in these things, some emotional fervours and even a certain amount of mystic seeking can be tolerated – within rational limits; but, after all, it is perhaps safest to do without these dangerous spices. Trained in these conceptions, the European critic comes to India and is struck by the immense mass and intricacy of a polytheistic cult crowned at its summit by a belief in the one Infinite. This belief he erroneously supposes to be identical with the barren and abstract intellectual pantheism of the West. He applies with an obstinate prejudgment the ideas and definitions of his own thinking, and this illegitimate importation has fixed many false values on Indian spiritual conceptions, – unhappily, even in the mind of “educated” India. But where our religion eludes his fixed standards, misunderstanding, denunciation and supercilious condemnation come at once to his rescue. The Indian mind on the contrary is averse to intolerant mental exclusions; for a great force of intuition and inner experience had given it from the beginning that towards which the mind of the West is only now reaching with much fumbling and difficulty, – the cosmic consciousness, the cosmic vision. Even when it sees the One without a second, it still admits his duality of Spirit and Nature; it leaves room for his many trinities and million aspects. Even when it concentrates on a single limiting aspect of the Divinity and seems to see nothing but that, it still keeps instinctively at the back of its consciousness the sense of the All and the idea of the One. Even when it distributes its worship among many objects, it looks at the same time through the objects of its worship and sees beyond the multitude of godheads the unity of the Supreme….”45

“Indian religion founded itself on the conception of a timeless, nameless and formless Supreme, but it did not feel called upon, like the narrower and more ignorant monotheisms of the younger races, to deny or abolish all intermediary forms and names and powers and personalities of the Eternal and Infinite. A colourless monism or a pale vague transcendental Theism was not its beginning, its middle and its end. The one Godhead is worshipped as the All, for all in the universe is he or made out of his being or his nature. But Indian religion is not therefore pantheism; for beyond this universality it recognises the supracosmic Eternal. Indian polytheism is not the popular polytheism of ancient Europe; for here the worshipper of many gods still knows that all his divinities are forms, names, personalities and powers of the One; his gods proceed from the one Purusha, his goddesses are energies of the one divine Force. Those ways of Indian cult which most resemble a popular form of Theism, are still something more; for they do not exclude, but admit the many aspects of God. Indian image-worship is not the idolatry of a barbaric or undeveloped mind; for even the most ignorant know that the image is a symbol and support and can throw it away when its use is over. The later religious forms which most felt the impress of the Islamic idea, like Nanak’s worship of the timeless One, Akala, and the reforming creeds of today, born under the influence of the West, yet draw away from the limitations of Western or Semitic monotheism. Irresistibly they turn from these infantile conceptions towards the fathomless truth of Vedanta. The divine Personality of God and his human relations with man are strongly stressed by Vaishnavism and Shaivism as the most dynamic Truth; but that is not the whole of these religions, and this divine Personality is not the limited magnified-human personal God of the West. Indian religion cannot be described by any of the definitions known to the occidental intelligence. In its totality it has been a free and tolerant synthesis of all spiritual worship and experience. Observing the one Truth from all its many sides, it shut out none. It gave itself no specific name and bound itself by no limiting distinction. Allowing separative designations for its constituting cults and divisions, it remained itself nameless, formless, universal, infinite, like the Brahman of its agelong seeking. Although strikingly distinguished from other creeds by its traditional scriptures, cults and symbols, it is not in its essential character a credal religion at all but a vast and many-sided, an always unifying and always progressive and self-enlarging system of spiritual culture.[7]

It is necessary to emphasise this synthetic character and embracing unity of the Indian religious mind, because otherwise we miss the whole meaning of Indian life and the whole sense of Indian culture. It is only by recognising this broad and plastic character that we can understand its total effect on the life of the community and the life of the individual.”46

‡ As has been contextually compared and shown earlier how in most of the other religions of the world some particular aspect or experience of the Divine Reality is held to be the ultimate truth and strictly systematised into one set of dogmas, one cult, one system of ceremonies, one array of prohibitions and injunctions which in the exclusiveness of its spirit is sharply intolerant of anything that doesn’t fall into the narrow limits of that system. Whereas, the Indian religion, which is essentially Indian spiritual philosophy put into action and experience, in the endless catholicity of its spirit, allows complete freedom of discovery of the Divine Reality resulting into a multitude of varied experiences and approaches to the Absolute. Even more remarkable is the fact that this endless variety of experiences, philosophies and systems, however varied and seemingly contradictory, where some of them may go even to the extreme of denying the very existence of God, live in perfect harmony. It is a fact so common in this culture that even an ordinary man knows in his heart that all the infinite experiences are but so many varied descriptions of the one Divine alone, and therefore there can possibly be no essential disparity or conflict between them. It would not at all, therefore, be surprising or something unusual to come across a family with some or all of its members following different faiths or spiritual masters, or worshiping different deities, and yet living together in perfect harmony. The religious mind of India has been synthetic as well as all-inclusive, with its doors always wide open to admit and embrace any novel element or experience. Not only did it take in itself any new thought, philosophy, system, etc. but even the most insignificant approach to or way of coming into contact with the Divine was given its utmost chance of expression within the entire scheme. The religious mind of India intuitively knows that a wholehearted service even of Shaligram can be far more effective and superior than any dry mental philosophisings, however seemingly profound and imposing, and has the power to lead one to the direct touch of the Divine. Not only has it always taken in every possible approach to the Divine but has constantly enlarged its synthesis by assimilating new elements. ‡

[7]	The only religion that India has apparently rejected in the end, is Buddhism; but in fact this appearance is a historical error. Buddhism lost its separative force, because its spiritual substance, as opposed to its credal parts, was absorbed by the religious mind of Hindu India. Even so, it survived in the North and was exterminated not by Shankaracharya or another, but by the invading force of Islam.

F. The Total Movement of Indian Spirituality – the Transmutation of All the Instruments of the Human Living into Instruments of a Divine Living

“The task of religion and spirituality is to mediate between God and man, between the Eternal and Infinite and this transient, yet persistent finite, between a luminous Truth-consciousness not expressed or not yet expressed here and the Mind’s ignorance. But nothing is more difficult than to bring home the greatness and uplifting power of the spiritual consciousness to the natural man forming the vast majority of the race; for his mind and senses are turned outward towards the external calls of life and its objects and never inwards to the Truth which lies behind them. This external vision and attraction are the essence of the universal blinding force which is designated in Indian philosophy the Ignorance. Ancient Indian spirituality recognised that man lives in the Ignorance and has to be led through its imperfect indications to a highest inmost knowledge. Our life moves between two worlds, the depths upon depths of our inward being and the surface field of our outward nature. The majority of men put the whole emphasis of life on the outward and live very strongly in their surface consciousness and very little in the inward existence. Even the choice spirits raised from the grossness of the common vital and physical mould by the stress of thought and culture do not usually get farther than a strong dwelling on the things of the mind. The highest flight they reach – and it is this that the West persistently mistakes for spirituality – is a preference for living in the mind and emotions more than in the gross outward life or else an attempt to subject this rebellious life-stuff to the law of intellectual truth or ethical reason and will or aesthetic beauty or of all three together. But spiritual knowledge perceives that there is a greater thing in us; our inmost self, our real being is not the intellect, not the aesthetic, ethical or thinking mind, but the divinity within, the Spirit, and these other things are only the instruments of the Spirit. A mere intellectual, ethical and aesthetic culture does not go back to the inmost truth of the spirit; it is still an Ignorance, an incomplete, outward and superficial knowledge. To have made the discovery of our deepest being and hidden spiritual nature is the first necessity and to have erected the living of an inmost spiritual life into the aim of existence is the characteristic sign of a spiritual culture.

This endeavour takes in certain religions the form of a spiritual exclusiveness which revolts from the outward existence rather than seeks to transform it. The main tendency of the Christian discipline was not only to despise the physical and vital way of living, but to disparage and imprison the intellectual and distrust and discourage the aesthetic thirsts of our nature. It emphasised against them a limited spiritual emotionalism and its intense experiences as the one thing needful; the development of the ethical sense was the sole mental necessity, its translation into act the sole indispensable condition or result of the spiritual life. Indian spirituality reposed on too wide and many-sided a culture to admit as its base this narrow movement; but on its more solitary summits, at least in its later period, it tended to a spiritual exclusiveness loftier in vision, but even more imperative and excessive. A spirituality of this intolerant high-pointed kind, to whatever elevation it may rise, however it may help to purify life or lead to a certain kind of individual salvation, cannot be a complete thing. For its exclusiveness imposes on it a certain impotence to deal effectively with the problems of human existence; it cannot lead it to its integral perfection or combine its highest heights with its broadest broadness. A wider spiritual culture must recognise that the Spirit is not only the highest and inmost thing, but all is manifestation and creation of the Spirit. It must have a wider outlook, a more embracing range of applicability and, even, a more aspiring and ambitious aim of its endeavour. Its aim must be not only to raise to inaccessible heights the few elect, but to draw all men and all life and the whole human being upward, to spiritualise life and in the end to divinise human nature. Not only must it be able to lay hold on his deepest individual being but to inspire too his communal existence. It must turn by a spiritual change all the members of his ignorance into members of the knowledge; it must transmute all the instruments of the human into instruments of a divine living. The total movement of Indian spirituality is towards this aim; in spite of all the difficulties, imperfections and fluctuations of its evolution, it had this character. But like other cultures it was not at all times and in all its parts and movements consciously aware of its own total significance. This large sense sometimes emerged into something like a conscious synthetic clarity, but was more often kept in the depths and on the surface dispersed in a multitude of subordinate and special stand-points. Still, it is only by an intelligence of the total drift that its manifold sides and rich variations of effort and teaching and discipline can receive their full reconciling unity and be understood in the light of its own most intrinsic purpose.”47

‡ Seldom does one find anywhere such an important revelation about the Sanatana Dharma brought out so explicitly as has been made here by Sri Aurobindo. Though the total movement of Indian spirituality and religion has always been in its very nature all-embracing, it is only at times that this synthetic, and all-inclusive impulse consciously formulates and makes itself evident on the surface. Mostly, working secretly from behind the veil it remains obscure even to a discerning eye that can at best catch a glimpse of the multitude of forms, systems and stand-points in which this secret impulse disperses itself on the surface. It, therefore, follows that the whole web of Sanatana Dharma — guided always by the Divine Presence — is nothing but a manifestation of this secret spirit in infinite forms. The coming of Sri Aurobindo and the Mother to announce the Supramental manifestation to eventually transform even the material nature and establish divine life upon earth is, therefore, only a logical step in the total movement of the Sanatana Dharma that leads it to its consummation. When Sri Aurobindo first propounded his ideal of Supramental manifestation and its inevitability in the logic of things, many questioned the novelty of his conception saying that the Indian yogis had already been experiencing the states of consciousness up to the level of Sachchidananda which is a far higher level than the supermind. To this one may respond by clarifying that indeed yogis had long been experiencing Sachchidananda – a status of consciousness greater than that of the Supermind – in their physical, vital and mental natures since times immemorial. However, there is a glorious domination in these experiences but not a real mastery of Nature because the mental consciousness is not wide enough to enable Sachchidananda consciousness to master the outermost material nature. It is only the Supramental consciousness that is wide and complex enough to permit the manifestation of the native omniscience, omnipotence and omnipresence of the Spirit (Sachchidananda) in terrestrial nature and establish divine life on Earth. For example, however learned a teacher may be, his expression of knowledge will be conditioned by the standard of the pupils he is addressing – whether they are of primary, high school or college level. Similarly, when the physical consciousness of man enters into the self of Sachchidananda, “The result is a glorified sleep of the physical mind in which the physical being forgets itself in a kind of conscious Nirvana or else moves about like a thing inert in the hands of Nature, jaḍavat, like a leaf in the wind, or otherwise a state of pure happy and free irresponsibility of action, bālavat, a divine childhood. But this comes without the higher glories of knowledge and delight which belong to the same status upon a more exalted level. It is an inert realisation of Sachchidananda in which there is neither any mastery of the Prakriti by the Purusha nor any sublimation of Nature into her own supreme power, the infinite glories of the Para Shakti.” (CWSA 23, 499). When the vital consciousness of man enters into the self of Sachchidananda, “The result is either a profound state of sheer self-oblivion or else an action driven irresponsibly by the life nature, an exalted enthusiasm of self-abandonment to the great world-energy in its vitalistic dance. The outer being lives in a God-possessed frenzy careless of itself and the world, unmattavat, or with an entire disregard whether of the conventions and proprieties of fitting human action or of the harmony and rhythms of a greater Truth. It acts as the unbound vital being, piśācavat, the divine maniac or else the divine demoniac. Here too there is no mastery or supreme sublimation of nature.” (CWSA 23, 500)

“The mind soul and mind consciousness in man, manomaya puruṣa, can in the same direct way reflect and enter into Sachchidananda by a reflection of the Soul as it mirrors itself in the nature of pure universal mind luminous, unwalled, happy, plastic, illimitable, or by absorption in the vast free unconditioned uncentred Self within it and without it. The result is either the immobile cessation of all mind and action or a desire-free unbound action watched by the unparticipating inner Witness. The mental being becomes the eremite soul alone in the world and careless of all human ties or the saint soul that lives in a rapturous God-nearness or felicitous identity and in joyful relations of pure love and ecstasy towards all creatures. The mental being may even realise the Self in all three planes together. Then he is all these things alternately, successively or at once. Or he may transform the lower forms into manifestations of the higher state; he may draw upward the childlikeness or the inert irresponsibility of the free physical mind or the free vital mind’s divine madness and carelessness of all rules, proprieties, harmonies and colour or disguise with them the ecstasy of the saint or the solitary liberty of the wandering eremite. Here again there is no mastery, no sublimation of the Nature by the soul in the world …. Mind can arrive only at a compromise between the infinite within and the finite nature without; it cannot pour the infinity of the inner being’s knowledge and power and bliss with any sense of fullness into its external action which remains always inadequate. Still it is content and free because it is the Lord within who takes up the responsibility of the action adequate or inadequate, assumes its guidance and fixes its consequence.

But the gnostic soul, the vijñānamaya puruṣa, is the first to participate not only in the freedom, but in the power and sovereignty of the Eternal.”[8] (CWSA 23, 500-501)

Only when one looks at the entire progression of Sanatana Dharma from this perspective, can one get some glimpse of its great effort, and then the whole course of its development appears to be throughout a perfectly consistent movement of the spirit progressively manifesting itself from its highest peaks to its most material parts. Once having caught a glimpse of this secret Wisdom at work, one may rest assured, even in the face of the most opposite and trying circumstances, that this Divine Wisdom is constantly at work to lead this culture to its goal of a complete divine realisation. ‡

[8] The Vijñānamaya is the traditional name for the Supramental.

G. The Spirit and Forms of Indian Religion and Spiritual Culture

(i) The Vedic and Vedantic Form

“Now the spirit of Indian religion and spiritual culture has been persistently and immovably the same throughout the long time of its vigour, but its form has undergone remarkable changes. Yet if we look into them from the right centre it will be apparent that these changes are the results of a logical and inevitable evolution inherent in the very process of man’s growth towards the heights. In its earliest form, its first Vedic system, it took its outward foundation on the mind of the physical man whose natural faith is in things physical, in the sensible and visible objects, presences, representations and the external pursuits and aims of this material world. The means, symbols, rites, figures, by which it sought to mediate between the spirit and the normal human mentality were drawn from these most external physical things. Man’s first and primitive idea of the Divine can only come through his vision of external Nature and the sense of a superior Power or Powers concealed behind her phenomena, veiled in the heaven and earth, father and mother of our being, in the sun and moon and stars, its lights and regulators, in dawn and day and night and rain and wind and storm, the oceans and the rivers and the forests, all the circumstances and forces of her scene of action, all that vast and mysterious surrounding life of which we are a part and in which the natural heart and mind of the human creature feel instinctively through whatever bright or dark or confused figures that there is here some divine Multitude or else mighty Infinite, one, manifold and mysterious, which takes these forms and manifests itself in these motions. The Vedic religion took this natural sense and feeling of the physical man; it used the conceptions to which they gave birth, and it sought to lead him through them to the psychic and spiritual truths of his own being and the being of the cosmos. It recognised that he was right when he saw behind the manifestations of Nature great living powers and godheads, even though he knew not their inner truth, and right too in offering to them worship and propitiation and atonement. For that inevitably must be the initial way in which his active physical, vital and mental nature is allowed to approach the Godhead. He approaches it through its visible outward manifestations as something greater than his own natural self, something single or multiple that guides, sustains and directs his life, and he calls to it for help and support in the desires and difficulties and distresses and struggles of his human existence.[9] The Vedic religion accepted also the form in which early man everywhere expressed his sense of the relation between himself and the godheads of Nature; it adopted as its central symbol the act and ritual of a physical sacrifice. However crude the notions attached to it, this idea of the necessity of sacrifice did express obscurely a first law of being. For it was founded on that secret of constant interchange between the individual and the universal powers of the cosmos which covertly supports all the process of life and develops the action of Nature.

But even in its external or exoteric side the Vedic religion did not limit itself to this acceptance and regulation of the first religious notions of the natural physical mind of man. The Vedic Rishis gave a psychic function to the godheads worshipped by the people; they spoke to them of a higher Truth, Right, Law of which the gods were the guardians, of the necessity of a truer knowledge and a larger inner living according to this Truth and Right and of a home of Immortality to which the soul of man could ascend by the power of Truth and of right doing. The people no doubt took these ideas in their most external sense; but they were trained by them to develop their ethical nature, to turn towards some initial development of their psychic being, to conceive the idea of a knowledge and truth other than that of the physical life and to admit even a first conception of some greater spiritual Reality which was the ultimate object of human worship or aspiration. This religious and moral force was the highest reach of the external cult and the most that could be understood or followed by the mass of the people.

The deeper truth of these things was reserved for the initiates, for those who were ready to understand and practise the inner sense, the esoteric meaning hidden in the Vedic scripture. For the Veda is full of words which, as the Rishis themselves express it, are secret words that give their inner meaning only to the seer, kavaye nivacanā niṇyā vacāṁsi. This is a feature of the ancient sacred hymns which grew obscure to later ages; it became a dead tradition and has been entirely ignored by modern scholarship in its laborious attempt to read the hieroglyph of the Vedic symbols. Yet its recognition is essential to a right understanding of almost all the ancient religions; for mostly they started on their upward curve through an esoteric element of which the key was not given to all. In all or most there was a surface cult for the common physical man who was held yet unfit for the psychic and spiritual life and an inner secret of the Mysteries carefully disguised by symbols whose sense was opened only to the initiates. This was the origin of the later distinction between the Shudra, the undeveloped physical-minded man, and the twice-born, those who were capable of entering into the second birth by initiation and to whom alone the Vedic education could be given without danger. This too actuated the later prohibition of any reading or teaching of the Veda by the Shudra.[10] It was this inner meaning, it was the higher psychic and spiritual truths concealed by the outer sense, that gave to these hymns the name by which they are still known, the Veda, the Book of Knowledge. Only by penetrating into the esoteric sense of this worship can we understand the full flowering of the Vedic religion in the Upanishads and in the long later evolution of Indian spiritual seeking and experience. For it is all there in its luminous seed, preshadowed or even prefigured in the verses of the early seers. The persistent notion which through every change ascribed the foundation of all our culture to the Rishis, whatever its fabulous forms and mythical ascriptions, contains a real truth and veils a sound historic tradition. It reflects the fact of a true initiation and an unbroken continuity between this great primitive past and the riper but hardly greater spiritual development of our historic culture.

This inner Vedic religion started with an extension of the psychic significance of the godheads in the Cosmos. Its primary notion was that of a hierarchy of worlds, an ascending stair of planes of being in the universe. It saw a mounting scale of the worlds corresponding to a similar mounting scale of planes or degrees or levels of consciousness in the nature of man. A Truth, Right and Law sustains and governs all these levels of Nature; one in essence, it takes in them different but cognate forms. There is for instance the series of the outer physical light, another higher and inner light which is the vehicle of the mental, vital and psychic consciousness and a highest inmost light of spiritual illumination. Surya, the Sun-God, was the lord of the physical Sun; but he is at the same time to the Vedic seer-poet the giver of the rays of knowledge which illumine the mind and he is too the soul and energy and body of the spiritual illumination. And in all these powers he is a luminous form of the one and infinite Godhead. All the Vedic godheads have this outer and this inner and inmost function, their known and their secret Names. All are in their external character powers of physical Nature; all have in their inner meaning a psychic function and psychological ascriptions; all too are various powers of some one highest Reality, ekaṁ sat, the one infinite Existence. This hardly knowable Supreme is called often in the Veda ‘That Truth’ or ‘That One’, tat satyam, tad ekam. This complex character of the Vedic godheads assumes forms which have been wholly misunderstood by those who ascribe to them only their outward physical significance. Each of these gods is in himself a complete and separate cosmic personality of the one Existence and in their combination of powers they form the complete universal power, the cosmic whole, vaiśvadevyam. Each again, apart from his special function, is one godhead with the others; each holds in himself the universal divinity, each god is all the other gods. This is the aspect of the Vedic teaching and worship to which a European scholar, mistaking entirely its significance because he read it in the dim and poor light of European religious experience, has given the sounding misnomer, henotheism. Beyond, in the triple Infinite, these godheads put on their highest nature and are names of the one nameless Ineffable.

But the greatest power of the Vedic teaching, that which made it the source of all later Indian philosophies, religions, systems of Yoga, lay in its application to the inner life of man. Man lives in the physical cosmos subject to death and the “much falsehood” of the mortal existence. To rise beyond this death, to become one of the immortals, he has to turn from the falsehood to the Truth; he has to turn to the Light and to battle with and to conquer the powers of the Darkness. This he does by communion with the divine Powers and their aid; the way to call down this aid was the secret of the Vedic mystics. The symbols of the outer sacrifice are given for this purpose in the manner of the Mysteries all over the world an inner meaning; they represent a calling of the gods into the human being, a connecting sacrifice, an intimate interchange, a mutual aid, a communion. There is a building of the powers of the godheads within man and a formation in him of the universality of the divine nature. For the gods are the guardians and increasers of the Truth, the powers of the Immortal, the sons of the infinite Mother; the way to immortality is the upward way of the gods, the way of the Truth, a journey, an ascent by which there is a growth into the law of the Truth, ṛtasya panthāḥ. Man arrives at immortality by breaking beyond the limitations not only of his physical self, but of his mental and his ordinary psychic nature into the highest plane and supreme ether of the Truth: for there is the foundation of immortality and the native seat of the triple Infinite. On these ideas the Vedic sages built up a profound psychological and psychic discipline which led beyond itself to a highest spirituality and contained the nucleus of later Indian Yoga. Already we find in their seed, though not in their full expansion, the most characteristic ideas of Indian spirituality. There is the one Existence, ekaṁ sat, supracosmic beyond the individual and the universe. There is the one God who presents to us the many forms, names, powers, personalities of his Godhead. There is the distinction between the Knowledge and the Ignorance,[11] the greater truth of an immortal life opposed to the much falsehood or mixed truth and falsehood of mortal existence. There is the discipline of an inward growth of man from the physical through the psychic to the spiritual existence. There is the conquest of death, the secret of immortality, the perception of a realisable divinity of the human spirit. In an age to which in the insolence of our external knowledge we are accustomed to look back as the childhood of humanity or at best a period of vigorous barbarism, this was the inspired and intuitive psychic and spiritual teaching by which the ancient human fathers, pūrve pitaraḥ manuṣyāḥ, founded a great and profound civilisation in India.

This high beginning was secured in its results by a larger sublime efflorescence. The Upanishads have always been recognised in India as the crown and end of Veda; that is indicated in their general name, Vedanta. And they are in fact a large crowning outcome of the Vedic discipline and experience. The time in which the Vedantic truth was wholly seen and the Upanishads took shape, was, as we can discern from such records as the Chhandogya and Brihadaranyaka, an epoch of immense and strenuous seeking, an intense and ardent seed-time of the Spirit. In the stress of that seeking the truths held by the initiates but kept back from ordinary men broke their barriers, swept through the higher mind of the nation and fertilised the soil of Indian culture for a constant and ever increasing growth of spiritual consciousness and spiritual experience. This turn was not as yet universal; it was chiefly men of the higher classes, Kshatriyas and Brahmins trained in the Vedic system of education, no longer content with an external truth and the works of the outer sacrifice, who began everywhere to seek for the highest word of revealing experience from the sages who possessed the knowledge of the One. But we find too among those who attained to the knowledge and became great teachers men of inferior or doubtful birth like Janashruti, the wealthy Shudra, or Satyakama Jabali, son of a servant-girl who knew not who was his father. The work that was done in this period became the firm bedrock of Indian spirituality in later ages and from it gush still the life-giving waters of a perennial and never failing inspiration. This period, this activity, this grand achievement created the whole difference between the evolution of Indian civilisation and the quite different curve of other cultures.

For a time had come when the original Vedic symbols must lose their significance and pass into an obscurity that became impenetrable, as did the inner teaching of the Mysteries in other countries. The old poise of culture between two extremes with a bridge of religious cult and symbolism to unite them, the crude or half-trained naturalness of the outer physical man on one side of the line, and on the other an inner and secret psychic and spiritual life for the initiates could no longer suffice as the basis of our spiritual progress. The human race in its cycle of civilisation needed a large-lined advance; it called for a more and more generalised intellectual, ethical and aesthetic evolution to help it to grow into the light. This turn had to come in India as in other lands. But the danger was that the greater spiritual truth already gained might be lost in the lesser confident half-light of the acute but unillumined intellect or stifled within the narrow limits of the self-sufficient logical reason. That was what actually happened in the West, Greece leading the way. The old knowledge was prolonged in a less inspired, less dynamic and more intellectual form by the Pythagoreans, by the Stoics, by Plato and the Neo-Platonists; but still in spite of them and in spite of the only half-illumined spiritual wave which swept over Europe from Asia in an ill-understood Christianity, the whole real trend of Western civilisation has been intellectual, rational, secular and even materialistic, and it keeps this character to the present day. Its general aim has been a strong or a fine culture of the vital and physical man by the power of an intellectualised ethics, aesthesis and reason, not the leading up of our lower members into the supreme light and power of the spirit. The ancient spiritual knowledge and the spiritual tendency it had created were saved in India from this collapse by the immense effort of the age of the Upanishads. The Vedantic seers renewed the Vedic truth by extricating it from its cryptic symbols and casting it into a highest and most direct and powerful language of intuition and inner experience. It was not the language of the intellect, but still it wore a form which the intellect could take hold of, translate into its own more abstract terms and convert into a starting-point for an ever widening and deepening philosophic speculation and the reason’s long search after a Truth original, supreme and ultimate. There was in India as in the West a great upbuilding of a high, wide and complex intellectual, aesthetic, ethical and social culture. But left in Europe to its own resources, combated rather than helped by obscure religious emotion and dogma, here it was guided, uplifted and more and more penetrated and suffused by a great saving power of spirituality and a vast stimulating and tolerant light of wisdom from a highest ether of knowledge.”49

‡ Sri Aurobindo has provided here a broad perspective on how the essential spirit of the Indian spiritual culture and religion has persistently and unceasingly been the same throughout its long course of development even though the forms that this spirit has taken have undergone remarkable changes with changing times and stages of human development.

Qs: While deliberating on the nature of religion in the Vedic age Sri Aurobindo elaborates on the internal and external function of the Vedic gods. What does it mean when he says that in the Vedic religion ‘each god is all the other gods’, and how is it different from the misnomer ‘henotheism’?

Ans: A term originally from the Greek culture, ‘henotheism’ literally means the worship of a single, supreme god while not denying the existence or possible existence of other lower deities and, therefore, carries with itself the sense of the existence of various gods with their well-defined functions, their mutual interactions as well as their discordances and struggles, for such is the nature of the Greek gods. When a European scholar reads in the dim and poor light of his own religious experience the account of the complex character of Vedic Godheads and their respective inner and outer functions, he tends to call it by the term familiar to him, that is henotheism. Whereas, the Indian mind always had this deep perception that all the Godheads are one in their essence and it is only when they come down to the lower levels of manifestation that the action of each deity appears to be different from every other. But being one in their essence, these godheads reassume their original solidarity for one who ascends to the higher levels of consciousness. For ease of understanding, we may liken it to a human individual carrying within himself a multitude of faculties, powers and personality traits. At different times or stages of his development, certain traits or aspects of his complex being may come into prominence and express themselves. But behind all these expressions, however varied or multifarious, the human individual remains the same, and in the totality of his being he is too far above to be defined or delimited by all of these or even infinite other such aspects of his personality put together. Therefore, the Indian mind, from the very outset, had this deep perception that even though there appear to be infinite forms and aspects of the Divine, none of them can claim for itself to be the only real one while disdaining the others. For, it knew that these forms are verily the forms of the one Divine, who, even while manifesting through them all, is not bound or limited by them. But the thing of yet greater significance was that even this deep perception did not in any way overshadow or belittle the significance of any particular form, which was always given its utmost value and importance in this culture. Our Puranic literature also amply brings out this fact where each Purana propounds its own presiding deity as the Supreme and all the other deities as various forms or auxiliary powers of the same. For example, we find Lord Shiva propounded as the Supreme Lord in Shiva Purana, Lord Ganesha in Ganesha Purana, Devi in Devi Purana, and so on. Even the agency of Guru, the human representative of the Divine, has never been taken to be of secondary importance, rather it has always been regarded as the ultimate Parabrahman, and a great emphasis has always been kept on maintaining utmost loyalty and exclusivity towards him.

In the Vedic system, the gods are conscious psychological powers in man. Actually, the whole creation appears to us the way it does because of a given constitution of our consciousness, that is to say, our perception of the world depends on the balance of our psychological powers within. Even for a person of ordinary consciousness, this perception changes with the changing stages of development in his life. As one progresses from his present psychological constitution towards his true goal, the action of Gods too becomes increasingly pervasive encompassing in itself gradually the action of other Gods also which was completely or in most part dormant in the beginning. This progression in the Vedic system is symbolised as the ascent of sacrifice. From the interpretation of the Vedic system given by Sri Aurobindo, it becomes clear that, while each one of the Vedic godheads has its more outer psychological function, each godhead is, at times spoken of in the Veda as the Supreme and Ultimate Reality, containing in itself all the other godheads. For example, the Rishi speaks of Soma in his impersonal manifestation, as the Ananda or delight of divine existence in the human being’s conscious experience. But when he turns, as is the habit of the Vedic Rishis, from the divine manifestation to the divine Person, Soma at once appears as the supreme Personality, the high and universal Deva. It becomes the generator of the worlds of the becoming, for from the Ananda, from the all-blissful One they all proceed; delight is the parent of the variety of existences. The same is the case with all the other Vedic godheads, which justifies the saying ‘each god is all the other gods’.

Qs. It is said that the Vedic Rishis were mystics who reserved their inner knowledge for the initiates; they shielded it from the vulgar by the use of an alphabet of symbols which could not readily be understood without the initiation. What after all is the basic difference between an initiate and an ordinary man?

Ans: The Vedic Rishis in India have always had this deep perception that this whole universe is nothing but an objectivisation or manifestation of the Will of the Divine Mother which alone is the true cause of everything. But being completely ignorant of this Divine Will and its action, a sense-bound mentality mistakes the sensory perceptions and phenomenal appearances for the truth and erects on the basis of that false view the whole of its structure of life and action. This for the Indian mentality is falsehood, for it maintains that things in themselves have no value, it is only the spirit within that gives everything its true worth. Therefore, when the central idea of life and ourselves from which we start is a falsehood, all else — our thought, emotion, will and action — is inevitably falsified by it. It is only when one becomes somewhat conscious of that Divine Will and of the form that it assumes in the manifestation that one begins to get some sense of the true cause of things, the truth of this creation. When one psychologically reaches a stage where one is capable of recognising the divine Will (Agni) – even though not yet, most of the time, of consciously assenting to it – then it (the stage) may be taken to symbolise the birth of Agni in one’s being. This birth or emergence of truth within effectuates a fundamental exchange of the old externalized outlook towards the world, existence and being for a deeper vision that inevitably reorients in this new light the whole perception about oneself and all that is there. The initiate is such a one, in whom this emergence has taken place, and therefore, no more grossly insisting on one’s own sense-bound mentality, admits and consciously allows in oneself the action of the Divine Mother, who resides as one’s innermost soul. The birth of this Agni is what is termed in the Vedas as the commencement of sacrifice. It is a common experience of all true seekers who have trod the spiritual path that not all the parts of the being are in conformity with the Divine Will at the very outset. One begins one’s march with a whole baggage of parts that do not share this higher aspiration and have their own egoistic motives, deeply ingrained habits, desires, passions, cravings, prejudices, their own set ideas, patterns of thought, norms of right and wrong, and countless other such things. When the sacrifice begins with the kindling of the inner flame, one gradually consecrates the contents of this baggage into the sacrificial fire as oblation and, thus, increasingly substitutes the working of the lower parts by that of the higher ones. The sacrifice thus becomes a means for the sadhak to ascend from his present obscurity and littleness to an ever greater enlightenment, immortality, fulfilment and beatitude. But this mystic symbolism of sacrifice represents a deep psychological, inner and spiritual alchemy of our being in a language of symbols and images the deeper meaning of which can be entered into only by an initiate. The following extract from a letter of Sri Krishnaprem provides a clear perspective on the whole distinction between the outlook of a profane and an initiate. He writes, “It is well known that there are three main sources of proof — Pratyaksha, Anumana and Shabda (or Aptabachan). Now common opinion starts by assuming that Pratyaksha is the most valid — ‘seeing is believing’ as they say, then Anumana, and lastly authority or Aptabachan. …On the contrary the great seers of the past, of all schools of thought, have taken quite the contrary view. They agreed that inasmuch as our senses are notoriously liable to error and supernormal experiences, notoriously liable to misinterpretation, Pratyaksha praman is defective. Inference (Anumana) being dependent on Pratyaksha is liable to the same defects and the best basis for belief is Aptabachan whether in the form of Gurubakya or of Shastra — the two are fundamentally the same thing. They then reversed the ordinary order and by so doing arrived not at Russellism but at spiritual experience and Divine realisation. Hence I hold that one must at all costs start from the right end if one is to get the right result. One must give up the stupid belief that the world is what it seems to be. It isn’t, and the sooner we realise that, the better for us. …Has any one yet been known to reach God through Russellism? …No one has yet reached God by reliance on sense-testimony alone.” (Yogi Sri Krishnaprem by D. K. Roy, Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan 1992, pp. 161-63)

Qs: What does it mean that the inner Vedic religion saw ‘a mounting scale of the worlds corresponding to a similar mounting scale of planes or degrees or levels of consciousness in the nature of man’? Also, what is the true meaning of the example of the sun presented here by Sri Aurobindo?

Ans: The Indian mind looks upon this entire creation as a manifestation of the Supreme Lord where the Supreme Consciousness has descended from its superconscient levels to the complete Inconscience and, in this process, termed as the process of involution, created a descending series of increasingly limited planes of consciousness. When that Consciousness evolves back to its origin, there emerges an ascending stair of planes of being corresponding to the one created in the process of involution. In Indian Puranic literature also one gets an ample account of these planes, worlds or ‘lokas’ described variously. But had it not been for a corresponding scale of planes or levels of consciousness that are latent in the nature of man himself, never ever would he be able to come into contact with or become conscious of the whole hierarchy of the levels of consciousness. It is an occult and deep spiritual truth that a human individual is an organised unit of existence which reflects the constitution of the universe and repeats in itself the same arrangement of states and play of forces. Man, subjectively, contains in himself all the worlds in which, objectively, he is contained. In the awareness of the Rishis a world is primarily a formation of consciousness and only secondarily a physical formation of things. A world is a loka, a way in which conscious being images itself, which means that as is the observing consciousness so appears this phenomenal existence. For, it is evident that the same creation appears differently to a human being and an insect. Even to different human beings, the actual appearance differs according to the different states of their consciousness and psychology. The Gita too, in its analysis of the double principle of Purusha (soul) and Prakriti (nature), elucidates how this whole appearance of infinitely varied creation comes into existence only by the combination of or an interrelationship between this dual principle, i.e. the observing consciousness and an active objectivity. As the Purusha (the witnessing principle) assumes the various poises of witness, upholder, source of the sanction, knower, enjoyer or lord, Prakriti, the active principle, too seems to execute its operation correspondingly. It is in this sense that it is said that an individual contains in itself the whole creation, for, truly the whole creation is nothing but a projection of one’s own Self. Therefore, one can never come into contact with something, whether in this world or in any other worlds or lokas or planes, which is not potentially contained in that Self. This explains the statement that the inner Vedic religion saw a mounting scale of the worlds corresponding to a similar mounting scale of planes or degrees or levels of consciousness in the nature of man. Having a deep perception of this close correspondence in the working of the spiritual, psychological and physical planes the Vedic Rishis maintained that the forces and processes of the physical world repeat, as in a symbol, the truths of the supraphysical action which preceded it. And since it is by the same forces and the same processes, one in the physical worlds and the supraphysical, that our inner life and its development are governed, the Rishis adopted the phenomena of physical Nature as appropriate symbols for those functionings of the inner life. For, this is the significance of a symbol, that it is an image or a form on one plane representing the truth of a higher plane. It is to illustrate this correspondence that Sri Aurobindo has utilised here the symbol of the Sun. When reflecting upon the action of the Sun on various planes, firstly, it is evident that, materially, it is the Sun that makes earthly existence possible. Illumining and revealing before us all that there exists in this phenomenal world it brings us into contact with the truth of existence and, with its vision-power, helps us discern and have a perspective of a thing in itself and in its relation to other things in a larger view. Surya is not only the illuminator, but also, as the Veda says, Savitri the Creator, and Pushan the Increaser and the Nourisher. Corresponding to the more physical functioning, one finds a yet greater action of Sun in our mentality where it enlightens the mind and the thoughts with the illuminations of the Truth. It is he who delivers the individual human mind from the circumscribed consciousness of self and environment and enlarges the limited and obscure movement which is imposed on it by its preoccupation with its own individuality. Men, as soon as they begin to receive something of this solar illumination, strive to yoke their whole mentality and its thought-contents to the conscious existence of the divine Surya within them. That is to say, they join, as it were, all their obscure mental state and all their erring thoughts to this Light manifested in them so that it may turn the obscurity of the mind into clearness and convert the surface thoughts of the mind into those truths which they distortedly represent. The unbroken succession of the physical dawns is also symbolic of the new openings of divine illumination on man’s consciousness progressively illuminating and sublimating the working of various parts of his being. It should therefore be clear that as compared to its physical function the deeper action of the Sun is still more vast and potent in our mentality. For, the greater fulfilment of our being depends much more on the development and refinement of our deeper psychology than any mere outer intelligence devoid of any deeper insight. Thus, while for a person of superficial consciousness this symbol of Sun carries primarily a more external meaning, it readily reveals its deeper psychological, inner and spiritual significance to a true seeker who has already become conscious of its action in himself. This whole discussion succinctly provides us a perspective on the spirit of Indian religion and spiritual culture in the Vedic times, and also, on how this spirit remained immovably the same throughout even when its form underwent remarkable changes.‡

(ii) The Post-Vedic Age

“The second or post-Vedic age of Indian civilisation was distinguished by the rise of the great philosophies, by a copious, vivid, many-thoughted, many-sided epic literature, by the beginnings of art and science, by the evolution of a vigorous and complex society, by the formation of large kingdoms and empires, by manifold formative activities of all kinds and great systems of living and thinking. Here as elsewhere, in Greece, Rome, Persia, China, this was the age of a high outburst of the intelligence working upon life and the things of the mind to discover their reason and their right way and bring out a broad and noble fullness of human existence. But in India this effort never lost sight of the spiritual motive, never missed the touch of the religious sense. It was a birth time and youth of the seeking intellect and, as in Greece, philosophy was the main instrument by which it laboured to solve the problems of life and the world. Science too developed, but it came second only as an auxiliary power. It was through profound and subtle philosophies that the intellect of India attempted to analyse by the reason and logical faculty what had formerly been approached with a much more living force through intuition and the soul’s experience. But the philosophic mind started from the data these mightier powers had discovered and was faithful to its parent Light; it went back always in one form or another to the profound truths of the Upanishads which kept their place as the highest authority in these matters. There was a constant admission that spiritual experience is a greater thing and its light a truer if more incalculable guide than the clarities of the reasoning intelligence.

The same governing force kept its hold on all the other activities of the Indian mind and Indian life. The epic literature is full almost to excess of a strong and free intellectual and ethical thinking; there is an incessant criticism of life by the intelligence and the ethical reason, an arresting curiosity and desire to fix the norm of truth in all possible fields. But in the background and coming constantly to the front there is too a constant religious sense and an implicit or avowed assent to the spiritual truths which remained the unshakable basis of the culture. These truths suffused with their higher light secular thought and action or stood above to remind them that they were only steps towards a goal. Art in India, contrary to a common idea, dwelt much upon life; but still its highest achievement was always in the field of the interpretation of the religio-philosophical mind and its whole tone was coloured by a suggestion of the spiritual and the infinite. Indian society developed with an unsurpassed organising ability, stable effectiveness, practical insight its communal coordination of the mundane life of interest and desire, kāma, artha; it governed always its action by a reference at every point to the moral and religious law, the Dharma: but it never lost sight of spiritual liberation as our highest point and the ultimate aim of the effort of Life. In later times when there was a still stronger secular tendency of intellectual culture, there came in an immense development of the mundane intelligence, an opulent political and social evolution, an emphatic stressing of aesthetic, sensuous and hedonistic experience. But this effort too always strove to keep itself within the ancient frame and not to lose the special stamp of the Indian cultural idea. The enlarged secular turn was compensated by a deepening of the intensities of psycho-religious experience. New religious or mystic forms and disciplines attempted to seize not only the soul and the intellect, but the emotions, the senses, the vital and the aesthetic nature of man and turn them into stuff of the spiritual life. And every excess of emphasis on the splendour and richness and power and pleasures of life had its recoil and was balanced by a corresponding potent stress on spiritual asceticism as the higher way. The two trends, on one side an extreme of the richness of life experience, on the other an extreme and pure rigorous intensity of the spiritual life, accompanied each other; their interaction, whatever loss there might be of the earlier deep harmony and large synthesis, yet by their double pull preserved something still of the balance of Indian culture.

Indian religion followed this line of evolution and kept its inner continuity with its Vedic and Vedantic origins; but it changed entirely its mental contents and colour and its outward basis. It did not effectuate this change through any protestant revolt or revolution or with any idea of an iconoclastic reformation. A continuous development of its organic life took place, a natural transformation brought out latent motives or else gave to already established motive-ideas a more predominant place or effective form. At one time indeed it seemed as if a discontinuity and a sharp new beginning were needed and would take place. Buddhism seemed to reject all spiritual continuity with the Vedic religion. But this was after all less in reality than in appearance. The Buddhist ideal of Nirvana was no more than a sharply negative and exclusive statement of the highest Vedantic spiritual experience. The ethical system of the eightfold path taken as the way to release was an austere sublimation of the Vedic notion of the Right, Truth and Law followed as the way to immortality, ṛtasya panthāḥ. The strongest note of Mahayana Buddhism, its stress on universal compassion and fellow-feeling, was an ethical application of the spiritual unity which is the essential idea of Vedanta.[12] The most characteristic tenets of the new discipline, Nirvana and Karma, could have been supported from the utterances of the Brahmanas and Upanishads. Buddhism could easily have claimed for itself a Vedic origin and the claim would have been no less valid than the Vedic ascription of the Sankhya philosophy and discipline with which it had some points of intimate alliance. But what hurt Buddhism and determined in the end its rejection, was not its denial of a Vedic origin or authority, but the exclusive trenchancy of its intellectual, ethical and spiritual positions. A result of an intense stress of the union of logical reason with the spiritualised mind – for it was by an intense spiritual search supported on a clear and hard rational thinking that it was born as a separate religion, – its trenchant affirmations and still more exclusive negations could not be made sufficiently compatible with the native flexibility, many-sided susceptibility and rich synthetic turn of the Indian religious consciousness; it was a high creed but not plastic enough to hold the heart of the people. Indian religion absorbed all that it could of Buddhism, but rejected its exclusive positions and preserved the full line of its own continuity, casting back to the ancient Vedanta.”50

‡ The whole curve of the evolution of Indian religion, through the ages, has gradually moved down the descending planes of consciousness towards bringing under Spirit’s influence and infusing with its light even the most external and material parts of human nature to turn them into the soul’s instruments for its faultless expression. In the far off times, the times of the Vedas, the Rishis were moved through the intuition and there was no need of set forms and institutions, the Spirit permeated and moulded the whole of society directly through the intuition of the Rishis. The Vedic age was the period when Truth revealed itself by the power of deep spiritual intuition, inspiration and revelation, so the Vedas were unintelligible to the ordinary human mentality. Consequently, as the intellect and mental being needed to be moulded, in the times of the Upanishads, the Vedic truth was renewed by extricating it from its cryptic symbols and casting it into the language of intuition which was not as completely inaccessible to the intellect in the Vedas. The powerful intuitive aphoristic style of the Upanishads wore a form that the higher part of Buddhi could get hold of and catch a glimpse of the truths expressed there. Then creating mental forms for the expression of the Spirit, the six Darshanas (the six systems of Yoga) arose with their revelation of the different aspects of the Divine and practical ways of reaching him, with Gita as the crowning movement, synthesising the different strands masterfully for all times. Then as the expression of the Spirit descended into the heart, the emotional being, into the various strands of life, there came the Puranas and the Tantras, to establish the possibility of opening all these parts of life to the Divine. Various ways of worshiping the Divine through the emotional and sensational being developed with a plethora of rites, rituals, religious ceremonies connecting man to the Divinity concealed in every element of creation. It was inevitable that this enriching descent from the spirit to matter should take into account even the aesthetic, hedonistic and sensuous parts of the being and, while giving them their just chance of satisfaction, help them grow into the deeper light, so came Kalidasa and others. The coming of Sri Chaitanya and the various saints of the Santmat established Bhakti and the possibility of opening the various levels and parts of the vital, emotional being to the Divine with greater completeness. Bhakti could transcend and synthesise all other ways and means on the ultimate path. As an overabundance of paths and sects mushroomed, Sri Ramakrishna provided a synthesizing influence weaving them into a single strand leading to the Divine. But without the transformation of Matter, the most material part of the being, there was always a blockage, a stumbling block to the complete consecration; death always proved to be an abrupt pause, a long hiatus on the greatest spiritual journey. But this coming down of the Spirit to the very realm of matter and the material human nature to act upon and transform them, is for it, in a sense, fighting the battle in enemy’s own territory in utterly adverse conditions. For, it has to meet a fierce resistance of the grosser parts and, therefore, it cannot act upon them with the same facility with which it could upon the higher parts of the human nature. Sri Aurobindo and The Mother have come with their secret of the Supramental descent to solve this last riddle, provide the final answer.

Having provided a bird’s eye view of the essential spirit of Indian religion and the forms it developed in the Vedic and the Vedantic ages, Sri Aurobindo here does the same for the post-Vedic age. It is only in the light of this vast overview that one can see the hidden logic and a perfect coherence behind all the various forms taken by Indian religion in different ages. An evolution so begun had to proceed by a sort of enriching descent from the spirit to matter and to pass on first to an intellectual endeavour to see life and the world and the self in all their relations as they present themselves to the reasoning and the practical intelligence. When the mind is open to higher truths, it tries to analyse and organise life and the world in that light. This inevitably brings about a remarkable upliftment in all the aspects of individual and collective existence. As in India, we find a similar period of an outburst of high intelligence in other cultures also, accompanied by a great activity in the various fields of human thought and life. But there is a fundamental difference between the path taken by this intellectual development in India and in other cultures. While in other cultures the intellect diverged from the original intuition and lost its touch with the deeper truths which resulted in a growing dominance of the vital nature in man, in Indian culture the Rishis always gave spirituality the paramount importance and kept the human mind and intellect subservient to it which, to a great extent, prevented the intellect from becoming a stooge of the ego and the blind vital propensities. One must never lose sight of this fundamental truth that to subordinate the intellect, or any other part of our being, to a higher light does not in any way limit its scope or confine its possibilities. On the contrary, it greatly widens its scope, opens up before it such novel possibilities and vistas as would otherwise have not been possible or even conceivable. This explains the secret behind the multifarious activity in India, unparalleled both in quality and quantity, not only in the things of the mind and the spirit but even in those areas concerned more with the outer material life. Our epic literature vividly illustrates through various episodes, tales and anecdotes how each and every activity and detail of life can be successfully dealt with in a higher light and given a higher turn. Thus we find there is a whole scale of rising truths ranging from the ethical and moral to progressively more exalted spiritual truths through which both an individual and the collectivity could ascend towards the highest spiritual attainment. There is hardly enough appreciation of this prodigious attempt — not even conceived anywhere else — and supreme achievement of this culture in having successfully dealt with and turned Godwards even the most unruly and despotic parts of our being. It is in this context that Sri Aurobindo writes here ‘The enlarged secular turn was compensated by a deepening of the intensities of psycho-religious experience’. This great attempt reaches its culmination in the Bhagawat Purana where not only all the different parts of the human being with their own nature and disposition but even the demonic or Asuric natures and tendencies are brought into contact with the Divine.

When Sri Aurobindo says that ‘Science too developed, but it came second only as an auxiliary power’, it should not be taken to mean that the development of science was ignored in this culture, for the overwhelming record of the prolific achievements in the field of physical science leave no shadow of doubt on that account. He is just affirming, through this comparison, the paramount importance that this culture always gave to the higher pursuits giving all else a secondary place. Western culture, with its materialistic outlook, supposes matter to be the sole basis of everything and firmly believes that a deeper probe into the laws of matter will eventually enable it to thoroughly understand and solve all the problems of physical existence. Indian culture, starting from a completely different and a deeper outlook, firmly held that only by entering into the mysteries of the higher realms can the working of the lower ones be truly understood and effectively mastered. This is why all the later philosophies and schools of thought in India accepted the truths revealed in the Vedas and the Vedanta as final and concerned themselves not with the enquiry of the fundamental cause or the why of this creation, but rather with the application of those truths, or say, with the interpretation of how those truths, contained in the Veda, unfolded and manifested themselves in the outermost parts of our being. All the later schools of thought in India, however divergent or discordant in themselves, and however ignorant of the deeper meaning of the Veda, unquestionably accept the Veda as their rock of firm foundation. Swami Dayananda even went so far as to assert that the Vedas not only contain the profound spiritual, psychological and inner truths of our being and existence but even those truths of physical nature to which modern science has only arrived at with much difficulty, and even more, it contains even those truths to which science can hardly ever arrive at or even conceive of with its current approach of enquiry.

One can thus see how from the Vedic origin to all the later ages, religion has always been the chief note and a constant undercurrent of Indian culture and has always had its great influence not only in the fields of mind and spirit such as philosophy, art, literature etc. but even on the more outward concerns of material life. The constancy of the essential spirit even in the apparent change in outer forms of religion can very well be equated to that perennial stream that even while assuming different forms according to the changing course of its flow remains essentially the same throughout. This is a common phenomenon even in the life of a true spiritual seeker when the outer expression in life inevitably changes with his progressive ascension in consciousness and the resulting change in the states of inner and psychological development. But this outer change is a spontaneous outcome of the inner development and does not come by any revolt. This clearly explains the statement of Sri Aurobindo that, ‘Indian religion followed this line of evolution and kept its inner continuity with its Vedic and Vedantic origins; but it changed entirely its mental contents and colour and its outward basis. It did not effectuate this change through any protestant revolt or revolution or with any idea of an iconoclastic reformation.’ The Purano-tantric stage followed the post-Vedic stage of religion. ‡

(iii) The Purano-Tantric Stage

“This lasting line of change moved forward not by any destruction of principle, but by a gradual fading out of the prominent Vedic forms and the substitution of others. There was a transformation of symbol and ritual and ceremony or a substitution of new kindred figures, an emergence of things that are only hints in the original system, a development of novel idea-forms from the seed of the original thinking. And especially there was a farther widening and fathoming of psychic and spiritual experience. The Vedic gods rapidly lost their deep original significance. At first they kept their hold by their outer cosmic sense but were overshadowed by the great Trinity, Brahma-Vishnu-Shiva, and afterwards faded altogether. A new pantheon appeared which in its outward symbolic aspects expressed a deeper truth and larger range of religious experience, an intenser feeling, a vaster idea. The Vedic sacrifice persisted only in broken and lessening fragments. The house of Fire was replaced by the temple; the karmic ritual of sacrifice was transformed into the devotional temple ritual; the vague and shifting mental images of the Vedic gods figured in the mantras yielded to more precise conceptual forms of the two great deities, Vishnu and Shiva, and of their Shaktis and their offshoots. These new concepts stabilised in physical images which were made the basis both for internal adoration and for the external worship which replaced sacrifice. The psychic and spiritual mystic endeavour which was the inner sense of the Vedic hymns, disappeared into the less intensely luminous but more wide and rich and complex psycho-spiritual inner life of Puranic and Tantric religion and Yoga.

The Purano-Tantric stage of the religion was once decried by European critics and Indian reformers as a base and ignorant degradation of an earlier and purer religion. It was rather an effort, successful in a great measure, to open the general mind of the people to a higher and deeper range of inner truth and experience and feeling. Much of the adverse criticism once heard proceeded from a total ignorance of the sense and intention of this worship. Much of this criticism has been uselessly concentrated on side-paths and aberrations which could hardly be avoided in this immensely audacious experimental widening of the basis of the culture. For there was a catholic attempt to draw towards the spiritual truth minds of all qualities and people of all classes. Much was lost of the profound psychic knowledge of the Vedic seers, but much also of new knowledge was developed, untrodden ways were opened and a hundred gates discovered into the Infinite. If we try to see the essential sense and aim of this development and the intrinsic value of its forms and means and symbols, we shall find that this evolution followed upon the early Vedic form very much for the same reason as Catholic Christianity replaced the mysteries and sacrifices of the early Pagan religions. For in both cases the outward basis of the early religion spoke to the outward physical mind of the people and took that as the starting-point of its appeal. But the new evolution tried to awaken a more inner mind even in the common man, to lay hold on his inner vital and emotional nature, to support all by an awakening of the soul and to lead him through these things towards a highest spiritual truth. It attempted in fact to bring the mass into the temple of the spirit rather than leave them in the outer precincts. The outward physical sense was satisfied through its aesthetic turn by a picturesque temple worship, by numerous ceremonies, by the use of physical images; but these were given a psycho-emotional sense and direction that was open to the heart and imagination of the ordinary man and not reserved for the deeper sight of the elect or the strenuous tapasya of the initiates. The secret initiation remained but was now a condition for the passage from the surface psycho-emotional and religious to a profounder psychic-spiritual truth and experience.

Nothing essential was touched in its core by this new orientation; but the instruments, atmosphere, field of religious experience underwent a considerable change. The Vedic godheads were to the mass of their worshippers divine powers who presided over the workings of the outward life of the physical cosmos; the Puranic Trinity had even for the multitude a predominant psycho-religious and spiritual significance. Its more external significances, for instance the functions of cosmic creation, preservation and destruction, were only a dependent fringe of these profundities that alone touched the heart of its mystery. The central spiritual truth remained in both systems the same, the truth of the One in many aspects. The Trinity is a triple form of the one supreme Godhead and Brahman; the Shaktis are energies of the one Energy of the highest divine Being. But this greatest religious truth was no longer reserved for the initiated few; it was now more and more brought powerfully, widely and intensely home to the general mind and feeling of the people. Even the so-called henotheism of the Vedic idea was prolonged and heightened in the larger and simpler worship of Vishnu or Shiva as the one universal and highest Godhead of whom all others are living forms and powers. The idea of the Divinity in man was popularised to an extraordinary extent, not only the occasional manifestation of the Divine in humanity which founded the worship of the Avataras, but the Presence discoverable in the heart of every creature. The systems of Yoga developed themselves on the same common basis. All led or hoped to lead through many kinds of psycho-physical, inner vital, inner mental and psycho-spiritual methods to the common aim of all Indian spirituality, a greater consciousness and a more or less complete union with the One and Divine or else an immergence of the individual soul in the Absolute. The Purano-Tantric system was a wide, assured and many-sided endeavour, unparalleled in its power, insight, amplitude, to provide the race with a basis of generalised psycho-religious experience from which man could rise through knowledge, works or love or through any other fundamental power of his nature to some established supreme experience and highest absolute status.”51

‡ It is Sri Aurobindo alone who gives us such a comprehensive perspective of the Purano-Tantric stage of Indian religion. When viewed in this light, we find, on the one hand that the numerous misunderstandings, misconceptions and criticisms of this period are the result of viewing it from a deluded point of view or from a view concentrated on one of its many side paths or ways or evaluating it while suffering from prejudice. On the other hand, if the evolution of Indian religion is viewed rightly, we find the inevitability of this stage, its true justification and paramount importance. It is Purano-Tantric development which has kept the Soul of India, the Indian religion, the stream of spirituality alive, up until today, otherwise it would have been dead among the educated people of the present like the cultures of Greece and Rome. That is why Sri Aurobindo says that, generally, echoing western critics, we attempt to base ourselves intellectually on the Upanishads and the Gita, trying to denigrate the Puranas by calling them a collection of mythological stories, but in practice, we live much more by the religion of the Puranas and Tantras than by the Upanishads, because the Puranas and Tantras are practical applications in life of that same profound inner spiritual experience which the Upanishads express intellectually. However, if the truth can be manifested only in the pure intellect or the higher parts of the human being then, the lower parts could never experience the touch of their truth and find their inherent fulfilment. In such a case, there would always be the likelihood that the religion established in the intellect would be fossilised, in the dead formalism of religious Theism or the dry intellectualisation of Philosophy like that of the Europeans. The Purano-Tantric stage saved Indian religion from exactly this possibility. It acted as a bridge which gave the people a comprehensive corpus of thoughts, parables and symbols which attracted their imagination and emotions, their ethical and aesthetic being and were partly manifestations of the spiritual Truth and partly that of ordinary religious sentiment and spiritual emotion. It made it easier for people to spontaneously turn their more external, practical and emotional nature towards the treasures of the Spirit and permit it to have an increasing entry into their life.

If we would deal, in brief, with the common misconceptions about this development of religion, then, first and foremost, it has to be understood that this was not the result of any kind of distortion or depletion nor was it a diminished or ignorant successor of an ancient and pure religion. These kind of misconceptions arise when we are completely ignorant of the profound meaning and purpose behind the outer forms, symbols, rituals etc. that the religion uses at this stage; or, when we begin to think that the limitations and falsifications of the notions of Truth that religion has to accept in an attempt to work on human nature are the distortions of the Truth itself. Another major reason for the accusations of distortion has been the fact that, unlike the Vedic and Vedantic times, when only initiates and spiritually developed souls were allowed into the mystical doors the purity of the religion was easier to maintain; in the Purano-Tantric times, the hugely ambitious, comprehensive and largely successful endeavor was made to bring the common people under the influence of the Spirit. But it would be unreasonable to expect the religion to retain its original purity in so all-encompassing an effort. Leading even a committed group of people towards a higher ideal becomes a challenging task without a developed spiritual consciousness and balance because of the limitations of human nature. So even the concept of manifesting materially the spiritual Truth on a collective scale is an indication, not of the pettiness or deficiency of the religion but of its ultimate courage and greatness. And the organisation of the necessary means and resources to fulfil such a concept shows the superhuman capacity of Indian culture. Thus seen, we appreciate not only the baselessness of the accusations and criticisms but also the paramount importance of this stage in the endurance of the Indian religion. At the same time, we must not forget that human nature has always, more or less, lived in the external, desire-ridden consciousness bound by the body. It is only the presence of the Rishis and Yogis that has kept the spiritual lineage unbroken in all ages and times, has made the spiritual truths clear, accessible and effective for humans and has created the various means by which the ordinary human mind can turn towards and even enter into those truths. ‡

(iv) The Third and the Last Stage

“This great effort and achievement which covered all the time between the Vedic age and the decline of Buddhism, was still not the last possibility of religious evolution open to Indian culture. The Vedic training of the physically-minded man made the development possible. But in its turn this raising of the basis of religion to the inner mind and life and psychic nature, this training and bringing out of the psychic man ought to make possible a still larger development and support a greater spiritual movement as the leading power of life. The first stage makes possible the preparation of the natural external man for spirituality; the second takes up his outward life into a deeper mental and psychical living and brings him more directly into contact with the spirit and divinity within him; the third should render him capable of taking up his whole mental, psychical, physical living into a first beginning at least of a generalised spiritual life. This endeavour has manifested itself in the evolution of Indian spirituality and is the significance of the latest philosophies, the great spiritual movements of the saints and bhaktas and an increasing resort to the various paths of Yoga. But unhappily it synchronised with a decline of Indian culture and an increasing collapse of its general power and knowledge, and in these surroundings it could not bear its natural fruit; but at the same time it has done much to prepare such a possibility in the future. If Indian culture is to survive and keep its spiritual basis and innate character, it is in this direction, and not in a mere revival or prolongation of the Puranic system, that its evolution must turn, rising so towards the fulfilment of that which the Vedic seers saw as the aim of man and his life thousands of years ago and the Vedantic sages cast into the clear and immortal forms of their luminous revelation.

Even the psychic-emotional part of man’s nature is not the inmost door to religious feeling, nor is his inner mind the highest witness to spiritual experience. There is behind the first the inmost soul of man, in that deepest secret heart, hṛdaye guhāyām, in which the ancient seers saw the very tabernacle of the indwelling Godhead and there is above the second a luminous highest mind directly open to a truth of the Spirit to which man’s normal nature has as yet only an occasional and momentary access. Religious evolution, spiritual experience can find their true native road only when they open to these hidden powers and make them their support for a lasting change, a divinisation of human life and nature. An effort of this kind was the very force behind the most luminous and vivid of the later movements of India’s vast religious cycle. It is the secret of the most powerful forms of Vaishnavism and Tantra and Yoga. The labour of ascent from our half-animal human nature into the fresh purity of the spiritual consciousness needed to be followed and supplemented by a descent of the light and force of the spirit into man’s members and the attempt to transform human into divine nature.

But it could not find its complete way or its fruit because it synchronised with a decline of the life force in India and a lowering of power and knowledge in her general civilisation and culture. Nevertheless here lies the destined force of her survival and renewal, this is the dynamic meaning of her future. A widest and highest spiritualising of life on earth is the last vision of all that vast and unexampled seeking and experiment in a thousand ways of the soul’s outermost and innermost experience which is the unique character of her past; this in the end is the mission for which she was born and the meaning of her existence.”52

‡ Qs: How should one look at the decline of the vitality of Indian culture and an increasing collapse of its general power and knowledge?

Ans: There can be more than one way in which this can be viewed in the light of Sri Aurobindo. Firstly, one must always bear in mind that the action of the Divine Mother is so vast and many-sided that it is impossible even for the deepest, freest and the most profound mental intelligence to understand, define or formulate it. The formulations can be no more than various ways of looking at the Absolute Truth that can at best capture some kind of glimpse of it. Therefore, when a culture begins with some conception of truth, however high or wide that may be, and strives to express that into outer forms, inevitably it finds, sooner or later, that once the utility of those forms is over they tend to become insufficient, or even bondages, for the expression of the original idea. Besides, even the original conception in itself being a partial truth needs to be perpetually renewed, failing which a culture is bound to undergo a period of decline or degeneration, as is evident from the case of even those civilisations of the past that had once succeeded in reaching great heights of growth and expansion. During its long historical past, Indian civilisation too has time and again undergone such periods of transition. But an unbroken continuity of saints and sages here not only kept on renewing that Absolute truth in their own experiences but even reestablished it by moulding it into new forms more suitable for the need of the spirit of the age. This has been the perennial source of light and renovation that has always kept this culture moving steadily towards its goal. Even in times of foreign invasions, dominations and their gruesome atrocities, the force of her survival and revival remained intact due to the presence of great spiritual masters. Sri Aurobindo reveals in one of his writings that even in our own era when scepticism had reached its height, and a time had come for spirituality to reassert itself and establish the reality of the world as a manifestation of the spirit, Sri Ramakrishna came to begin the consummation of this work by harmonising and revivifying all the spiritual teaching and experience of the previous two thousand years and more since Buddha appeared. Therefore, for most other cultures, the insufficiency of outer forms to house the spirit may have been the main reason behind their decline and decay, but the same is not true in the case of Indian culture. We must therefore bring into consideration other possible aspects to get some perspective on the decline of the vitality of Indian culture.

If one looks from a deeper perspective at the whole curve of the evolution of Indian religion, which through the ages, has gradually moved down towards the descending planes of consciousness bringing under the Spirit’s influence and infusing with its light even the most external and material parts of human nature to turn them into the soul’s instruments for its faultless expression. In the far off times, the times of the Vedas, the Rishis were moved through the intuition and there was no need of set forms and institutions, the Spirit permeated and moulded the whole of society directly through the intuition of the Rishis. Then as the intellect and mental being needed to be moulded, the Spirit came through the Upanishads and Vedanta, creating mental forms for the expression of the Spirit. The six Darshanas arose with their revelation of the different aspects of the Divine and practical ways of reaching him, with Gita as the crowning movement, synthesising the different strands masterfully by rising above them all. Then as the Spirit descended into the heart, the emotional being, into the various strands of life, came the Puranas and the Tantra, to establish the possibility of opening all these aspects of life to the Divine. Various ways of worshipping the Divine through the emotional and sensational being developed along with a plethora of rites, rituals, religious ceremonies connecting man to the Divinity concealed in every element of creation. The age of Kalidasa and others effected an opening of the hedonistic parts of our being making it easier for them to turn towards the Divine. The coming of Sri Chaitanya and the various saints of the Santmat established Bhakti and the possibility of opening the various levels and parts of the vital, emotional being to the Divine with greater completeness. Bhakti can transcend all other ways and means on the ultimate path. As an overabundance of paths and sects mushroomed, Sri Ramakrishna provided a synthesizing influence weaving them into a single strand leading to the Divine. But without the transformation of Matter, the most material part of the being, there was always a blockage, a stumbling block to the complete consecration; death always proved to be an abrupt pause, a long hiatus on the greatest spiritual journey. But this coming down of the Spirit to the very realm of matter and the material human nature to act upon and transform them, is for it, in a sense, like fighting the battle in enemy’s own territory in utterly adverse conditions. For, it has to meet a fierce resistance of the grossest parts and, therefore, it cannot act upon them with the same facility with which it could upon the higher parts of the human being. Sri Aurobindo and The Mother have come with their secret of the Supramental descent to solve this last riddle, provide the final answer. Along with this development of Dharma, there is yet another more universal cycle of Yugas (ages) that moves from Satyayuga to Kali and through Kali to the Satya. According to the Hindu theory of the Yugas, in the Satyayuga, Yajna, the spirit of sacrifice reigns in the hearts of men and they follow the law by the power of their purified nature and full knowledge. Therefore, there is no need of external ritual, external sacrifices, elaborate law, government, castes, classes and creeds. In the Treta the old perfect order begins to break and Vishnu descends as the Chakravarti raja, the warrior and ruler, and the sword, law and the written Veda are instituted to govern men. But there is still great elasticity and freedom and within certain limits men follow the healthy impulse of their nature, only slightly corrupted by the first descent from purity. It is in the Dwapara, when one is further alienated from one’s inner being, that form and rule have to take the place of the idea and the spirit as the true governors of religion, ethics and society. Vishnu then descends as Vyasa to codify, ritualise and formalise everything to provide detailed codes of conduct to help an individual and the society at each step to securely move according to dharma. Kaliyuga then destroys all these laws and codes of conduct. When we consider these two movements and look at our present debilitated condition we can see how far we have drifted away from the original vigour and strength. Indeed, all the great achievements in the field of human thought, action and experience of the Vedic and post-Vedic eras of Indian culture seem almost unimaginable and impossible for the present human capability. Even the account of the great intellectual, ethical, moral and physical strength and capacity of the people that we get from history seems to the present mentality rather a fiction or an exaggerated literary production than a reality. It is this period of transition of this culture to which the eye of the antagonist turns and, refusing to see or recognise the millenniums of culture and greatness of Indian civilisation, tries to present before us in the strongest terms possible the poverty, confusion and disorganisation of a period of temporary decline as the whole of this culture. It is only in the light of Sri Aurobindo that one gets a true perspective and understanding of not only this transitional stage of the culture but also of how the supreme intelligence of Rishis has always been active even in the darkest days to guide this culture towards its true mission.

Further, while talking about the third and the last stage of religion Sri Aurobindo states here that this stage should render man capable of taking up his whole mental, psychical, physical living at least into a first beginning of a generalised spiritual life. It is this raising and transformation even of the very material life and nature which has been envisioned by the Vedic rishis since time immemorial as the true aim of man and his existence. Although from the very outset this culture has cut out infinite roads and developed innumerable systems to move towards the spiritual goal, still all of these have been in the most part concerned with the individual and his pursuit towards the spiritual ideal, and the great endeavour of the Sanatana Dharma to effectively establish and express itself in the human collectivity seems to have found no secure basis as yet. But when the culture reached a stage where the surface physical nature of man began to dominate and, overshadowing the original intuition, the egoistic forces came to take the precedence, it posed a serious problem in the synthesis, unification and management of not only more than a hundred kingdoms, clans, peoples, tribes, races with their own distinct cultural identities but also of the innumerable systems of Yoga, spiritual paths, traditions, schools of thought, etc. that existed in the vast territory of India. It was the supreme intelligence and intuition of the great Rishis and founders of this culture who saw that to keep the culture and Sanatana Dharma alive in such conditions, a conscious spiritual and cultural unity of all these peoples was the first, the indispensable condition without which no enduring political and imperial unity could be possible. It was with these considerations that the Rishis, the guardians of India’s destiny, wisely and consciously chose to refuse any strong outward political unification, whatever the consequences. But those who have no sense of the deeper working and truth of things, strongly condemn and point out that by not insisting primarily on an imperial unity, India had to suffer its painful consequences. It is usually these consequences of a conscious choice that to a surface mentality seem to be the obvious signs of decline or downfall of this culture and the indisputable proofs of its weakness and incapacity. But would it not have been a greater disaster for India, and even more so for the whole world, if it had staked and lost its original peculiarity, its indelible spiritual stamp and its underlying oneness amidst all diversities in an attempt to achieve some outward unity by artificial means. As Yogi Sri Krishnaprem said, “When the traditions of a nation die, then the nation is dead, and even if it persists as a great Power in the world, yet it is nothing but an aggregate of meaningless individuals determinedly pursuing their contemptible aims.” (Yogi Sri Krishnaprem, Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan, 1992 edition, page 8) For example, even a strong political unification effected by an external rule centralised, imposed or constructed, as was done in Rome or ancient Persia, by a conquering kingdom or the genius of a military and organising people did not endure, but India still survives, and that too in a true sense, and firmly advances towards its destined goal. It is only when viewed in this light that behind all the seemingly incoherent accidents one gets some glimpse of a perfectly guided action by the higher wisdom of our Rishis. Also, the decline of the vitality of Indian culture and an increasing collapse of its general power and knowledge should not be taken to mean the decline of this culture. Any culture necessarily meets in its course periods of crisis and transition and, therefore, its true greatness lies in its power of survival, renovation and adaptation to new phases of the permanent needs of the race. The coming of Sri Aurobindo, in a way, marks the commencement of a new phase that assures us of the renaissance of Indian culture and also of the movement towards the consummation of the destined goal of Sanatana Dharma. Not only did the soul of India reveal and revive its past mysteries through Sri Aurobindo but has even placed before the individual and collective human soul the whole blueprint of its future movement towards the establishment of a divine life in a divine body. Even his proclamation of the advent of divine life on earth by the manifestation of supramental consciousness is a continuation of the spiritual movement of Indian culture. ‡

[9]	The Gita recognises four kinds or degrees of worshippers and God-seekers. There are first the arthārthī and ārta, those who seek him for the fulfilment of desire and those who turn for divine help in the sorrow and suffering of existence; there is next the jijñāsu, the seeker of knowledge, the questioner who is moved to seek the Divine in his truth and in that to meet him; last and highest, there is the jñānī who has already contact with the truth and is able to live in unity with the Spirit.

[10]	“The ancients held that all men are born in their lower nature as Shudras and only regenerated by ethical and spiritual culture, but in their highest inner self are Brahmanas capable of the full spirit and godhead, a theory which is not far perhaps from the psychological truth of our nature.”48

The above psychological truth of our nature must have been at the root of this prohibition because, otherwise, if based on a system of distinguishing between persons merely on the basis of a system of Caste or Varna based on birth, it is an entire absurdity to which no right minded person can acquiesce to. It is however, correct to say that no person who lives predominantly in his surface physical nature (as most do) and is, therefore, a being of very small (shudra) consciousness, can profitably study the Veda.

[11] Cittim acittiṁ cinavad vi vidvān. “Let the knower distinguish the Knowledge and the Ignorance.”

[12]	Buddha himself does not seem to have preached his tenets as a novel revolutionary creed, but as the old Aryan way, the true form of the eternal religion.

H. The Dynamic Formulation of Indian Religious Culture

“The past dealings of Indian religion with life must be judged according to the stages of its progress; each age of its movement must be considered on its own basis. But throughout it consistently held to two perceptions that showed great practical wisdom and a fine spiritual tact.”53

‡ After having illuminated the various outer and inner forms that the Indian religion has taken during the different stages through which it passed, Sri Aurobindo now moves on to deliberate upon how this religion could make its aim of leading a man from his present unregenerate stage to self-realisation so effective in practice.

As we have been discussing from the beginning, Indian culture has always had a deeper view of existence and looked upon a human being as a soul that, in this terrestrial manifestation, has put on a personality made up of mind, life and body for its self-expression. But rather than regarding it as some sublime conception void of any practical bearing on life, when a culture moves on to erect a comprehensive collective system that can most effectively — swiftly and integrally — lead both an individual and the collectivity to the realisation of this ideal, inevitably there will arise some fundamental perceptions about the complexities of inner and outer nature of both an individual and the society. Here, Sri Aurobindo sheds light on how this culture held consistently to these fundamental perceptions and how it put them into effect. ‡

(i) The First Perception

“First, it saw that the approach to the spirit cannot be sudden, simple and immediate for all individuals or for the community of men; it must come ordinarily or at least at first through a gradual culture, training, progress. There must be an enlarging of the natural life accompanied by an uplifting of all its motives; a growing hold upon it of the higher rational, psychic and ethical powers must prepare and lead it towards a higher spiritual law.”54

(ii) The Second Perception

“But the Indian religious mind saw too at the same time that if its greater aim was to be fruitful and the character of its culture imperative, there must be throughout and at every moment some kind of insistence on the spiritual motive. And for the mass of men this means always some kind of religious influence. That pervasive insistence was necessary in order that from the beginning some power of the universal inner truth, some ray from the real reality of our existence might cast its light or at least its sensible if subtle influence on the natural life of man. Human life must be induced to flower, naturally in a way, but at the same time with a wise nurturing and cultivation into its own profounder spiritual significance. Indian culture has worked by two coordinated, mutually stimulating and always interblended operations of which these perceptions are the principle. First, it has laboured to lead upward and enlarge the life of the individual in the community through a natural series of life-stages till it was ready for the spiritual levels. But also it has striven to keep that highest aim before the mind at every stage and throw its influence on each circumstance and action both of man’s inner and his outer existence.”55

(iii) The Frame for the Execution of Its First Perception – The Triple Quartette

In the plan of its first perception or aim it came nearer to the highest ancient cultures in other regions but in its execution its system was in a type and with a motive all its own. “The frame of its system was constituted by a triple quartette. Its first circle was the synthesis and gradation of the fourfold object of life, vital desire and hedonistic enjoyment, personal and communal interest, moral right and law, and spiritual liberation. Its second circle was the fourfold order of society, carefully graded and equipped with its fixed economic functions and its deeper cultural, ethical and spiritual significances. Its third, the most original and indeed unique of its englobing life-patterns, was the fourfold scale of the successive stages of life, student, householder, forest recluse and free supersocial man. This frame, these lines of a large and noble life-training subsisted in their purity, their grand natural balance of austerity and accommodation, their fine effectiveness during the later Vedic and heroic age of the civilisation: afterwards they crumbled slowly or lost their completeness and order. But the tradition, the idea with some large effect of its force and some figure of its lines endured throughout the whole period of cultural vigour. However deflected it might have been from its true form and spirit, however mutilated and complicated for the worse, there was always left some presence of its inspiration and power. Only in the decline do we get the slow collapse, the degraded and confused mass of conventions which still labours to represent the ancient and noble Aryan system, but in spite of relics of glamour and beauty, in spite of survivals of spiritual suggestion and in spite of a residue of the old high training, is little better than a detritus or a mass of confused relics. Still even in this degradation enough of the original virtue has remained to ensure a remarkable remnant of the ancient beauty, attractiveness and power of survival.”56

(iv) The Cultural Effort for the Execution of the Second Perception – the Endeavour to Cast the Whole Life into a Religious Mould

This is a more direct spiritual operation of Indian culture than the first and is of a still greater importance because it coloured permanently the Indian mind and life and has remained the same – always renewed its effectiveness and held its field – behind every change of form and throughout all the ages of the civilisation. This cultural effort “...multiplied means and devices which by their insistent suggestion and opportunity and their mass of effect would help to stamp a Godward tendency on the entire existence. Indian culture was founded on a religious conception of life and both the individual and the community drank in at every moment its influence. It was stamped on them by the training and turn of the education; the entire life atmosphere, all the social surroundings were suffused with it; it breathed its power through the whole original form and hieratic character of the culture. Always was felt the near idea of the spiritual existence and its supremacy as the ideal, highest over all others; everywhere there was the pervading pressure of the notion of the universe as a manifestation of divine Powers and a movement full of the presence of the Divine. Man himself was not a mere reasoning animal, but a soul in constant relation with God and with the divine cosmic Powers. The soul’s continued existence was a cyclic or upward progress from birth to birth; human life was the summit of an evolution which terminated in the conscious Spirit, every stage of that life a step in a pilgrimage. Every single action of man had its importance of fruit whether in future lives or in the worlds beyond the material existence.”57

‡ The wonderful elucidation by Sri Aurobindo of the first two perceptions of this culture reveals in essence, the whole of the course of development of this culture from the original conception to its actual working out. It is only in the light of this wide perspective that one can get a true sense of all the various forms — both outward and inner — that this culture adopted for the fulfilment of its fundamental spirit.

While setting before itself the goal of self-realisation and self-attainment, Indian culture also knew well that the emergence from the natural unregenerate state and the movement towards the spirit cannot be sudden, simple and immediate for all individuals. For, each carries within itself some special attribute or aspect of the Divine which it has to work out and manifest through the great complexity of the various parts of its being. And ordinarily, this can come only through a long and arduous process of gradual culture, training and progress.

Qs: Deliberating on the first perception of Indian culture, Sri Aurobindo says, “There must be an enlarging of the natural life accompanied by an uplifting of all its motives”, what does this statement truly mean?

Ans: As in one’s physical life one has to undergo various stages of physical development before reaching maturity, the same applies to the other parts of our being which also need training, refinement, culture and enlargement before they can be prepared for a truer and larger working. Generally, a natural man begins at a stage where not only his intellectual, ethical, and aesthetic faculties are abeyant, but also he is confined in a petty egoistic consciousness and, therefore, the balance of his being is such that the action of the lower parts is much stronger than that of the higher and deeper ones. The whole outlook on life and its motives at this stage remains entirely superficial and shut up within a narrow circle. Therefore, before one reaches a stage where one is ready to undertake the spiritual pursuit in life, it is necessary first to cultivate one’s intellectual, moral, aesthetic and other latent inner powers and faculties to bring about, in their light, not only an enlargement of the natural unregenerate life but even an ever-growing upliftment of the otherwise limited outlook on life and its motives. It is a fact of common observation that as compared to someone concentrated grossly on the satisfaction of his animalistic and petty appetites, one with developed aesthetic or ethical faculties has much wider and greater aims and perspectives, field of action, possibilities and the resulting manifestation and fulfilment in life. As one ascends higher in scale, the whole framework of life, its scope and its motives too keep enlarging. It was in view of putting into effect this fundamental perception that a whole wide system of triple quartettes was laid down by this culture to help a growing soul (whatever its current stage of inner and outer life) to successively ascend towards ever greater scales of spiritual illumination. ‡

(v) The Third Perception – The Varying Natural Capacity of Man, Adhikāra

The Indian religion was not content with merely creating the general pressure of its noble conceptions. “Its persistent effort was to impress the mind at every moment and in each particular with the religious influence. And to do this more effectively by a living and practical adaptation, not asking from anyone what was too much for him or too little, it took as a guiding idea its perception of the varying natural capacity of man, adhikāra. It provided in its system means by which each man high or low, wise or ignorant, exceptional or average might feel in the way suitable to his nature and evolutionary stage the call, the pressure, the influence. Avoiding the error of the religions that impose a single dogmatic and inflexible rule on every man regardless of the possibilities of his nature, it tried rather to draw him gently upward and help him to grow steadily in religious and spiritual experience. Every part of human nature, every characteristic turn of its action was given a place in the system; each was suitably surrounded with the spiritual idea and a religious influence, each provided with steps by which it might rise towards its own spiritual possibility and significance. The highest spiritual meaning of life was set on the summits of each evolving power of the human nature. The intelligence was called to a supreme knowledge, the dynamic active and creative powers pointed to openness and unity with an infinite and universal Will, the heart and sense put in contact with a divine love and joy and beauty. But this highest meaning was also put everywhere indicatively or in symbols behind the whole system of living, even in its details, so that its impression might fall in whatever degree on the life, increase in pervasion and in the end take up the entire control. This was the aim and, if we consider the imperfections of our nature and the difficulty of the endeavour, we can say that it achieved an unusual measure of success. It has been said with some truth that for the Indian the whole of life is a religion. True of the ideal of Indian life, it is true to a certain degree and in a certain sense in its fact and practice. No step could be taken in the Indian’s inner or outer life without his being reminded of a spiritual existence. Everywhere he felt the closeness or at least saw the sign of something beyond his natural life, beyond the moment in time, beyond his individual ego, something other than the needs and interests of his vital and physical nature. That insistence gave its tone and turn to his thought and action and feeling; it produced that subtler sensitiveness to the spiritual appeal, that greater readiness to turn to the spiritual effort which are even now distinguishing marks of the Indian temperament. It is that readiness, that sensitiveness which justifies us when we speak of the characteristic spirituality of the Indian people.

The ancient idea of the adhikāra has to be taken into careful account if we would understand the peculiar character of Indian religion. In most other religious systems we find a high-pitched spiritual call and a difficult and rigid ethical standard far beyond the possibilities of man’s half-evolved, defective and imperfect nature. This standard, this call are announced as if imperative on all; but it is evident that only a few can give an adequate response. There is presented to our view for all our picture of life the sharp division of two extremes; the saint and the worldling, the religious and the irreligious, the good and the bad, the pious and the impious, souls accepted and souls rejected, the sheep and the goats, the saved and the damned, the believer and the infidel, are the two categories set constantly before us. All between is a confusion, a tug of war, an uncertain balance. This crude and summary classification is the foundation of the Christian system of an eternal heaven and hell; at best, the Catholic religion humanely interposes a precarious chance hung between that happy and this dread alternative, the chance of a painful purgatory for more than nine tenths of the human race. Indian religion set up on its summits a still more high-pitched spiritual call, a standard of conduct still more perfect and absolute; but it did not go about its work with this summary and unreflecting ignorance. All beings are to the Indian mind portions of the Divine, evolving souls, and sure of an eventual salvation and release into the spirit. All must feel, as the good in them grows or, more truly, the godhead in them finds itself and becomes conscious, the ultimate touch and call of their highest self and through that call the attraction to the Eternal and Divine.”58

(vi) The Means Used to Give Effect to the Third Perception – the Perception of the Three Types or Levels of the Evolving Human Soul and the Creation of the Varying Religious Atmosphere Suited to Each

“...in life there are infinite differences between man and man; some are more inwardly evolved, others are less mature, many if not most are infant souls incapable of great steps and difficult efforts. Each needs to be dealt with according to his nature and his soul stature. But a general distinction can be drawn between three principal types varying in their openness to the spiritual appeal or to the religious influence or impulse. This distinction amounts to a gradation of three stages in the growing human consciousness. One crude, ill-formed, still outward, still vitally and physically minded can be led only by devices suited to its ignorance. Another, more developed and capable of a much stronger and deeper psycho-spiritual experience, offers a riper make of manhood gifted with a more conscious intelligence, a larger vital or aesthetic opening, a stronger ethical power of the nature. A third, the ripest and most developed of all, is ready for the spiritual heights, fit to receive or to climb towards the loftiest ultimate truth of God and of its own being and to tread the summits of divine experience.”[13] 59

It was understood that there was the need to provide each type the religious atmosphere suited to its needs. “It was to meet the need of the first type or level that Indian religion created that mass of suggestive ceremony and effective ritual and strict outward rule and injunction and all that pageant of attracting and compelling symbol with which the cult is so richly equipped or profusely decorated. These are for the most part forming and indicative things which work upon the mind consciently and subconsciently and prepare it for an entry into the significance of the greater permanent things that lie behind them. And for this type too, for its vital mind and will, is intended all in the religion that calls on man to turn to a divine Power or powers for the just satisfaction of his desires and his interests, just because subject to the right and the law, the Dharma. In the Vedic times the outward ritual sacrifice and at a later period all the religious forms and notions that clustered visibly around the rites and imagery of temple worship, constant festival and ceremony and daily act of outward devotion were intended to serve this type or this soul-stage. Many of these things may seem to the developed mind to belong to an ignorant or half awakened religionism; but they have their concealed truth and their psychic value and are indispensable in this stage for the development and difficult awakening of the soul shrouded in the ignorance of material Nature.

The middle stage, the second type starts from these things, but gets behind them; it is capable of understanding more clearly and consciently the psychic truths, the conceptions of the intelligence, the aesthetic indications, the ethical values and all the other mediating directions which Indian religion took care to place behind its symbols. These intermediate truths vivify the outward forms of the system and those who can grasp them can go through these mental indices towards things that are beyond the mind and approach the profounder truths of the spirit. For at this stage there is already something awake that can go inward to a more deeply psycho-religious experience. Already the mind, heart and will have some strength to grapple with the difficulties of the relations between the spirit and life, some urge to satisfy more luminously or more inwardly the rational, aesthetic and ethical nature and lead them upward towards their own highest heights; one can begin to train mind and soul towards a spiritual consciousness and the opening of a spiritual existence. This ascending type of humanity claims for its use all that large and opulent middle region of philosophic, psycho-spiritual, ethical, aesthetic and emotional religious seeking which is the larger and more significant portion of the wealth of Indian culture. At this stage intervene the philosophical systems, the subtle illumining debates and inquiries of the thinkers; here are the nobler or more passionate reaches of devotion, here are held up the higher, ampler or austerer ideals of the Dharma; here break in the psychical suggestions and first definite urgings of the eternal and infinite which draw men by their appeal and promise towards the practice of Yoga.

But these things, great as they were, were not final or supreme: they were openings, steps of ascension towards the luminous grandeurs of spiritual truth and its practice was kept ready and its means of attainment provided for the third and greatest type of human being, the third loftiest stage of the spiritual evolution. The complete light of spiritual knowledge when it emerges from veil and compromise and goes beyond all symbols and middle significances, the absolute and universal divine love, the beauty of the All-beautiful, the noblest dharma of unity with all beings, universal compassion and benevolence calm and sweet in the perfect purity of the spirit, the upsurge of the psychical being into the spiritual unity or the spiritual ecstasy, these divinest things were the heritage of the human being ready for divinity and their way and call were the supreme significances of Indian religion and Yoga. He reached by them the fruits of his perfect spiritual evolution, an identity with the Self and Spirit, a dwelling in or with God, the divine law of his being, a spiritual universality, communion, transcendence.”60

‡ Indian religion did not remain content with the execution of its first two fundamental perceptions, for it had yet another perception which had to be considered before shaping for an individual the actual course of his inner development, his proper field of practical action, the right code of conduct and duty. This was Adhikara or the varying natural capacity of man.

The term ‘Adhikara’ has nothing to do with the sense of ‘right’ or of ‘proprietorship’ or of ‘possession’ in which it is commonly understood. When talking of the varying natural capacity of man (adhikara), one must take care to deal with the term ‘capacity’ in its more subjective and psychological sense rather than stopping short at its common superficial meaning. For example, it is not merely the capacity of the sense of hearing, or that of the sight, however faultless in its working, that can enable one to enter into the deeper sense of music or to go behind the outer form of art to its deeper intent, any more than mere command over vocabulary can enable one to enter into the heart of literature. It is evidently much more the cultivation and refinement of the subjective and psychological sense than the mere accuracy or sensitivity of the outer sense organs that can truly enable one to enter into and appreciate music, art or literature. Indian culture throughout had this deep perception that just as an apparently lifeless idol can express much more of its beauty and emotion to one with a cultivated aesthetic sense than to a brute, and even more so to one with an awakened deeper eye to whom it may even reveal the secret Divinity behind the form, similarly, the whole creation appears to us the way it does because of the given constitution and state of our consciousness. Sanatana Dharma looked upon each being as a portion of the Divine, and therefore, capable of regaining its original divinity. It is for the fulfilment of this fundamental perception that the whole intricate web of Sanatana Dharma was built.

In the discussion about the varying religious atmosphere and devices suited to the different levels of the evolving human soul, there is a point that needs to be rightly understood to avoid possible misunderstanding. It has been said that the whole mass of suggestive ceremony and effective ritual and strict outward rule and injunction etc. was provided to meet the need of the first type or level, that is, the crude, ill-formed, still outward, vitally and physically minded person, but that must not be taken to mean that the utility of all such ceremonies and rituals gradually loses its relevance as one ascends to the higher levels of consciousness and when, finally, one reaches a certain stage one can completely do away with all outer worship. It is only those who have no deeper understanding and experience of the subject that make such a sharp distinction between knowledge and works — where, in truth, no such disparity exists — and while trying to vindicate the supremacy of Jnanakanda over Karmakanda (ritualism), advocate a complete abstention from works. In the past also, such misconceptions have been responsible for much confusion and misunderstanding. The aim of the rich mass of rituals, ceremonies and symbols with which a cult equips itself is to appeal to the still outward, crude and physically minded consciousness and surround it with such indicative things that work upon the mind consciently and subconsciently to prepare it for an entry into the deeper significance of the symbol. But with the growth in consciousness, the symbols — ceasing to be mere dead or unintelligible representations — become more and more alive with that deeper truth which they are meant to symbolise. Therefore, with the development of consciousness, the usefulness of ritualism, ceremony, outer worship, etc. does not necessarily cease, on the contrary, they get their true significance. It is only in such a state that works are no more a bondage but become powerful means of expression of the joy of union with the Divine. Thus, primarily, works (or rituals) serve as means for the surface nature to ascend and establish contact with the Divine, and once that is attained, they become means of its expression and manifestation.

The whole discussion on the dynamic formulation of Indian religious culture summarises the three fundamental perceptions of this culture and the colossal effort it put into developing the necessary framework for the execution of those perceptions. But even after having devised such wide structure, Indian religion throughout held to a yet greater perception of the possibility of a direct approach to the spiritual reality free of gradations. For it, the inner spiritual call — the call of the Divine — was the one thing of paramount importance. The whole ingenious framework was meant only to serve as means for creating the most conducive atmosphere for the reception of that inner call and, once received, to provide the necessary help and support to move towards its fulfilment. That is why in his commentary on the Gita, Sri Aurobindo writes, “Previous effort and preparation, the purity and the holiness of the Brahmin, the enlightened strength of the king-sage great in works and knowledge have their value, because they make it easier for the imperfect human creature to arrive at this wide vision and self-surrender; but even without this preparation all who take refuge in the divine Lover of man, the Vaishya once preoccupied with the narrowness of wealth-getting and the labour of production, the Shudra hampered by a thousand hard restrictions, woman shut in and stunted in her growth by the narrow circle society has drawn around her self-expansion, those too, pāpa-yonayaḥ, on whom their past Karma has imposed even the very worst of births, the outcaste, the Pariah, the Chandala, find at once the gates of God opening before them. In the spiritual life all the external distinctions of which men make so much because they appeal with an oppressive force to the outward mind, cease before the equality of the divine Light and the wide omnipotence of an impartial Power.” (CWSA 19, 335).

It is this significant perception of Indian religion that Sri Aurobindo proceeds to clarify. ‡

(vii) The Provision for or the Admittance of the Possibility of a Direct Approach to the Spiritual Reality Free of the Gradations

The above gradations or “...distinctions are lines that can always be overpassed in the infinite complexity of man’s nature and there was no sharp and unbridgeable division, only a gradation, since the actuality or potentiality of the three powers coexist in all men. Both the middle and the highest significances were near and present and pervaded the whole system, and the approaches to the highest status were not absolutely denied to any man, in spite of certain prohibitions: but these prohibitions broke down in practice or left a way of escape to the man who felt the call; the call itself was a sign of election. He had only to find the way and the guide. But even in the direct approach the principle of adhikāra, differing capacity and varying nature, svabhāva, was recognised in subtle ways, which it would be beyond my present purpose to enumerate. One may note as an example the significant Indian idea of the iṣṭa-devatā, the special name, form, idea of the Divinity which each man may choose for worship and communion and follow after according to the attraction in his nature and his capacity of spiritual intelligence. And each of the forms has its outer initial associations and suggestions for the worshipper, its appeal to the intelligence, psychical, aesthetic, emotional power in the nature and its highest spiritual significance which leads through some one truth of the Godhead into the essence of spirituality. One may note too that in the practice of Yoga the disciple has to be led through his nature and according to his capacity and the spiritual teacher and guide is expected to perceive and take account of the necessary gradations and the individual need and power in his giving of help and guidance. Many things may be objected to in the actual working of this large and flexible system and I shall take some note of them when I have to deal with the weak points or the pejorative side of the culture against which the hostile critic directs with a misleading exaggeration his missiles. But the principle of it and the main lines of the application embody a remarkable wisdom, knowledge and careful observation of human nature and an assured insight into the things of the spirit which none can question who has considered deeply and flexibly these difficult matters or had any close experience of the obstacles and potentialities of our nature in its approach to the concealed spiritual reality.”61

[13]	The Tantric distinction is between the animal man, the hero man and the divine man, paśu, vīra, deva. Or we may grade the difference according to the three gunas, – first, the tamasic or rajaso-tamasic man ignorant, inert or moved only in a little light by small motive forces, the rajasic or sattwo-rajasic man struggling with an awakened mind and will towards self-development or self-affirmation, and the sattwic man open in mind and heart and will to the Light, standing at the top of the scale and ready to transcend it.

A. The Rishi and the Shastra – the Linking and the Culture of the Thinking Being of Man

“The most delicate and difficult part of this task of human development is concerned with the thinking being of man, his mind of reason and knowledge. No ancient culture of which we have knowledge, not even the Greek, attached more importance to it or spent more effort on its cultivation. The business of the ancient Rishi was not only to know God, but to know the world and life and to reduce it by knowledge to a thing well understood and mastered with which the reason and will of man could deal on assured lines and on a safe basis of wise method and order. The ripe result of this effort was the Shastra. When we speak of the Shastra nowadays, we mean too often only the religio-social system of injunctions of the middle age made sacrosanct by their mythical attribution to Manu, Parashara and other Vedic sages. But in older India Shastra meant any systematised teaching and science; each department of life, each line of activity, each subject of knowledge had its science or Shastra. The attempt was to reduce each to a theoretical and practical order founded on detailed observation, just generalisation, full experience, intuitive, logical and experimental analysis and synthesis, in order to enable man to know always with a just fruitfulness for life and to act with the security of right knowledge. The smallest and the greatest things were examined with equal care and attention and each provided with its art and science. The name was given even to the highest spiritual knowledge whenever it was stated not in a mass of intuitive experience and revelatory knowledge as in the Upanishads, but for intellectual comprehension in system and order, – and in that sense the Gita is able to call its profound spiritual teaching the most secret science, guhyatamaṁ śāstram. This high scientific and philosophical spirit was carried by the ancient Indian culture into all its activities. No Indian religion is complete without its outward form of preparatory practice, its supporting philosophy and its Yoga or system of inward practice or art of spiritual living: most even of what seems irrational in it to a first glance, has its philosophical turn and significance. It is this complete understanding and philosophical character which has given religion in India its durable security and immense vitality and enabled it to resist the acid dissolvent power of modern sceptical inquiry; whatever is ill-founded in experience and reason, that power can dissolve, but not the heart and mind of these great teachings. But what we have more especially to observe is that while Indian culture made a distinction between the lower and the higher learning, the knowledge of things and the knowledge of self, it did not put a gulf between them like some religions, but considered the knowledge of the world and things as a preparatory and a leading up to the knowledge of Self and God. All Shastra was put under the sanction of the names of the Rishis, who were in the beginning the teachers not only of spiritual truth and philosophy, – and we may note that all Indian philosophy, even the logic of Nyaya and the atomic theory of the Vaisheshikas, has for its highest crowning note and eventual object spiritual knowledge and liberation, – but of the arts, the social, political and military, the physical and psychic sciences, and every instructor was in his degree respected as a guru or ācārya, a guide or preceptor of the human spirit. All knowledge was woven into one and led up by degrees to the one highest knowledge.”62

‡ After a detailed discussion on the dynamic formulation of Indian religious culture, Sri Aurobindo gives an overview of how it brought about the general culture and refinement of ordinary human life and its powers and linked it successfully to religious development and spiritual evolution. This has been the secret of all the great achievements of this culture. This overview also carries in itself the necessary hints for proper dealing with our own life and its forces. One can see how the present misguided attempts at regulating these forces through a narrow utilitarian approach have given rise to serious problems for the whole of humanity.

Our fundamental problem when we deal with life is that we do not really understand life and its powers, their nature, their action and their interrelationship. Consequently, all our efforts at regulation and cultivation of these prove to be altogether ineffective or, if applied forcibly, may even frustrate their natural development, and engender serious consequences. This culture could so triumphantly link human nature to its lofty ideas due, primarily, to a deep understanding of its construction — for the average human nature is much the same everywhere. Our present humanity, devoid of any such deep understanding, vainly dreams of regulating life by the enactment of ever more elaborate laws and rules and by the construction of novel institutions and increasingly intricate administrative machinery which, in effect — despite the appearances to the contrary — hardly amounts to any real regulation. It is vain to expect that people with a gross utilitarian outlook, devoid of any sense of those deeper forces that govern life, and whose own life is driven by blind egoistic impulses, can frame regulatory laws that are truly effective and applicable to life.

Life, a mobile, progressive and evolving force, differs from the mechanical order of the physical universe with which the reason has been able to deal victoriously only because it is mechanical and runs almost immutably in the groove of fixed cosmic habits. Therefore, in the end, life defeats all the calculations of the idealising reason, undoes its elaborate systems or accepts only the little that it can assimilate to its own need and purpose. It is only in a deeper light of the soul that life can truly and satisfactorily be regulated, because only so can it freely develop and express that deeper truth which it carries within itself. Therefore, Indian culture throughout acted on the firm intuition that the regulation and development of life should always be administered by the supreme authority of the Rishi, who being stationed in the Truth-consciousness and free from the distorting influence of the lower parts of the being, possessed a genuine understanding of life and its powers. It is such Rishis who were called upon to provide society with proper rules, regulations and guiding principles which, even when binding on all, were not of an absolute nature and in practical execution were very much responsive to the formula of time, place and person.

The general culture of life concerns itself first with the development of the thinking being, the reflective part of man which observes life and the world and tries to discover the secret laws of things and their workings and build upon them various generalisations, disciplines, sciences, systems, etc. But the peculiarity of the Indian mind lay in its fundamental perception of the spirit as being the true origin and base of everything and, the higher knowledge, the knowledge of the self (para vidya) to be the basis of the lower, the knowledge of the world and things (apara vidya), therefore only by going deeper into the soul and looking at the world and things in that light can the thinking being of man truly enter into their secrets. Not content with regarding its highest spiritual experience as a distant ideal that did not impact life or connect with it, the authority of the Rishi and the Shastra served as a powerful link, so that ordinary human life could be uplifted by the deeper truths of the spirit, and thus spirituality may find a secure basis for its manifestation. The ancient Indian Rishi not only possessed a deep knowledge of the spirit’s secrets but had a detailed understanding of all the various aspects of the outer world and life and their practical working as well which brought about detailed Shastras of each department of life, each line of activity and each subject of knowledge that provided the thinking being of man a secure ground for the proper dealing with life. It is this sounding of the highest spiritual heights and the minutest outer details that has given Indian religion that unshakable durability that no acid of sceptical enquiry can dissolve. Explaining in a letter how their own work moved on a secure ground of rigorous testing, Sri Aurobindo wrote, “...we do not found ourselves on faith alone but on a great ground of knowledge which we have been developing and testing all our lives. I think I can say that I have been testing day and night for years upon years more scrupulously than any scientist his theory or his method on the physical plane. That is why I am not alarmed by the aspect of the world around me…” (CWSA 35, 322)

One may wonder if the thinking power of the common people in ancient India was so undeveloped as to turn to the Rishis and the Shastras for guidance even regarding the most ordinary or trivial activities of life. To be able to get a perspective on this, one must not lose sight of this deep truth that the profundities, the potent secrets, the great, hidden, all-determining laws behind the surface of life are exceedingly difficult for us to truly understand. Even for a physically minded person with necessary formal education and background, it should not be difficult to admit to the fact that rather than remaining content at the surface appearances of things it is an ever deeper inquiry by the physical science into the laws of matter that has enabled man to enter the greater secrets of matter and acquire greater control over physical nature. The more one explores matter, the more powerful the control one gets over its outer working. Thus, we understand that it is those more subtle laws and workings of physical nature, unintelligible to the outer senses, that sustain all the outer working. But it is difficult for a sense-bound mentality to perceive that the material world itself has no independent existence and that it is the Soul, the Spirit that is the true basis of this material world as well as that of all the other higher worlds. Therefore, without having some sense of the nature of these worlds one cannot truly know the nature and working of even this physical world. The ancient Indian Rishis not only had a deep understanding of the entire hierarchy of these worlds and their respective manifestations, but even more, the fundamental perception of the true source and cause of all these, — the Will of the Divine Mother. That is why, according to Sri Aurobindo, the business of the ancient Rishi was not only to know God, but to know the world and life and to reduce it by knowledge to a thing well understood and mastered with which the reason and will of man could deal on assured lines and on a safe basis of wise method and order. Considering the example of Sri Aurobindo himself, one can see how from the deepest and the most profound truths of spirituality to all the other possible concerns of individual and collective human existence — life, thought and action — there hardly remains any aspect or subject the truth of which has not been revealed or a conclusive perspective has not been provided by him. It seems, however, that mankind has a long way to go yet, before it can truly benefit by his words. Above all, by the founding of an Ashram in Pondicherry on a purely spiritual basis, he has presented a living example of how life and its concerns can be handled successfully and its issues dealt with perfectly in a community by the sole power of spirituality without taking recourse to a great number of external rules and regulations.

After having provided the thinking being of man with broad outlines and shastras to move on assured lines, the subsequent task of the Rishis was to enable each one to move according to those shastras, and this they effected by the culture and ordering of the ethical nature of man.‡

B. The Dharma – the Culture and the Ordering of the Ethical Nature

“The whole right practice of life founded on this knowledge was in the view of Indian culture a Dharma, a living according to a just understanding and right view of self-culture, of the knowledge of things and life and of action in that knowledge. Thus each man and class and kind and species and each activity of soul, mind, life, body has its dharma. But the largest or at least most vitally important part of the Dharma was held to be the culture and ordering of the ethical nature of man. The ethical aspect of life, contrary to the amazingly ignorant observation of a certain type of critics, attracted a quite enormous amount of attention, occupied the greater part of Indian thought and writing not devoted to the things of pure knowledge and of the spirit and was so far pushed that there is no ethical formation or ideal which does not reach in it its highest conception and a certain divine absolutism of ideal practice. Indian thought took for granted, – though there are some remarkable speculations to the contrary, – the ethical nature of man and the ethical law of the world. It considered that man was justified in satisfying his desires, since that is necessary for the satisfaction and expansion of life, but not in obeying the dictates of desire as the law of his being; for in all things there is a greater law, each has not only its side of interest and desire, but its dharma or rule of right practice, satisfaction, expansion, regulation. The Dharma, then, fixed by the wise in the Shastra is the right thing to observe, the true rule of action. First in the web of Dharma comes the social law; for man’s life is only initially for his vital, personal, individual self, but much more imperatively for the community, though most imperatively of all for the greatest Self one in himself and in all beings, for God, for the Spirit. Therefore first the individual must subordinate himself to the communal self, though by no means bound altogether to efface himself in it as the extremists of the communal idea imagine. He must live according to the law of his nature harmonised with the law of his social type and class, for the nation and in a higher reach of his being – this was greatly stressed by the Buddhists – for humanity. Thus living and acting he could learn to transcend the social scale of the Dharma, practise without injuring the basis of life the ideal scale and finally grow into the liberty of the spirit, when rule and duty were not binding because he would then move and act in a highest free and immortal dharma of the divine nature. All these aspects of the Dharma were closely linked up together in a progressive unity. Thus, for an example, each of the four orders had its own social function and ethics, but also an ideal rule for the growth of the pure ethical being, and every man by observing his dharma and turning his action Godwards could grow out of it into the spiritual freedom. But behind all dharma and ethics was put, not only as a safeguard but as a light, a religious sanction, a reminder of the continuity of life and of man’s long pilgrimage through many births, a reminder of the Gods and planes beyond and of the Divine, and above it all the vision of a last stage of perfect comprehension and unity and of divine transcendence.”63

‡ To effectively link the life of the human being and its powers with the highest spiritual ideal, Indian culture, on the one hand, provided the authority of the Rishi and the shastra to instruct and guide each and every detail of life, and on the other, strove to cultivate the ethical nature of man by laying down relative Dharmas so as to make him capable of following the instructions or the guidance of the Rishi and the Shastra. To facilitate the general culture and development of the ethical being of man, the entire culture was surrounded by countless shining examples of great personalities in whom the moral virtues and ideals were carried to their ultimate. The Dharmas, being relative, would prescribe the right code of conduct in accordance with the state and stage of the inner and outer development of an individual and society which would evolve until, finally, they reached a stage where they became capable of living in the freedom of the soul. Thus, the whole system was geared towards transmuting the thinking, ethical, aesthetic, hedonistic, external parts of the being into effective instruments of the soul for its self-expression – not by suppression, but by proper cultivation under the yoke of Dharma. ‡

C. All the Arts Under the Sanction of the Rishi – the Linking and Culture of Aesthetic and the Hedonistic Being of Man

“The system of Indian ethics liberalised by the catholicity of the ancient mind did not ban or violently discourage the aesthetic or even the hedonistic being of man in spite of a growing ascetic tendency and a certain high austerity of the summits. The aesthetic satisfactions of all kinds and all grades were an important part of the culture. Poetry, the drama, song, dance, music, the greater and lesser arts were placed under the sanction of the Rishis and were made instruments of the spirit’s culture. A just theory held them to be initially the means of a pure aesthetic satisfaction and each was founded on its own basic rule and law, but on that basis and with a perfect fidelity to it still raised up to minister to the intellectual, ethical and religious development of the being. It is notable that the two vast Indian epics have been considered as much as Dharma-shastras as great historico-mythic epic narratives, itihāsas. They are, that is to say, noble, vivid and puissant pictures of life, but they utter and breathe throughout their course the law and ideal of a great and high ethical and religious spirit in life and aim in their highest intention at the idea of the Divine and the way of the mounting soul in the action of the world. Indian painting, sculpture and architecture did not refuse service to the aesthetic satisfaction and interpretation of the social, civic and individual life of the human being; these things, as all evidences show, played a great part in their motives of creation, but still their highest work was reserved for the greatest spiritual side of the culture, and throughout we see them seized and suffused with the brooding stress of the Indian mind on the soul, the Godhead, the spiritual, the Infinite. And we have to note too that the aesthetic and hedonistic being was made not only an aid to religion and spirituality and liberally used for that purpose, but even one of the main gates of man’s approach to the Spirit. The Vaishnava religion especially is a religion of love and beauty and of the satisfaction of the whole delight-soul of man in God and even the desires and images of the sensuous life were turned by its vision into figures of a divine soul-experience. Few religions have gone so far as this immense catholicity or carried the whole nature so high in its large, puissant and many-sided approach to the spiritual and the infinite.”64

VI. The Record of the Great Achievements of India in Every Field

“To say that there has been no great or vivid activity of life in India, that she has had no great personalities with the mythical exception of Buddha and the other pale exception of Asoka, that she has never shown any will-power and never done any great thing, is so contrary to all the facts of history that only a devil’s advocate in search of a case could advance it at all or put it with that crude vehemence. India has lived and lived greatly, whatever judgment one may pass on her ideas and institutions. What is meant after all by life and when is it that we most fully and greatly live? Life is surely nothing but the creation and active self-expression of man’s spirit, powers, capacities, his will to be and think and create and love and do and achieve. When that is wanting or, since it cannot be absolutely wanting, depressed, held under, discouraged or inert, whether by internal or external causes, then we may say that there is a lack of life. ... The ancient and mediaeval life of India was not wanting in any of the things that make up the vivid interesting activity of human existence. On the contrary, it was extraordinarily full of colour and interest. ... India has been as much a home of serious and solid realities, of a firm grappling with the problems of thought and life, of measured and wise organisation and great action as any other considerable centre of civilisation. ... The colour and magnificence have been its aesthetic side; she has had great dreams and high and splendid imaginations, for that too is wanted for the completeness of our living; but also deep philosophical and religious thinking, a wide and searching criticism of life, a great political and social order, a strong ethical tone and a persistent vigour of individual and communal living. That is a combination which means life in all its fullness, though deficient, it may be, except in extraordinary cases, in the more violent egoistic perversities and exaggerations which some minds seem to take for a proof of the highest vigour of existence.

In what field indeed has not India attempted, achieved, created, and in all on a large scale and yet with much attention to completeness of detail? Of her spiritual and philosophic achievement there can be no real question. They stand there as the Himalayas stand upon the earth in the phrase of Kalidasa, pṛthivyā iva mānadaṇḍaḥ, ‘as if earth’s measuring rod,’ mediating still between earth and heaven, measuring the finite, casting their plummet far into the infinite, plunging their extremities into the upper and lower seas of the superconscient and the subliminal, the spiritual and the natural being. But if her philosophies, her religious disciplines, her long list of great spiritual personalities, thinkers, founders, saints are her greatest glory, as was natural to her temperament and governing idea, they are by no means her sole glories, nor are the others dwarfed by their eminence. It is now proved that in science she went farther than any country before the modern era, and even Europe owes the beginning of her physical science to India as much as to Greece, although not directly but through the medium of the Arabs. And, even if she had only gone as far, that would have been sufficient proof of a strong intellectual life in an ancient culture. Especially in mathematics, astronomy and chemistry, the chief elements of ancient science, she discovered and formulated much and well and anticipated by force of reasoning or experiment some of the scientific ideas and discoveries which Europe first arrived at much later, but was able to base more firmly by her new and completer method. She was well-equipped in surgery and her system of medicine survives to this day and has still its value, though it declined intermediately in knowledge and is only now recovering its vitality.

In literature, in the life of the mind, she lived and built greatly. Not only has she the Vedas, Upanishads and Gita, not to speak of less supreme but still powerful or beautiful work in that field, unequalled monuments of religious and philosophic poetry, a kind in which Europe has never been able to do anything much of any great value, but that vast national structure, the Mahabharata, gathering into its cycle the poetic literature and expressing so completely the life of a long formative age, that it is said of it in a popular saying which has the justice if also the exaggeration of a too apt epigram, ‘What is not in this Bharata, is not in Bharatavarsha (India),’ and the Ramayana, the greatest and most remarkable poem of its kind, that most sublime and beautiful epic of ethical idealism and a heroic semi-divine human life, and the marvellous richness, fullness and colour of the poetry and romance of highly cultured thought, sensuous enjoyment, imagination, action and adventure which makes up the romantic literature of her classical epoch. Nor did this long continuous vigour of creation cease with the loss of vitality by the Sanskrit tongue, but was paralleled and carried on in a mass of great or of beautiful work in her other languages, in Pali first and Prakrit, much unfortunately lost,[14] and Tamil, afterwards in Hindi, Bengali, Marathi and other tongues. The long tradition of her architecture, sculpture and painting speaks for itself, even in what survives after all the ruin of stormy centuries: whatever judgment may be formed of it by the narrower school of Western aesthetics, – and at least its fineness of execution and workmanship cannot be denied, nor the power with which it renders the Indian mind, – it testifies at least to a continuous creative activity. And creation is proof of life and great creation of greatness of life.

But these things are, it may be said, the things of the mind, and the intellect, imagination and aesthetic mind of India may have been creatively active, but yet her outward life depressed, dull, poor, gloomy with the hues of asceticism, void of willpower and personality, ineffective, null. That would be a hard proposition to swallow; for literature, art and science do not flourish in a void of life. But here too what are the facts? India has not only had the long roll of her great saints, sages, thinkers, religious founders, poets, creators, scientists, scholars, legists; she has had her great rulers, administrators, soldiers, conquerors, heroes, men with the strong active will, the mind that plans and the seeing force that builds. She has warred and ruled, traded and colonised and spread her civilisation, built polities and organised communities and societies, done all that makes the outward activity of great peoples. A nation tends to throw out its most vivid types in that line of action which is most congenial to its temperament and expressive of its leading idea, and it is the great saints and religious personalities that stand at the head in India and present the most striking and continuous roll-call of greatness, just as Rome lived most in her warriors and statesmen and rulers. The Rishi in ancient India was the outstanding figure with the hero just behind, while in later times the most striking feature is the long uninterrupted chain from Buddha and Mahavira to Ramanuja, Chaitanya, Nanak, Ramdas and Tukaram and beyond them to Ramakrishna and Vivekananda and Dayananda. But there have been also the remarkable achievements of statesmen and rulers, from the first dawn of ascertainable history which comes in with the striking figures of Chandragupta, Chanakya, Asoka, the Gupta emperors and goes down through the multitude of famous Hindu and Mahomedan figures of the middle age to quite modern times. In ancient India there was the life of republics, oligarchies, democracies, small kingdoms of which no detail of history now survives, afterwards the long effort at empire-building, the colonisation of Ceylon and the Archipelago, the vivid struggles that attended the rise and decline of the Pathan and Mogul dynasties, the Hindu struggle for survival in the south, the wonderful record of Rajput heroism and the great upheaval of national life in Maharashtra penetrating to the lowest strata of society, the remarkable episode of the Sikh Khalsa. An adequate picture of that outward life still remains to be given; once given it would be the end of many fictions. All this mass of action was not accomplished by men without mind and will and vital force, by pale shadows of humanity in whom the vigorous manhood had been crushed out under the burden of a gloomy and all-effacing asceticism, nor does it look like the sign of a metaphysically minded people of dreamers averse to life and action. It was not men of straw or lifeless and will-less dummies or thin-blooded dreamers who thus acted, planned, conquered, built great systems of administration, founded kingdoms and empires, figured as great patrons of poetry and art and architecture or, later, resisted heroically imperial power and fought for the freedom of clan or people. Nor was it a nation devoid of life which maintained its existence and culture and still lived on and broke out constantly into new revivals under the ever increasing stress of continuously adverse circumstances. The modern Indian revival, religious, cultural, political, called now sometimes a renaissance, which so troubles and grieves the minds of her critics, is only a repetition under altered circumstances, in an adapted form, in a greater though as yet less vivid mass of movement, of a phenomenon which has constantly repeated itself throughout a millennium of Indian history.

And it must be remembered that by virtue of its culture and its system the whole nation shared in the common life. In all countries in the past the mass has indeed lived with a less active and vivid force than the few, – sometimes with the mere elements of life, not with even any beginning of finished richness, – nor has modern civilisation yet got rid of this disparity, though it has opened the advantages or at least the initial opportunities of a first-hand life and thought and knowledge to a greater number. But in ancient India, though the higher classes led and had the lion’s share of the force and wealth of life, the people too lived and until much later times intensely though on a lesser scale and with a more diffused and less concentrated force. Their religious life was more intense than that of any other country; they drank in with remarkable facility the thoughts of the philosophers and the influence of the saints; they heard and followed Buddha and the many who came after him; they were taught by the Sannyasins and sang the songs of the Bhaktas and Bauls and thus possessed some of the most delicate and beautiful poetical literature ever produced; they contributed many of the greatest names in our religion, and from the outcastes themselves came saints revered by the whole community. In ancient Hindu times they had their share of political life and power; they were the people, the viśaḥ of the Veda, of whom the kings were the leaders and from them as well as from the sacred or princely families were born the Rishis; they held their villages as little self-administered republics; in the time of the great kingdoms and empires they sat in the municipalities and urban councils and the bulk of the typical royal Council described in the books of political science was composed of commoners, Vaishyas, and not of Brahmin Pundits and Kshatriya nobles; for a long time they could impose their will on their kings, without the need of a long struggle, by a single demonstration of their displeasure. So long as Hindu kingdoms existed, something of all this survived, and even the entrance into India of central Asian forms of absolutist despotism, never an indigenous Indian growth, left some remnant of the old edifice still in being. The people had their share too in art and poetry, their means by which the essence of Indian culture was disseminated through the mass, a system of elementary education in addition to the great universities of ancient times, a type of popular dramatic representation which was in some parts of the country alive even yesterday; they gave India her artists and architects and many of the famous poets in the popular tongues; they preserved by the force of their long past culture an innate aesthetic sense and faculty of which the work of Indian craftsmen remained a constant and striking evidence until it was destroyed or degraded by the vulgarisation and loss of aesthetic sense and beauty which has been one of the results of modern civilisation. Nor was the life of India ascetic, gloomy or sad, as the too logical mind of the critic would have it be. The outward form is more quiet than in other countries, there is a certain gravity and reserve before strangers which deceives the foreign observer, and in recent times asceticism and poverty and an increase of puritanic tendency had their effect, but the life portrayed in the literature of the country is glad and vivid, and even now despite certain varieties of temperament and many forces making for depression laughter, humour, an unobtrusive elasticity and equanimity in the vicissitudes of life are very marked features of the Indian character.

The whole theory of a want of life and will and activity in the Indian people as a result of their culture is then a myth.”67

[14]	E.g. the once famous work in Paisachi of which the Kathāsaritsāgara is an inferior version.

References:

1. 	CWSA 20: 120

2.	CWSA 20: 214-15	3.	CWSA 20: 231-32	4.	CWSA 20: 56-57

5.	CWSA 20: 34-35

6.	CWSA 20: 169-70	7.	CWSA 20: 176-77	8.	CWSA 20: 98

9.	CWSA 20: 118

10.	CWSA 20: 120-21	11.	CWSA 20: 122-23	12.	CWSA 20: 119-20	13.	CWSA 20: 123-25	14.	CWSA 20: 125-28	15.	CWSA 20: 131-32	16.	CWSA 20: 133-34	17.	CWSA 20: 134-35	18.	CWSA 20: 135-36	19.	CWSA 20: 136-37	20.	CWSA 20: 147-48	21.	CWSA 20: 149-50	22.	CWSA 20: 150

23.	CWSA 20: 151-53	24.	CWSA 20: 153

25.	CWSA 20: 153-54

26.	CWSA 20: 154-56	27.	CWSA 20: 156-58	28.	CWSA 20: 158-61	29.	CWSA 20: 161-62	30.	CWSA 20: 162-64	31.	CWSA 20: 164-66	32.	CWSA 20: 167-68	33.	CWSA 20: 168

34.	CWSA 20: 168-70	35.	CWSA 20: 170

36.	CWSA 20: 170-73

37.	CWSA 20: 173-74	38.	CWSA 20: 174-76	39.	CWSA 20: 178

40.	CWSA 20: 178-81	41.	CWSA 20: 181-82	42 .	CWSA 20: 193-95

43.	CWSA 20: 183-86	44.	CWSA 20: 186-88	45.	CWSA 20: 188-92	46.	CWSA 20: 192-93	47.	CWSA 20: 196-98	48.	CWSA 24: 747

49.	CWSA 20: 198-205	50.	CWSA 20: 205-08	51.	CWSA 20: 208-11	52.	CWSA 20: 211-13	53.	CWSA 20: 216

54.	CWSA 20: 216

55.	CWSA 20: 216-17	56.	CWSA 20: 217

57.	CWSA 20: 218

58.	CWSA 20: 218-20	59.	CWSA 20: 220-21	60.	CWSA 20: 221-23	61.	CWSA 20: 223-24	62.	CWSA 20: 224-25	63.	CWSA 20: 225-27	64.	CWSA 20: 227-28	65.	CWSA 20: 228-29	66.	CWSA 20: 229-30	67.	CWSA 20: 242-49

I. The Spirit of Ancient India

“The spirit of ancient India was aristocratic; its thought & life moulded in the cast of a high & proud nobility, an extreme & lofty strenuousness. The very best in thought, the very best in action, the very best in character, the very best in literature & art, the very best in religion and all the world well lost if only this very best might be attained, such was the spirit of ancient India. The Brahmin who devoted himself to poverty & crushed down every desire in the wholehearted pursuit of knowledge & religious self-discipline; the Kshatriya who, hurling his life joyously into the shock of chivalrous battle, held life, wife, children, possessions, ease, happiness as mere dust in the balance compared with honour & the Kshatriya dharma, the preservation of self-respect, the protection of the weak, the noble fulfilment of princely duty; the Vaishya, who toiling all his life to amass riches, poured them out as soon as amassed in self-forgetting philanthropy holding himself the mere steward & not the possessor of his wealth; the Shudra who gave himself up loyally to humble service, faithfully devoting his life to his dharma, however low, in preference to self-advancement & ambition; these were the social ideals of the age.

The imagination of the Indian tended as has been well said to the grand & enormous in thought and morals. The great formative images of legend & literature to the likeness with which his childhood was encouraged to develop & which his manhood most cherished were of an extreme & lofty type. He saw Harischundra give up all that life held precious & dear rather than that his lips should utter a lie or his plighted word be broken. He saw Prahlada buried under mountains, whelmed in the seas, tortured by the poison of a thousand venomous serpents, yet calmly true to his faith. He saw Buddha give up his royal state, wealth, luxury, wife, child & parents so that mankind might be saved. He saw Shivi hew the flesh from his own limbs to save one small dove from the pursuing falcon; Karna tear his own body with a smile for the joy of making a gift; Duryodhan refuse to yield one inch of earth without noble resistance & warlike struggle. He saw Sita face exile, hardship, privation & danger in the eagerness of wifely love & duty, Savitri rescue by her devotion her husband back from the visible grip of death. These were the classical Indian types. These were the ideals into the mould of which the minds of men & women were trained to grow. The sense-conquering thought of the philosopher, the magnificent achievements of the hero, the stupendous renunciations of the Sannyasin, [the] unbounded liberality of the man of wealth, everything was exaggeration, extreme, filled with an epic inspiration, a world-defying enthusiasm.”1

“The ancient Indian culture attached quite as much value to the soundness, growth and strength of the mind, life and body as the old Hellenic or the modern scientific thought, although for a different end and a greater motive. Therefore to everything that serves and belongs to the healthy fullness of these things, it gave free play, to the activity of the reason, to science and philosophy, to the satisfaction of the aesthetic being and to all the many arts great or small, to the health and strength of the body, to the physical and economical well-being, ease, opulence of the race, – there was never a national ideal of poverty in India as some would have us believe, nor was bareness or squalor the essential setting of her spirituality, – and to its general military, political and social strength and efficiency. Their aim was high, but firm and wide too was the base they sought to establish and great the care bestowed on these first instruments.”2

Thus one can safely say that, “…Indian civilisation has been the form and expression of a culture as great as any of the historic civilisations of mankind, great in religion, great in philosophy, great in science, great in thought of many kinds, great in literature, art and poetry, great in the organisation of society and politics, great in craft and trade and commerce. There have been dark spots, positive imperfections, heavy shortcomings; what civilisation has been perfect, which has not had its deep stains and cruel abysses? There have been considerable lacunae, many blind alleys, much uncultured or ill-cultured ground: what civilisation has been without its unfilled parts, its negative aspects? But our ancient civilisation can survive the severest comparisons of either ancient or mediaeval times. More high-reaching, subtle, many-sided, curious and profound than the Greek, more noble and humane than the Roman, more large and spiritual than the old Egyptian, more vast and original than any other Asiatic civilisation, more intellectual than the European prior to the eighteenth century, possessing all that these had and more, it was the most powerful, self-possessed, stimulating and wide in influence of all past human cultures.”3

‡ If we try to delve deeper into the heart of this splendid account of the aristocratic spirit of Indian culture, we may be sure to arrive at a deep perception — although there may be many others — that such a lofty atmosphere inspiring one to attain the very best in thought, life and action could have been possible only by virtue of the great founders of this culture who, being themselves firmly established in the depths of their heart rather than living on the surface, raised the collectivity also to enable it to live more and more from the depths of its heart. It is the heart alone that can give the necessary zeal, intensity and energy indispensable for the realisation of the ideal. It is this intensity that can bring about a complete self-forgetfulness, a willing self-sacrifice for the ideal or for one’s beloved and devour the ego and break the limitations of its petty and narrow mould for the full and wide reception of that which it seeks. This has been the secret of all the great achievements on earth. By outer enforcement of laws and rules, or even some kind of moral disciplining, devoid of any deeper insight, one can at best arrive at a system where people get the utmost chance of fulfilling their ordinary desires within a limited harmonious framework, but which can never be the basis which alone can bring about those superlative achievements such as we find in Indian culture. Those who have some deeper sense of the functioning of things know how difficult it is even for an organisation of persons with a spiritual motive or some higher ideal and, therefore, moved and organised much more by a deeper intuition than any outer regimentation, to continually keep to its original spirit and vigour. To have successfully moulded the collective life to live more from the depths of their hearts than in their outer surface selves and further to have persisted in that noble spirit for centuries, as the record of the achievements of this culture amply bears out, is a sure indicator of the superhuman capacity of this culture. We must realise, once for all, that it is vain to seek any fundamental change or advancement in our individual or collective existence by merely changing or restructuring the outer machinery — politics, administration, industry, education, technology, or any other institution — as is evident enough from the complete failure of all such attempts made now or in the recent past. The power of self-giving and consecration alone can bring about this fundamental change and regeneration and will itself supply all the necessary guidance, schemes or policies etc. The following heartfelt, illuminative words of Sri Aurobindo, written at the time of India’s subjection, bring this entire discussion into sharp focus. “If any reservation mars the completeness of our self-abandonment, if any bargaining abridges the fullness of our sacrifice, if any doubt mars the strength of our faith and enthusiasm, if any thought of self pollutes the sanctity of our love, then the Mother will not be satisfied and will continue to withhold her presence. We call her to come, but the call has not yet gone out of the bottom of our hearts. The Mother’s feet are on the threshold, but she waits to hear the true cry, the cry that rushes out from the heart, before she will enter. We are still hesitating between ourselves and the country; we would give one anna to the service of the Mother and keep fifteen for ourselves, our wives, our children, our property, our fame and reputation, our safety, our ease. The Mother asks all before she will give herself. Not until Surath Raja offered the blood of his veins did the Mother appear to him and ask him to choose his boon. Not until Shivaji was ready to offer his head at the feet of the Mother, did Bhavani in visible form stay his hand and give him the command to free his people.... The schemes by which we seek to prepare the nation, the scheme of industrial regeneration, the scheme of educational regeneration, the scheme of political regeneration through self-help are subordinate features of the deeper regeneration which the country must go through before it can be free. The Mother asks us for no schemes, no plans, no methods. She herself will provide the schemes, the plans, the methods better than any that we can devise. She asks us for our hearts, our lives, nothing less, nothing more.... Regeneration is literally rebirth and rebirth comes not by the intellect, not by the fullness of the purse, not by policy, not by change of machinery, but by the getting of a new heart by throwing away all that we were into the fire of sacrifice and being reborn in the Mother. Self-abandonment is the demand made upon us. She asks of us, ‘How many will live for me? How many will die for me?’ and awaits our answer.” (CWSA 7, 1032-33) ‡

A. Spirituality

“Spirituality is indeed the master-key of the Indian mind; the sense of the infinite is native to it. India saw from the beginning, – and, even in her ages of reason and her age of increasing ignorance, she never lost hold of the insight, – that life cannot be rightly seen in the sole light, cannot be perfectly lived in the sole power of its externalities. She was alive to the greatness of material laws and forces; she had a keen eye for the importance of the physical sciences; she knew how to organise the arts of ordinary life. But she saw that the physical does not get its full sense until it stands in right relation to the supra-physical; she saw that the complexity of the universe could not be explained in the present terms of man or seen by his superficial sight, that there were other powers behind, other powers within man himself of which he is normally unaware, that he is conscious only of a small part of himself, that the invisible always surrounds the visible, the suprasensible the sensible, even as infinity always surrounds the finite. She saw too that man has the power of exceeding himself, of becoming himself more entirely and profoundly than he is, – truths which have only recently begun to be seen in Europe and seem even now too great for its common intelligence. She saw the myriad gods beyond man, God beyond the gods, and beyond God his own ineffable eternity; she saw that there were ranges of life beyond our life, ranges of mind beyond our present mind and above these she saw the splendours of the spirit. Then with that calm audacity of her intuition which knew no fear or littleness and shrank from no act whether of spiritual or intellectual, ethical or vital courage, she declared that there was none of these things which man could not attain if he trained his will and knowledge; he could conquer these ranges of mind, become the spirit, become a god, become one with God, become the ineffable Brahman. And with the logical practicality and sense of science and organised method which distinguished her mentality, she set forth immediately to find out the way. Hence from long ages of this insight and practice there was ingrained in her her spirituality, her powerful psychic tendency, her great yearning to grapple with the infinite and possess it, her ineradicable religious sense, her idealism, her Yoga, the constant turn of her art and her philosophy.

But this was not and could not be her whole mentality, her entire spirit; spirituality itself does not flourish on earth in the void, even as our mountaintops do not rise like those of an enchantment of dream out of the clouds without a base. When we look at the past of India, what strikes us next is her stupendous vitality, her inexhaustible power of life and joy of life, her almost unimaginably prolific creativeness.”4

‡ Spirituality has been the keynote of Indian culture and the whole culture can be justly described as a powerful manifestation of that alone. Throughout it held to this fundamental perception that life and the world cannot be truly lived and viewed in the light of their externalities. Even physical science, after having probed deeper into the secrets of matter, has come to realise that the actual working of things is different from what it appears to the physical senses. Similarly, being aware of the whole hierarchy of worlds ranging from the superconscient to nescience, the ancient Indian Rishis could comprehensively perceive that it is only in the light of the higher levels that the lower ones can be rightly viewed. Therefore, for a more potent action on life or a mastery over life and physical nature a deeper and higher dynamism is necessary. ‡

B. Stupendous Vitality

“For three thousand years at least, – it is indeed much longer, – she has been creating abundantly and incessantly, lavishly, with an inexhaustible many-sidedness, republics and kingdoms and empires, philosophies and cosmogonies and sciences and creeds and arts and poems and all kinds of monuments, palaces and temples and public works, communities and societies and religious orders, laws and codes and rituals, physical sciences, psychic sciences, systems of Yoga, systems of politics and administration, arts spiritual, arts worldly, trades, industries, fine crafts, – the list is endless and in each item there is almost a plethora of activity. She creates and creates and is not satisfied and is not tired; she will not have an end of it, seems hardly to need a space for rest, a time for inertia and lying fallow. She expands too outside her borders; her ships cross the ocean and the fine superfluity of her wealth brims over to Judaea and Egypt and Rome; her colonies spread her arts and epics and creeds in the Archipelago; her traces are found in the sands of Mesopotamia; her religions conquer China and Japan and spread westward as far as Palestine and Alexandria, and the figures of the Upanishads and the sayings of the Buddhists are reechoed on the lips of Christ. Everywhere, as on her soil, so in her works there is the teeming of a superabundant energy of life. European critics complain that in her ancient architecture, sculpture and art there is no reticence, no holding back of riches, no blank spaces, that she labours to fill every rift with ore, occupy every inch with plenty. Well, but defect or no, that is the necessity of her superabundance of life, of the teeming of the infinite within her. She lavishes her riches because she must, as the Infinite fills every inch of space with the stirring of life and energy because it is the Infinite.”5

‡ We need to reflect on some points here with the right perception. The true spirit of Indian spirituality has always been the all-embracing integral Vedic spirit which recognises the just claim of all the parts of our being and tries to give them their due chance of fulfilment. The available record unquestionably establishes the prolific creativeness and the great achievements of Indian culture and we can see how spirituality in no way discourages the vital force in man, on the contrary, it greatly sublimates, purifies and intensifies its working. It is this that enabled the Indian culture to have such great achievements in the past which, today, seem almost impossible or superhuman for the ordinary human capacity. But the vital force, being the most dynamic and energetic part of our being, can truly be handled and regulated only by a spiritual force. Such is the despotic nature of the vital that certain schools of later spirituality consider it a great obstacle in any serious spiritual pursuit, an unruly and completely incorrigible part of our being. Therefore, their whole effort has been either to rigorously quell this life force or at least to starve it by depriving it of its fulfilment or satisfaction. Apart from a few, for whom it may be the only possible remedy, rarely does this coercion engender happy results for the majority, as it discourages the completeness of the divine expression and the joy that that expression brings with it.

Now the question is, what was the secret of that stupendous vitality of Indian culture, and what exactly do we think we may derive from this discussion that can be of relevance for us today? To begin with, there is a great difference between the spiritual and the purely material outlook of life which alters our whole normal view of things; even in pursuing the aims of human life, it gives them a different sense and direction. An upward transference of our centre of being brings about the consequent transformation of our whole existence and consciousness and along with it a resultant change in the whole spirit and motive of our action, even though the action may remain precisely the same in all its outward appearances. To one who has some sense of the deeper working of things, it should be evident how the nature of even the most ordinary work changes the moment one does it not merely to earn one’s livelihood, or under some compulsion or for the fulfilment of some superficial motive, but out of love or as an expression of some deep emotion or feeling of one’s heart, to whomsoever or whatsoever it may be directed. For a sense-bound mentality, which takes the outer instrumental being of man for his real self, the entire motive of its action is the gratification of the outer self. When done solely with such an outlook or motive, work loses for the most part, if not completely, its true utility, force and enthusiasm and increasingly takes on the nature of some kind of obligation, punishment or something that needs to be compensated by way of some kind of a pay off for the physical and vital being. It is hardly possible that the past achievements of Indian culture were accomplished by such people whose sole motive of work was to somehow ensure their material well-being. It is when the spirit of self-perfection or deeper fulfilment becomes the sole, or at least the main, driving force of action that any disutility of work disappears and it gets its true significance and justification. Any true creation can take place only when the joy of creation becomes the main motive force of action. Thus, a spiritual view regards life as a field for higher and higher ascension toward one’s true self, and work, in this view, is a powerful means of that ascension, and also, of the expression of that joy that this ascension and self-realisation bring with it. This is the secret of the stupendous vitality of this culture. In such a consciousness where work is a means of ascension and a source of joy, one could not help but be driven to constantly engage oneself in work, and that too in an intense way which leads to perfection in works. ‡

C. Strong Intellectuality

“But this supreme spirituality and this prolific abundance of the energy and joy of life and creation do not make all that the spirit of India has been in its past. It is not a confused splendour of tropical vegetation under heavens of a pure sapphire infinity. It is only to eyes unaccustomed to such wealth that there seems to be a confusion in this crowding of space with rich forms of life, a luxurious disorder of excess or a wanton lack of measure, clear balance and design. For the third power of the ancient Indian spirit was a strong intellectuality, at once austere and rich, robust and minute, powerful and delicate, massive in principle and curious in detail. Its chief impulse was that of order and arrangement, but an order founded upon a seeking for the inner law and truth of things and having in view always the possibility of conscientious practice. India has been preeminently the land of the Dharma and the Shastra. She searched for the inner truth and law of each human or cosmic activity, its dharma; that found, she laboured to cast into elaborate form and detailed law of arrangement its application in fact and rule of life. Her first period was luminous with the discovery of the Spirit; her second completed the discovery of the Dharma; her third elaborated into detail the first simpler formulation of the Shastra; but none was exclusive, the three elements are always present.

In this third period the curious elaboration of all life into a science and an art assumes extraordinary proportions. The mere mass of the intellectual production during the period from Asoka well into the Mahomedan epoch is something truly prodigious, as can be seen at once if one studies the account which recent scholarship gives of it, and we must remember that that scholarship as yet only deals with a fraction of what is still lying extant and what is extant is only a small percentage of what was once written and known. There is no historical parallel for such an intellectual labour and activity before the invention of printing and the facilities of modern science; yet all that mass of research and production and curiosity of detail was accomplished without these facilities and with no better record than the memory and for an aid the perishable palm-leaf. Nor was all this colossal literature confined to philosophy and theology, religion and Yoga, logic and rhetoric and grammar and linguistics, poetry and drama, medicine and astronomy and the sciences; it embraced all life, politics and society, all the arts from painting to dancing, all the sixty-four accomplishments, everything then known that could be useful to life or interesting to the mind, even, for instance, to such practical side minutiae as the breeding and training of horses and elephants, each of which had its Shastra and its art, its apparatus of technical terms, its copious literature. In each subject from the largest and most momentous to the smallest and most trivial there was expended the same all-embracing, opulent, minute and thorough intellectuality. On one side there is an insatiable curiosity, the desire of life to know itself in every detail, on the other a spirit of organisation and scrupulous order, the desire of the mind to tread through life with a harmonised knowledge and in the right rhythm and measure. Thus an ingrained and dominant spirituality, an inexhaustible vital creativeness and gust of life and, mediating between them, a powerful, penetrating and scrupulous intelligence combined of the rational, ethical and aesthetic mind each at a high intensity of action, created the harmony of the ancient Indian culture.

Indeed without this opulent vitality and opulent intellectuality India could never have done so much as she did with her spiritual tendencies. It is a great error to suppose that spirituality flourishes best in an impoverished soil with the life half-killed and the intellect discouraged and intimidated. The spirituality that so flourishes is something morbid, hectic and exposed to perilous reactions. It is when the race has lived most richly and thought most profoundly that spirituality finds its heights and its depths and its constant and many-sided fruition. In modern Europe it is after a long explosion of vital force and a stupendous activity of the intellect that spirituality has begun really to emerge and with some promise of being not, as it once was, the sorrowful physician of the malady of life, but the beginning of a large and profound clarity.”6

‡ It is the power of strong intellectuality of the ancient Indian spirit that provided a firm basis for its stupendous vitality and prolific abundance of energy. But this intellectuality should not be confused with that materialistic analytical reasoning that takes the physical world and its appearances for the sole truth and due to the falsity of its approach inevitably arrives at false findings and conclusions. The intellectual power of the ancient Indian spirit was an enlightened intelligence informed with deeper inspiration, intuition and discrimination that could, while remaining completely unaffected by the surface considerations or appearances, not only look at a thing in its entirety but even penetrate and know its truth in the minutest details. The vital being in us is the seat of impulses and desires, of enthusiasm and violence, of dynamic energy, and if left unbridled can play havoc, and therefore, always needs higher guidance for its right functioning. The peculiarity of this culture lay in its phenomenal synthesis of the intellect and vitality guided by its deep spiritual intuition. On the one hand, it laid down detailed Shastras not only for the more profound aspects but even for the most mundane things of life to enable man to act with the security of right knowledge, and on the other hand, gave room for the potent and dynamic expression of that knowledge in life.

One more thing that must always be kept in mind is that the means of investigation or exploration must answer to the nature of the plane with which one is dealing. For example, the means proper for physical investigation are quite out of place in dealing with the vital and the mental planes, and the ones proper for these, are completely out of place in dealing with more involved psychological and spiritual states. Given the heights, depths and subtleties of the fields that this culture set itself to explore, it could ill-afford to rely on means ill-fit for the task. This explains the indispensability of a strong intellectuality that was ‘at once austere and rich, robust and minute, powerful and delicate, massive in principle and curious in detail’ and which, while remaining unaffected by the outer appearances — and even more, by the fixed habits, outlooks and prejudices of the mind, vital and physical, that in some way or the other affect or colour everything — had the power to go straight to the issue and look into its core. Besides, all the various attributes ascribed by Sri Aurobindo to the ancient Indian intellectuality, such as ‘austere and rich, robust and minute, powerful and delicate’, are in no way mutually inconsistent or contradictory, but rather complementary and each is inherent in the integral working of the other. For, an intellect incapable of an austere enquiry cannot be rich, and one that misses or is oblivious of details cannot be massive in principle. It is characteristic of the strong intellectuality of this culture that it has ventured, on the one hand, into the most profound metaphysical speculations and spiritual antinomies, and on the other, has engaged itself in the deep study and analysis of all the aspects of the world, human existence, thought and action, and yet has placed all these in a perfect harmony.‡

D. The Sounding of the Extremes and the Synthetic Impulse

“The European eye is struck in Indian spiritual thought by the Buddhistic and illusionist denial of life. But it must be remembered that this is only one side of its philosophic tendency which assumed exaggerated proportions only in the period of decline. In itself too that was simply one result, in one direction, of a tendency of the Indian mind which is common to all its activities, the impulse to follow each motive, each specialisation of motive even, spiritual, intellectual, ethical, vital, to its extreme point and to sound its utmost possibility. Part of its innate direction was to seek in each not only for its fullness of detail, but for its infinite, its absolute, its profoundest depth or its highest pinnacle. It knew that without a “fine excess” we cannot break down the limits which the dull temper of the normal mind opposes to knowledge and thought and experience; and it had in seeking this point a boundless courage and yet a sure tread. Thus it carried each tangent of philosophic thought, each line of spiritual experience to its farthest point, and chose to look from that farthest point at all existence, so as to see what truth or power such a view could give it. It tried to know the whole of divine nature and to see too as high as it could beyond nature and into whatever there might be of supradivine. When it formulated a spiritual atheism, it followed that to its acme of possible vision. When, too, it indulged in materialistic atheism, – though it did that only with a side glance, as the freak of an insatiable intellectual curiosity, – yet it formulated it straight out, boldly and nakedly, without the least concession to idealism or ethicism.

Everywhere we find this tendency. The ideals of the Indian mind have included the height of self-assertion of the human spirit and its thirst of independence and mastery and possession and the height also of its self-abnegation, dependence and submission and self-giving. In life the ideal of opulent living and the ideal of poverty were carried to the extreme of regal splendour and the extreme of satisfied nudity. Its intuitions were sufficiently clear and courageous not to be blinded by its own most cherished ideas and fixed habits of life. If it was obliged to stereotype caste as the symbol of its social order, it never quite forgot, as the caste-spirit is apt to forget, that the human soul and the human mind are beyond caste. For it had seen in the lowest human being the Godhead, Narayana. It emphasised distinctions only to turn upon them and deny all distinctions. If all its political needs and circumstances compelled it at last to exaggerate the monarchical principle and declare the divinity of the king and to abolish its earlier republican city states and independent federations as too favourable to the centrifugal tendency, if therefore it could not develop democracy, yet it had the democratic idea, applied it in the village, in council and municipality, within the caste, was the first to assert a divinity in the people and could cry to the monarch at the height of his power, “O king, what art thou but the head servant of the demos?” Its idea of the golden age was a free spiritual anarchism. Its spiritual extremism could not prevent it from fathoming through a long era the life of the senses and its enjoyments, and there too it sought the utmost richness of sensuous detail and the depths and intensities of sensuous experience. Yet it is notable that this pursuit of the most opposite extremes never resulted in disorder; and its most hedonistic period offers nothing that at all resembles the unbridled corruption which a similar tendency has more than once produced in Europe. For the Indian mind is not only spiritual and ethical, but intellectual and artistic, and both the rule of the intellect and the rhythm of beauty are hostile to the spirit of chaos. In every extreme the Indian spirit seeks for a law in that extreme and a rule, measure and structure in its application. Besides, this sounding of extremes is balanced by a still more ingrained characteristic, the synthetical tendency, so that having pushed each motive to its farthest possibility the Indian mind returns always towards some fusion of the knowledge it has gained and to a resulting harmony and balance in action and institution. Balance and rhythm which the Greeks arrived at by self-limitation, India arrived at by its sense of intellectual, ethical and aesthetic order and the synthetic impulse of its mind and life.

I have dwelt on these facts because they are apt to be ignored by those who look only at certain sides of the Indian mind and spirit which are most prominent in the last epochs. By insisting only upon these we get an inaccurate or incomplete idea of the past of India and of the integral meaning of its civilisation and the spirit that animated it. The present is only a last deposit of the past at a time of ebb; it has no doubt also to be the starting-point of the future, but in this present all that was in India’s past is still dormant, it is not destroyed; it is waiting there to assume new forms. The decline was the ebb-movement of a creative spirit which can only be understood by seeing it in the full tide of its greatness; the renascence is the return of the tide and it is the same spirit that is likely to animate it, although the forms it takes may be quite new. To judge therefore the possibilities of the renascence, the powers that it may reveal and the scope that it may take, we must dismiss the idea that the tendency of metaphysical abstraction is the one note of the Indian spirit which dominates or inspires all its cadences. Its real key-note is the tendency of spiritual realisation, not cast at all into any white monotone, but many-faceted, many-coloured, as supple in its adaptability as it is intense in its highest pitches. The note of spirituality is dominant, initial, constant, always recurrent; it is the support of all the rest. The first age of India’s greatness was a spiritual age when she sought passionately for the truth of existence through the intuitive mind and through an inner experience and interpretation both of the psychic and the physical existence. The stamp put on her by that beginning she has never lost, but rather always enriched it with fresh spiritual experience and discovery at each step of the national life. Even in her hour of decline it was the one thing she could never lose.

But this spiritual tendency does not shoot upward only to the abstract, the hidden and the intangible; it casts its rays downward and outward to embrace the multiplicities of thought and the richness of life. Therefore the second long epoch of India’s greatness was an age of the intellect, the ethical sense, the dynamic will in action enlightened to formulate and govern life in the lustre of spiritual truth. After the age of the Spirit, the age of the Dharma; after the Veda and Upanishads, the heroic centuries of action and social formation, typal construction and thought and philosophy, when the outward forms of Indian life and culture were fixed in their large lines and even their later developments were being determined in the seed. The great classical age of Sanskrit culture was the flowering of this intellectuality into curiosity of detail in the refinements of scholarship, science, art, literature, politics, sociology, mundane life. We see at this time too the sounding not only of aesthetic, but of emotional and sensuous, even of vital and sensual experience. But the old spirituality reigned behind all this mental and all this vital activity, and its later period, the post-classical, saw a lifting up of the whole lower life and an impressing upon it of the values of the spirit. This was the sense of the Puranic and Tantric systems and the religions of Bhakti. Later Vaishnavism, the last fine flower of the Indian spirit, was in its essence the taking up of the aesthetic, emotional and sensuous being into the service of the spiritual. It completed the curve of the cycle.

The evening of decline which followed the completion of the curve was prepared by three movements of retrogression. First there is, comparatively, a sinking of that superabundant vital energy and a fading of the joy of life and the joy of creation. Even in the decline this energy is still something splendid and extraordinary and only for a very brief period sinks nearest to a complete torpor; but still a comparison with its past greatness will show that the decadence was marked and progressive. Secondly, there is a rapid cessation of the old free intellectual activity, a slumber of the scientific and the critical mind as well as the creative intuition; what remains becomes more and more a repetition of ill-understood fragments of past knowledge. There is a petrification of the mind and life in the relics of the forms which a great intellectual past had created. Old authority and rule become rigidly despotic and, as always then happens, lose their real sense and spirit. Finally, spirituality remains but burns no longer with the large and clear flame of knowledge of former times, but in intense jets and in a dispersed action which replaces the old magnificent synthesis and in which certain spiritual truths are emphasised to the neglect of others. This diminution amounts to a certain failure of the great endeavour which is the whole meaning of Indian culture, a falling short in the progress towards the perfect spiritualisation of the mind and the life. The beginnings were superlative, the developments very great, but at a certain point where progress, adaptation, a new flowering should have come in, the old civilisation stopped short, partly drew back, partly lost its way. The essential no doubt remained and still remains in the heart of the race and not only in its habits and memories, but in its action it was covered up in a great smoke of confusion.”7

‡ Only a broad perspective on the four great powers of the Indian spirit can give one a glimpse of the visible action of these powers and of the various forms that they assume in the course of their manifestation and their interrelationships as well as their true justification. Without this perspective, one is helplessly lost in a maze of apparently meaningless minutiae without a clue and stumbles about among false and partial conclusions missing entirely the deeper significance of those forms. It is usually for this reason that most of even those people who try to demonstrate the greatness of this culture out of a deeply sympathetic outlook, not to mention those with a thoroughly hostile view, base their estimate on data that hardly reveal the core of its greatness. To obviate lamentable muddles, a true vision of what is the essence of greatness of this culture is indispensable, especially for those who are keen on entering the essential spirit of it.

Some of the points contained in Sri Aurobindo’s deliberation on the fourth power of the Indian spirit require further consideration. First of all, what was the true basis of the impulse to follow a thing to its extreme point and sound its utmost possibility? the logic behind it? The answer to this problem lay in the deep spiritual intuition of Indian culture that firmly held to this fundamental perception that the Supreme being, the Absolute is indescribable by any name or definite conception that the human mind can attribute to it. Therefore when the limited mental consciousness tries to express the Absolute in its own terms, there inevitably arise various ultimate contradictory perceptions about the nature of the Absolute, such as Existent and non-existent, Infinite and finite, Conscient and Inconscient, etc. accompanied by an impulse to follow each of these attributes to their extreme until it can be vividly experienced and transcending even these, the mind may arrive at some higher synthesis of these opposites. Man’s deeply ingrained nature of being always discontented, even with the highest possible achievements, is essentially a reflection of the insatiable urge of the Soul to break all resistances or obstacles and regain its own true nature. It is therefore a common characteristic of all the various philosophies and yoga systems in India to follow any given experience or approach to the Divine to its extreme and try to perceive the Divine and define this world and existence from that standpoint. It is indeed this urge to sound the extreme limits of the spirit, world and existence that has greatly extended the field of human thought, experience and action. But the inert and obscure outer nature of man content within its narrow and petty confines instinctively resists any change in the limited framework of its ordinary life. A fine excess is therefore always necessary to break this dead resistance of the lower nature and open novel dimensions and possibilities. It is this urge for an ever deeper exploration into the secrets of matter that has enabled physical science to have greater mastery over physical nature. But more than any outer exploration of the physical world and life, this culture explored profound spiritual, inner and psychological worlds and existences to their extremes of which the physical world and existence are mere derivatives. Thus, there hardly remains any aspect of man’s subjective and objective existence which has not been followed by this culture to its ultimate heights and depths.

But this tendency of sounding the extremes can truly exist only when it is accompanied by a synthetic impulse that alone can provide a firm basis for all possible extremes to harmoniously dwell together. After all, a synthesis that doesn’t have the necessary wideness to embrace the most extreme or discordant elements, cannot be a truly comprehensive synthesis in the true sense of the word. Nor should this synthesis be confused with an amalgamation of different things or components with no unifying element. It is the essential Spirit, the fire that burns in the spiritual heart of this culture that turns even the most extreme forms into those consistent with its original Vedic spirit and synthesises them all in that spirit. The tendency of extremes, lacking some wider synthetic spirit, often leads to serious consequences, and true spirit of synthesis exists only in the deeper parts of our being. Spirituality and the integral Vedic synthesis in the Indian culture was the reason why, right from the beginning, this culture could confidently take each idea, strand to its ultimate consummation. It knew that the Spirit is the true foundation of all and if firmly rooted in it, even the seemingly antagonistic elements can be triumphantly synthesized. ‡

III. The Aryan System of Education

“What was the secret of that gigantic intellectuality, spirituality and superhuman moral force which we see pulsating in the Ramayana and Mahabharata, in the ancient philosophy, in the supreme poetry, art, sculpture and architecture of India? What was at the basis of the incomparable public works and engineering achievements, the opulent and exquisite industries, the great triumphs of science, scholarship, jurisprudence, logic, metaphysics, the unique social structure? What supported the heroism and self-abandonment of the Kshatriya, the Sikh and the Rajput, the unconquerable national vitality and endurance? What was it that stood behind that civilisation second to none in the massiveness of its outlines or the perfection of its details? Without a great and unique discipline involving a perfect education of soul and mind, a result so immense and persistent would have been impossible. It would be an error to look for the secret of Aryan success in the details of the instruction given in the old ashrams and universities so far as they have come down to us. We must know what was the principle and basis on which the details were founded. We shall find the secret of their success in a profound knowledge of human psychology and its subtle application to the methods of intellectual training and instruction.”8

‡ Just as in all other fields, the view of ancient Indian culture towards education was inner – deeply psychological and spiritual. It would, therefore, be an error to look for the secret of the phenomenal success of the Aryan system of education in the outer details of the curriculum, setup of the school, educational qualification of the teacher, and so on, which are generally considered to be the chief elements of any education system. Can one develop, by any external means, that prodigious accurate memory of the ancient Indian who could successfully record and pass on through countless generations, without even the slightest inexactitude in any syllable or pronunciation, the Vedas and the colossal amount of other classical Indian literature? No outer schemes, techniques or means of education could have possibly developed those great powers of the ancient Indian spirit and attained to those superlative achievements. We must therefore look for that secret in the profound knowledge of deeper human psychology that could freely make use of all or some of these outer means, and if need be, create entirely new ones suited to its purpose, or even dispense with all possible outer means to act solely through the deeper intuition.

The Aryan system of education has indeed been one of the most profound education systems developed by mankind in the past. But those desirous of replicating the same system in present times must bear in mind that it cannot be replicated in this manner and that the progress of time and the need of humanity demand a new orientation and another form of that ideal more suited to the new demands. The old forms and methods are no longer sufficient for the present purposes of the time-spirit. Besides, the descent of the supramental consciousness and its constant action in the subtle physical plane is actively bringing about a change, even though it is almost imperceptible on the surface, in the whole balance of things. Therefore, we must keep to the essential spirit, but the forms must be more responsive to the present time and circumstances. ‡

B. The Process – the Conversion of the Retas into Ojas

“THE PRACTICE of Brahmacharya is the first and most necessary condition of increasing the force within and turning it to such uses as may benefit the possessor or mankind. All human energy has a physical basis. The mistake made by European materialism is to suppose the basis to be everything and confuse it with the source. The source of life and energy is not material but spiritual, but the basis, the foundation on which the life and energy stand and work, is physical. The ancient Hindus clearly recognised this distinction between kāraṇa and pratiṣṭhā, the north pole and the south pole of being. Earth or gross matter is the pratiṣṭhā, Brahman or spirit is the kāraṇa. To raise up the physical to the spiritual is Brahmacharya, for by the meeting of the two the energy which starts from one and produces the other is enhanced and fulfils itself.

This is the metaphysical theory. The application depends on a right understanding of the physical and psychological conformation of the human receptacle of energy. The fundamental physical unit is the retas, in which the tejas, the heat and light and electricity in a man, is involved and hidden. All energy is latent in the retas. This energy may be either expended physically or conserved. All passion, lust, desire wastes the energy by pouring it, either in the gross form or a sublimated subtler form, out of the body. Immorality in act throws it out in the gross form; immorality of thought in the subtle form. In either case there is waste, and unchastity is of the mind and speech as well as of the body. On the other hand, all self-control conserves the energy in the retas, and conservation always brings with it increase. But the needs of the physical body are limited and the excess of energy must create a surplus which has to turn itself to some use other than the physical. According to the ancient theory retas is jala or water, full of light and heat and electricity, in one word, of tejas. The excess of the retas turns first into heat or tapas which stimulates the whole system, and it is for this reason that all forms of self-control and austerity are called tapas or tapasyā, because they generate the heat or stimulus which is a source of powerful action and success; secondly, it turns to tejas proper, light, the energy which is at the source of all knowledge; thirdly, it turns to vidyut or electricity, which is at the basis of all forceful action whether intellectual or physical. In the vidyut again is involved the ojas, or prāṇaśakti, the primal energy which proceeds from ether. The retas refining from jala to tapas, tejas and vidyut and from vidyut to ojas, fills the system with physical strength, energy and brain-power and in its last form of ojas rises to the brain and informs it with that primal energy which is the most refined form of matter and nearest to spirit. It is ojas that creates a spiritual force or vīrya, by which a man attains to spiritual knowledge, spiritual love and faith, spiritual strength. It follows that the more we can by Brahmacharya increase the store of tapas, tejas, vidyut and ojas, the more we shall fill ourselves with utter energy for the works of the body, heart, mind and spirit.”10

C. The Three Gunas and the Development of Sattva

“This view of the human soul was not the whole of the knowledge on which ancient Hinduism based its educational discipline. In addition it had the view that all knowledge is within and has to be evoked by education rather than instilled from outside. The constitution of man consists of three principles of nature sattva, rajas and tamas, the comprehensive, active and passive elements of universal action, which, in one of their thousand fold aspects, manifest as knowledge, passion and ignorance. Tamas is a constitutional dullness or passivity which obscures the knowledge within and creates ignorance, mental inertia, slowness, forgetfulness, disinclination to study, inability to grasp and distinguish. Rajas is an undisciplined activity which obscures knowledge by passion, attachment, prejudgment, predilection and wrong ideas. Sattva is an illumination which reveals the hidden knowledge and brings it to the surface where the observation can grasp and the memory record it. This conception of the constitution of the knowing faculty made the removal of tamas, the disciplining of rajas and the awakening of sattva the main problem of the teacher. He had to train the student to be receptive of illumination from within. The disciplining of rajas was effected by a strict moral discipline which induced a calm, clear, receptive state of mind free from intellectual self-will and pride and the obscuration of passion, – the famous discipline of the brahmacārin which was the foundation of Aryan culture and Aryan morals; and the interference of wrong ideas was sought to be removed by strict mental submission to the teacher during the receptive period, when the body of ascertained knowledge or right ideas already in man’s possession was explained to him and committed to memory. The removal of tamas was effected by the discipline of moral purity, which awakened the energy of tejas and electricity in the system and by the power of tapasyā trained it to be a reservoir of mental force and clarity. The awakening of illumination was actively effected by the triple method of repetition, meditation and discussion. Āvṛtti or repetition was meant to fill the recording part of the mind with the śabda or word, so that the artha or meaning might of itself rise from within. Needless to say, a mechanical repetition was not likely to produce this effect. There must be that clear still receptivity and that waiting upon the word or thing with the contemplative part of the mind which is what the ancient Indians meant by dhyāna or meditation. All of us have felt, when studying a language, difficulties which seemed insoluble while grappling with a text, suddenly melt away and a clear understanding arise without assistance from book or teacher after putting away the book from our mind for a brief period. Many of us have experienced also, the strangeness of taking up a language or subject, after a brief discontinuance, to find that we understand it much better than when we took it up, know the meanings of words we had never met with before and can explain sentences which, before we discontinued the study, would have baffled our understanding. This is because the jñātā or knower within has had his attention called to the subject and has been busy in the interval drawing upon the source of knowledge within in connection with it. This experience is only possible to those whose sattwic or illuminative element has been powerfully aroused or consciously or unconsciously trained to action by the habit of intellectual clarity and deep study. The highest reach of the sattwic development is when one can dispense often or habitually with outside aids, the teacher or the text book, grammar and dictionary and learn a subject largely or wholly from within. But this is only possible to the Yogin by a successful prosecution of the discipline of Yoga.”11

‡ This succinct account of the Aryan system of education by Sri Aurobindo not only facilitates our entry into the secrets of those processes that this culture had utilised in the past for the building up of its great superstructure but even more, it provides us with those fundamental secrets of human psychology and education that should be the true basis and guiding principles for any education system. It may also help us to understand the root cause of the inevitable failure of all the various attempts, going on throughout the world, at reforms and innovations in this field due to a lack of this basic understanding of human psychology.

Firstly, what is the rationale behind Brahmacharya, and why was it made the basis of the Aryan system of education? Actually, the idea of Brahmacharya is a fundamental concept with a wider sense than the mere abstinence from any sexual activity, as is usually understood by the term. Fundamentally, Brahmacharya is to thoroughly regulate, cultivate and raise one’s whole being and its conduct in the light of Brahman or Spirit, or to say, to raise up one’s normal nature to the spiritual. Being aware of the hierarchy of worlds and planes the Rishis in this culture had a deep perception of the higher worlds being the true ‘kāraṇa’ or cause of the lower ones and of the lower worlds being the ‘pratiṣṭhā’ or the base or the ground for the expression of the truths of the higher ones. As a tree is involved in its seed, similarly the ‘kāraṇa’ is involved in the ‘pratiṣṭhā’. This is the secret of evolution which explains why we see life evolving out of matter, and mind out of life, for otherwise there would seem to be no justifiable reason for a higher principle evolving out of the lower. As even a physical body, however robust in its constitution, cannot be sustained for any length of time without the informing life, the life (vital) too cannot exist without the informing mind. By the virtue of their deep spiritual intuition, our Rishis knew that it is the Absolute Supreme Divine who being inherent in this world animates it, for otherwise, it could not exist, and therefore, it is only rational that this evolutionary terrestrial manifestation evolves back to its inherent spiritual reality. A conscious ascension to the divine Life is, therefore, man’s real business in the world and the true justification of his existence. The entire education system of the ancient Indian culture can be looked upon as a grand system aimed at preparing the human base (pratiṣṭhā) for the utmost possible realisation of this goal.

The greatest challenge before this system in preparing the base was to counter the persistent tendency of the lower nature to gravitate towards its original inconscient roots that resist any ascension. It is this downward pull that makes the physical nature predominantly tamasic, inert, obscure, ignorant and unwilling to change and the nature of the predominantly rajasic vital recklessly dynamic, so as to counter the dead inertia of the physical and impel it to move. The immiscence of the impurity of these lower members obscures and tarnishes the working of the mind. The mind, being a power higher in scale than the vital and the physical and should ideally be open to higher intuitions, knowledge and discernment and serve as a regulating and guiding authority for the two lower members, is usually their stooge engaged in indiscriminately working to fulfil their petty desires. This all-engrossing preoccupation with these lower gratifications dissipates most of the energy and there is hardly enough left for any higher pursuit in life. The reason for this is, firstly, the two main sources from which we derive our energy — food, and even more, physical sensations and vital interchange — are already very crude and indirect ways of receiving the universal energy and what we thus receive is very meagre in quantity and of a very mixed and impure nature in quality. Secondly, even what we receive through these sources is soon dissipated and lost due to the insufficient holding capacity — a lack of Brahmacharya — for there are blind instincts, egoistic demands, vital insistences, hedonistic tendencies, lusts, cravings, fears, passions and a numberless host of other things that act as so many drains that flush away the energy. A part of our energy is spent in the sustenance and smooth functioning of our material existence, but most of it goes in the satisfaction of these blind instincts and passions. The more one becomes conscious of the working of one’s being the more one is able to discern how these obscure movements tend to obscure and distort all our thoughts and actions.

It is a common experience of all those who have set themselves for sincere pursuance of some higher aim in their life that the least indulgence in any lower impulse takes away, to a greater or lesser extent, their energy and lowers their consciousness. Any such act prevents the consciousness from rising upwards and throws cold water on one’s efforts. This is why, if one is in a state where one is taken over by the mechanical lower nature and wastes one’s energies in petty and low occupations, in the gratification of one’s animal propensities, one is deprived of the uplifting action of the more refined and higher sources of energies. A lower working of energies renders practically impossible the action of such virtues as loyalty, obedience, courage, gratitude, service, and so on, that make up man’s true manhood. This explains why in a culture focused entirely on the satisfaction of its lower instincts and its entire system geared towards providing each individual and the collectivity the utmost chance of fulfilling their desires, there is hardly any room for the action of the higher parts of the being and any possibility of some diviner manifestation. In such an outlook on life, even if we come across some strict disciplining and arduous regulation of physical and even vital tendencies, that must not be in any way confused with Brahmacharya, for all such arduousness is completely in service of some subtle or magnified forms of those egoistic satisfactions, for, essentially the whole consciousness and its energies are still entirely concentrated on the gratification of the lower self only. Therefore, in view of the greatness of its aim it was indispensable for Indian culture to work on both ends, that is, on the one hand, put a check on the impurities coming through our usual sources of energy and avoid, as much as possible, any spillage and waste, and on the other, refine the sources themselves and open progressively to higher and more subtle sources of energy. When one is siddha or perfected in the practice of Brahmacharya not only does one learn to draw one’s energy more from the subtle universal and spiritual sources — which can truly come in an uninterrupted flow only when there is not the risk of any serious leakage or mixture from below — but, at the same time, the adhara itself is trained to bear an increasing inrush and play of the energy. Just as dammed water can be utilised to electrify a whole continent or be channelised to irrigate a large area, similarly it was the immense storage of energy that provided the necessary power for the greatest achievements of Indian culture. But unlike the water in the reservoir, the retas jala not only gains in volume but becomes progressively refined, sublimated and transformed into more potent forms — tapas, tejas, vidyut and ojas. This process fills our whole being with superior energy for the works of the body, heart, mind and spirit.

In the light of the above discussion, one can see how the present approach to education is diametrically opposite to that of the ancient Indian system. The sole aim of the present education, due to a materialistic outlook, is to equip the individual for a more and more efficient arrangement of the satisfactions of his lower physical and vital being and make the best he can of the ephemeral terrestrial existence. Instead of helping in curbing the lawless lower tendencies in man, which should be the primary aim of any education system, it, on the contrary, inflates them into despotic and exacting tyrants, in following whose dictates one ends up exhausting all one’s energies. In such a low state of energy in education, even the ordinary activity and functioning of the mind become too cumbersome for the child, not to mention the working of those more subtle and powerful intellectual, psychological and inner faculties. For example, even to be able to focus his attention on the subject of study and deeply reflect on it, grasp and record the meaning in his memory becomes difficult for a child. But instead of addressing the root of the problem, the whole effort in the field of education around the world is to make the academic studies more and more interesting and enjoyable for the student so that he may somehow take interest in studies and focus his attention. But to teach the children to take interest in whatever they are doing is not the same thing as interesting the students. This shortsighted approach has serious consequences on the child’s psychology as he is then habitually inclined for the rest of his life to choose always what seems to him to be more interesting, pleasurable, comfortable or, at least, the least troublesome, while ideally, he should be capable of rising above his preferences and do with utmost interest and concentration whatever he sees as the right thing to be done. Apart from this widespread attempt to make things interesting, there is yet another all-pervasive view or concept in education which has far more serious and disastrous consequences. This view holds that the sole aim of education is to prepare a man to succeed in life and society, and success for it means amassing more and more of those means — money and position and prestige being the most prominent among them — that may help the most in the fulfilment of the physical and vital propensities. The importance of these means is presented in such exaggerated terms that it seems as if human life would not even be possible without them. To dream of beauty, greatness and perfection, to aspire for some deeper and higher values in life, to strive for self-transcendence, all this seems to this narrow outlook very utopian and impractical. Being somewhat dissatisfied with this scenario, there have been independent attempts at conducting education by some moral principles and high ideals. Some of them have even gone so far as to try to reproduce the outer details of the old gurukul system of India so as to return to the ancient Indian system of education. But lacking any profound understanding of the fundamentals of education and human psychology, and being under the sway of the all-pervasive influence of the utilitarian spirit, all such attempts have as yet been found to be mostly, if not completely, ineffective in practice.

When one reflects on this cryptic statement of Sri Aurobindo on education, that ‘An education that confines itself to imparting knowledge, is no education’, one cannot but wonder as to what else or what more it is that would be expected of education, for the commonly accepted higher aim of education is the acquisition of knowledge. First of all, merely to have supplied the student with a large or well-selected mass of information on the various subjects which comprise the best part of human culture at the time cannot in itself be considered education. Summarising the whole approach of our present education through an apt simile, Sri Aurobindo writes at one place, that, “It would hardly be a good technical education for a carpenter to be taught how to fell trees so as to provide himself with wood & never to learn how to prepare tables, chairs & cabinets or even what tools were necessary for his craft. Yet this is precisely what our system of education does….the student who goes forth thus equipped, may become a great timber-merchant but unless he is an exceptional genius he will never be even a moderate carpenter….To give the student knowledge is necessary, but it is still more necessary to build up in him the power of using his knowledge.” (CWSA 1: 359) Therefore, it is far more important to cultivate the power to place that information, without being overwhelmed or bound by it, in a proper perspective and arrive at some conclusion from it. Without developed mental faculties mere information in itself can have no more value than the description of the elephant made by the blind inquirers. The development of various faculties such as memory, judgment, imagination, perception, visualisation and reasoning are needed to build the edifice of thought and knowledge for the knower. If we ponder over these faculties we can see how the complete action of any of these involves the action of others and the action of one affects the functioning of the others. Also, with more and more intellectual, psychological, subjective and inner development, the nature of the working of these faculties too gains in complexity, refinement and accuracy which should be evident enough by comparing their action in a highly cultivated and cultured person to that in an uncultured brute.

But there arises a fundamental question: can even the highest possible development of these or even various other such powers and faculties, however essential they may seem for human life and action, be the sole aim of education? Just as mere information has no meaning without the utilising intellectual capacity, similarly, not only do all these powers and faculties have no use in themselves without a developed consciousness that can put them in right order and utilise them for a proper end, they may, and mostly do, even prove to be serious obstacles in any higher pursuit when pursued for their own sake without the true consciousness. As it is, it is almost impossible for the little human ego to be able to maintain its balance and not get puffed up even by small successes, by the acquisition of wealth, position, or a host of other such things, which is why most spiritual practices lay stress on keeping a safe distance and abstaining from any indulgence in these things. Thus, the more subtle powers and faculties — much more potent than the ordinary acquisitions — that spontaneously develop by the practice of Brahmacharya demand a far greater consciousness that can, without being overwhelmed by these powers, securely make proper use of them under the guidance of some deeper truth. The extraordinary powers and capacities that are generated by the storage of energy can never be the sole object of education, which should be evident enough by closely examining the Asuric characters such as Ravana and Hiranyakashipu, who are classic examples of the terrible misuse of tremendously developed vital and mental powers.

In a deeper analysis, it is not so much the excellence or proficiency in some field of knowledge or some faculty, that constitutes the true personality of a person but, far more, that psychological development and innate constitution which is spontaneously oriented towards expressing the Divine Being and which guides all one’s thoughts, feelings and actions accordingly. For all the knowledge or the power of a person becomes all the more harmful and destructive if his fundamental orientation is wrong. Therefore, considering the greatness of its task and the prerequisites of the fields of its exploration, Indian culture needed to first ensure a strong and infallible psychological, intellectual, moral and inner base on which it could securely build the edifice of knowledge. Even in ordinary life the integrity, suitability or propriety of a person is taken into consideration before entrusting him some responsibility or when sharing with him some confidential or sensitive information. Those who have some sense of the deeper working of things, should be able to see how any amount of development of intellectual, or, even, of stupendous psychic and occult powers can fail to truly bring about any fundamental change in the narrow egoistic outlook on life and world. In fact, all such solitary development only facilitates the egoistic consciousness by giving more potent means in its hands for the fulfilment of its contemptible aims in an enlarged form.

All this discussion inevitably leads us to the conclusion that the development of a consciousness that is constantly open and responsive to the truth of one’s being and which spontaneously uses all its capacities and powers for the expression of that truth, is far more important than the mere development of any powers or faculties. Once a true orientation, that is a consciousness instinctively turned towards the Divine, which is indeed the very nature of the psychic being, is securely established in the being, then there can be no risk in developing any powers even to their highest limits. If we look at things in a truer way, we can say that it is our deeper self alone that can truly determine the necessary powers or the faculties that it may utilise for its self-expression, and if it so wishes, it may even dispense with all those and create new ones more suited to its purpose.

The greatest challenge before the teacher in the Aryan system of education was the removal of tamasic and the disciplining of the rajasic tendencies in the student that obscure or impede the knowledge, and then the awakening of sattva and the psychic being, to create the most conducive environment for the unfolding of the latent knowledge. Thus, moved by its original spiritual impulse, the whole effort of this culture even in the field of education has been to develop, first and foremost, that inner orientation which is constantly turned towards the Divine. Fundamentally, true motive is far more important and valuable than mere knowledge, until one reaches a stage when there remains no disparity between the two and each becomes an integral part of the other. Then, true knowledge leads to true motive and true motive facilitates entry into true knowledge. This explains why education cannot confine itself to merely imparting knowledge.

This succinct account of the Aryan system of education by Sri Aurobindo helps us enter into the secret of the great achievements of this culture and gives us a clue to the true sense of all the various outer processes, forms and expressions that this culture has used for an effective manifestation of its fundamental objective — the preparation of a sound instrumentation for the manifestation of the Divine.‡

I. The Legend of India’s Political Incompetence

“..there are many who would admit the greatness of the achievement of India in the things of the mind and the spirit, but would still point out that she has failed in life, her culture has not resulted in a strong, successful or progressive organisation of life such as Europe shows to us, and that in the end at least the highest part of her mind turned away from life to asceticism and an inactive and world-shunning pursuit by the individual of his personal spiritual salvation. Or at most she has come only to a certain point and then there has been an arrest and decadence….

The ideals that governed the spirit and body of Indian society were of the highest kind, its social order secured an inexpugnable basic stability, the strong life force that worked in it was creative of an extraordinary energy, richness and interest, and the life organised remarkable in its opulence, variety in unity, beauty, productiveness, movement. All the records of Indian history, art and literature bear evidence to a cultural life of this character and even in decline and dissolution there survives some stamp of it to remind however faintly and distantly of the past greatness. To what then does the charge brought against Indian culture as an agent of the life power amount and what is its justification? In its exaggerated form it is founded upon the characteristics of the decline and dissolution, the features of the decadence read backward into the time of greatness, and it amounts to this that India has always shown an incompetence for any free or sound political organisation and has been constantly a divided and for the most part of her long history a subject nation, that her economic system whatever its bygone merits, if it had any, remained an inelastic and static order that led in modern conditions to poverty and failure and her society an unprogressive hierarchy, caste-ridden, full of semi-barbaric abuses, only fit to be thrown on the scrap-heap among the broken rubbish of the past and replaced by the freedom, soundness and perfection or at least the progressive perfectibility of the European social order. It is necessary to reestablish the real facts and their meaning and afterwards it will be time to pass judgment on the political, the economic and the social aspects of Indian culture.

The legend of Indian political incompetence has arisen from a false view of the historical development and an insufficient knowledge of the ancient past of the country. It has long been currently supposed that she passed at once from the freer type of the primitive Aryan or Vedic social and political organisation to a system socially marked by the despotism of the Brahmin theocracy and politically by an absolute monarchy of the oriental, by which is meant the Western Asiatic, type and has remained fixed in these two things for ever after. That summary reading of Indian history has been destroyed by a more careful and enlightened scholarship and the facts are of a quite different nature. It is true that India never evolved either the scrambling and burdensome industrialism or the parliamentary organisation of freedom and self-styled democracy characteristic of the bourgeois or Vaishya period of the cycle of European progress. But the time is passing when the uncritical praise of these things as the ideal state and the last word of social and political progress was fashionable, their defects are now visible and the greatness of an oriental civilisation need not be judged by the standard of these Western developments. Indian scholars have attempted to read the modern ideas and types of democracy and even a parliamentary system into the past of India, but this seems to me an ill-judged endeavour. There was a strong democratic element*[1], if we must use the Western terms, in Indian polity and even institutions that present a certain analogy to the parliamentary form, but in reality these features were of India’s own kind and not at all the same thing as modern parliaments and modern democracy. And so considered they are a much more remarkable evidence of the political capacity of the Indian people in their living adaptation to the ensemble of the social mind and body of the nation than when we judge them by the very different standard of Western society…”2

‡ Wherever Indian culture is discussed, more and more people are coming to acknowledge India’s great contributions in the field of the mind and the spirit, but still, we find the misconception common that, despite her spiritual achievements, she failed in her organising of life, in political acumen and consequently, had to endure constant attacks by foreign invaders and a long period of foreign domination. While India’s so-called political incompetency has been used by her antagonists as the source of criticism, of attempts by critics to prove her incapacity, of derision, even her sympathisers, in the absence of any clarity on the subject, admit her ineptness in politics. This misconception and ambiguity has arisen because, firstly, Indian culture regarded the political aspect, like all other aspects of life, as only a means for realising the Spirit and manifesting it and she created forms and institutions solely from this point of view. It follows that one can neither understand her by surface appearances nor judge her according to surface standards. Even if some of her historical forms or institutions seem similar to modern ones, we will find that substantially they are different, because the Indian spirit perceives things in a special way. This is one underlying reason for misconception. The second reason Indian culture has been deemed incompetent is that, ignoring the long millenniums of ascendancy and greatness, her short history of decline and degradation has been underscored and given central importance. If we look deeper, in the light of Sri Aurobindo (as we have seen earlier), we find that what is ordinarily called a decline of the culture is nothing but a consistent and essential movement of the Spirit towards the most material parts of its being. Sri Aurobindo gives us such a profound and comprehensive perspective for examining Indian polity as cannot be found elsewhere, and, as a result, not only are the misconceptions about Indian political incompetence dispelled but we see that as in other aspects of life, her achievements and ability in the political arena too are incomparable. ‡

[1] “The principle of popular rule is the possession of the reins of government by the mass of the people, but by the possession is not intended necessarily the actual exercise of administration. When the people are able to approve or to disapprove of any action of the Government with the certainty that such approval or disapproval will be absolutely effective, the spirit of democracy is present even if the body is not evolved. India in her ancient polity possessed this spirit of democracy.”1

II. The Nature of the Indian Monarchical State – Its Subjection to the Yoke of the Dharma

“But Indian monarchy previous to the Mahomedan invasion was not, in spite of a certain sanctity and great authority conceded to the regal position and the personality of the king as the representative of the divine Power and the guardian of the Dharma, in any way a personal despotism or an absolutist autocracy: it had no resemblance to the ancient Persian monarchy or the monarchies of western and central Asia or the Roman imperial government or later European autocracies: it was of an altogether different type from the system of the Pathan or the Mogul emperors. The Indian king exercised supreme administrative and judicial power, was in possession of all the military forces of the kingdom and with his Council alone responsible for peace and war and he had too a general supervision and control over the good order and welfare of the life of the community, but his power was not personal and it was besides hedged in by safeguards against abuse and encroachment and limited by the liberties and powers of other public authorities and interests who were, so to speak, lesser copartners with him in the exercise of sovereignty and administrative legislation and control. He was in fact a limited or constitutional monarch, although the machinery by which the constitution was maintained and the limitation effected differed from the kind familiar in European history; and even the continuance of his rule was far more dependent than that of mediaeval European kings on the continued will and assent of the people.

A greater sovereign than the king was the Dharma, the religious, ethical, social, political, juridic and customary law organically governing the life of the people. This impersonal authority was considered sacred and eternal in its spirit and the totality of its body, always characteristically the same, the changes organically and spontaneously brought about in its actual form by the evolution of the society being constantly incorporated in it, regional, family and other customs forming a sort of attendant and subordinate body capable of change only from within, – and with the Dharma no secular authority had any right of autocratic interference. The Brahmins themselves were recorders and exponents of the Dharma, not its creators nor authorised to make at will any changes, although it is evident that by an authoritative expression of opinion they could and did favour or oppose this or that tendency to change of principle or detail. The king was only the guardian, executor and servant of the Dharma, charged to see to its observance and to prevent offences, serious irregularities and breaches. He himself was bound the first to obey it and observe the rigorous rule it laid on his personal life and action and on the province, powers and duties of his regal authority and office.

This subjection of the sovereign power to the Dharma was not an ideal theory inoperative in practice; for the rule of the socio-religious law actively conditioned the whole life of the people and was therefore a living reality, and it had in the political field very large practical consequences. It meant first that the king had not the power of direct legislation and was limited to the issue of administrative decrees that had to be in consonance with the religious, social, political, economic constitution of the community, – and even here there were other powers than that of the king who shared with him the right of promulgating and seeing to the execution of administrative decrees independently issued, – neither could he disregard in the general tenor and character and the effective result of his administration the express or tacit will of the people.

The religious liberties of the commons were assured and could not normally be infringed by any secular authority; each religious community, each new or long-standing religion could shape its own way of life and institutions and had its own authorities or governing bodies exercising in their proper field an entire independence. There was no exclusive State religion and the monarch was not the religious head of the people. Asoka in this respect seems to have attempted an extension of the royal control or influence and similar velleities were occasionally shown on a minor scale by other powerful sovereigns. But Asoka’s so-called edicts of this kind had a recommendatory rather than an imperative character, and the sovereign who wished to bring about a change in religious belief or institutions had always, in accordance with the Indian principle of communal freedom and the obligation of a respect for and a previous consultation of the wishes of those concerned, to secure the assent of the recognised authorities or to refer the matter to a consultative assembly for deliberation, as was done in the famous Buddhist councils, or to arrange a discussion between the exponents of the different religions and abide by the issue. The monarch might personally favour a particular sect or creed and his active preference might evidently have a considerable propagandist influence, but at the same time he was bound to respect and support in his public office all the recognised religions of the people with a certain measure of impartiality, a rule that explains the support extended by Buddhist and Brahmin emperors to both the rival religions. At times there were, mainly in the south, instances of petty or violent State persecutions, but these outbreaks were a violation of the Dharma due to momentary passion at a time of acute religious ferment and were always local and of a brief duration. Normally there was no place in the Indian political system for religious oppression and intolerance and a settled State policy of that kind was unthinkable.

The social life of the people was similarly free from autocratic interference. Instances of royal legislation in this province are rare and here too, when it occurred, there had to be a consultation of the will of those concerned, as in the rearrangement or the reconstitution of the caste system by the Sena kings in Bengal after its disorganisation during a long period of Buddhist predominance. Change in the society was brought about not artificially from above but automatically from within and principally by the freedom allowed to families or particular communities to develop or alter automatically their own rule of life, ācāra.

In the sphere of administration the power of the king was similarly hedged in by the standing constitution of the Dharma. His right of taxation was limited in the most important sources of revenue to a fixed percentage as a maximum and in other directions often by the right of the bodies representing the various elements of the community to a voice in the matter and always by the general rule that his right to govern was subject to the satisfaction and good-will of the people. This as we shall see, was not merely a pious wish or opinion of the Brahmin custodians of the Dharma. The king was in person the supreme court and the highest control in the execution of the civil and criminal law, but here too his role was that of the executor: he was bound to administer the law faithfully as it stood through his judges or with the aid of the Brahmin legists learned in these matters. He had the complete and unfettered control in his Council only of foreign policy, military administration and war and peace and of a great number of directive activities. He was free to make efficient arrangements for all that part of the administration that served to secure and promote the welfare of the community, good order, public morals, and all such matters as could best be supervised or regulated by the sovereign authority. He had a right of patronage and punishment consistent with the law and was expected to exercise it with a strict regard to an effect of general beneficence and promotion of the public welfare.

There could therefore be ordinarily little or no room in the ancient Indian system for autocratic freak or monarchical violence and oppression, much less for the savage cruelty and tyranny of so common an occurrence in the history of some other countries. Nevertheless such happenings were possible by the sovereign’s disregard of the Dharma or by a misuse of his power of administrative decree; instances occurred of the kind, – though the worst recorded is that of a tyrant belonging to a foreign dynasty; in other cases any prolonged outbreak of autocratic caprice, violence or injustice seems to have led before long to an effective protest or revolt on the part of the people. The legists provided for the possibility of oppression. In spite of the sanctity and prestige attaching to the sovereign it was laid down that obedience ceased to be binding if the king ceased to be faithful executor of the Dharma. Incompetence and violation of the obligation to rule to the satisfaction of the people were in theory and effect sufficient causes for his removal. Manu even lays it down that an unjust and oppressive king should be killed by his own subjects like a mad dog, and this justification by the highest authority of the right or even the duty of insurrection and regicide in extreme cases is sufficient to show that absolutism or the unconditional divine right of kings was no part of the intention of the Indian political system. As a matter of fact the right was actually exercised as we find both from history and literature. Another more peaceful and more commonly exercised remedy was a threat of secession or exodus which in most cases was sufficient to bring the delinquent ruler to reason. It is interesting to find the threat of secession employed against an unpopular monarch in the south as late as the seventeenth century, as well as a declaration by a popular assembly denouncing any assistance given to the king as an act of treason. A more common remedy was deposition by the council of ministers or by the public assemblies. The kingship thus constituted proved to be in effect moderate, efficient and beneficent, served well the purposes assigned to it and secured an abiding hold on the affections of the people. The monarchical institution was however only one, an approved and very important, but not, as we see from the existence of the ancient republics, an indispensable element of the Indian socio-political system, and we shall understand nothing of the real principle of the system and its working if we stop short with a view of the regal façade and fail to see what lay behind it. It is there that we shall find the clue to the essential character of the whole construction.”3

‡ Any proper understanding of Indian polity is possible only if we consider the Indian political system as one facet, with the same aim, of the Sanatana Dharma — the multi-faceted system that expresses India’s spiritual awareness. As has been discussed previously, in the course of its evolution, Indian society, during the Vedic times, did not need any outer laws and rules of conduct because individuals found their path and acted from the inner being which was open to the Truth. But slowly, as this inner awareness became less immediate, an authority which could mould society according to the right way (Dharma) became more and more necessary. Dharma is the right path that helps the human being realise and manifest the Divine in life. Even if the destination is the same, each individual chooses its path according to its differing needs and circumstances, and the support it needs also differs accordingly. Dharma provides precisely that support. So, broadly, we can say that whatever helps an individual connect to its inner purpose is Dharma and whatever causes an obstruction is Adharma (not Dharma). That is why, even though Dharma is structured and meticulously precise, in actual practice, it took shape and varied according to Desha-Kala and Patra (place-time-person). So in its ideal stage, Dharma, and under it, government and the justice system were ever living. But such a living organization based on place-time-person, needed an authority that was energized by the Truth and organized the Dharmas accordingly. That authority was the Rishi who alone could establish the Dharmas or modify them when needed. Accordingly, the king was constantly under the yoke of the Dharma and complete loyalty, obedience and commitment to the Rishi and Shastra were demanded of him. The detailed description of a king’s qualities, duties, dharmas, etc. found in the Puranas and other Indian scriptures makes it clear that the extent to which he was bound by the yoke of Dharma left few opportunities for personal satisfactions at the cost of the well-being of the people. Indeed, even governance and positions of power etc. that, normally, are the playground for human tendencies of inflated egoism, possessiveness and self-indulgent hedonism, were regulated so strictly by Dharma that they verily became an important means of self-discovery and self-realisation. Impelled by such a goal, it is natural that the real character of the system would be different from the one centred on the satisfaction of the surface nature.‡

C. The Sense in Which the Earlier Mind of India Understood the Problem of Unification

“..spiritual unity is a large and flexible thing and does not insist like the political and external on centralisation and uniformity; rather it lives diffused in the system and permits readily a great diversity and freedom of life. Here we touch on the secret of the difficulty in the problem of unifying ancient India. It could not be done by the ordinary means of a centralised uniform imperial State crushing out all that made for free divergence, local autonomies, established communal liberties, and each time that an attempt was made in this direction, it has failed after however long a term of apparent success, and we might even say that the guardians of India’s destiny wisely compelled it to fail that her inner spirit might not perish and her soul barter for an engine of temporary security the deep sources of its life. The ancient mind of India had the intuition of its need; its idea of empire was a uniting rule that respected every existing regional and communal liberty, that unnecessarily crushed out no living autonomy, that effected a synthesis of her life and not a mechanical oneness. Afterwards the conditions under which such a solution might securely have evolved and found its true means and form and basis, disappeared and there was instead an attempt to establish a single administrative empire. That endeavour, dictated by the pressure of an immediate and external necessity, failed to achieve a complete success in spite of its greatness and splendour. It could not do so because it followed a trend that was not eventually compatible with the true turn of the Indian spirit. It has been seen that the underlying principle of the Indian politico-social system was a synthesis of communal autonomies, the autonomy of the village, of the town and capital city, of the caste, guild, family, kula, religious community, regional unit. The state or kingdom or confederated republic was a means of holding together and synthetising in a free and living organic system these autonomies. The imperial problem was to synthetise again these states, peoples, nations, effecting their unity but respecting their autonomy, into a larger free and living organism. A system had to be found that would maintain peace and oneness among its members, secure safety against external attack and totalise the free play and evolution, in its unity and diversity...”9

“This was the sense in which the earlier mind of India understood the problem. The administrative empire of later times accepted it only partially, but its trend was, very slowly and almost subconsciously, what the centralising tendency must always be, if not actively to destroy, still to wear down and weaken the vigour of the subordinated autonomies. The consequence was that whenever the central authority was weak, the persistent principle of regional autonomy essential to the life of India reasserted itself to the detriment of the artificial unity established...”10

D. The Ancient Rishis’ Perception of the Solution of the Problem: the Ideal of the Chakravarti

“The failure to achieve Indian unity of which the invasions and the final subjection to the foreigner were the consequence, arose therefore at once from the magnitude and from the peculiarity of the task, because the easy method of a centralised empire could not truly succeed in India, while yet it seemed the only device possible and was attempted again and again with a partial success that seemed for the time and a long time to justify it, but always with an eventual failure. I have suggested that the early mind of India better understood the essential character of the problem. The Vedic Rishis and their successors made it their chief work to found a spiritual basis of Indian life and to effect the spiritual and cultural unity of the many races and peoples of the peninsula. But they were not blind to the necessity of a political unification. Observing the constant tendency of the clan life of the Aryan peoples to consolidate under confederacies and hegemonies of varying proportions, vairājya, sāmrājya, they saw that to follow this line to its full conclusion was the right way and evolved therefore the ideal of the Chakravarti, a uniting imperial rule, uniting without destroying the autonomy of India’s many kingdoms and peoples, from sea to sea. This ideal they supported, like everything else in Indian life, with a spiritual and religious sanction, set up as its outward symbol the Aswamedha and Rajasuya sacrifices, and made it the dharma of a powerful King, his royal and religious duty, to attempt the fulfilment of the ideal. He was not allowed by the Dharma to destroy the liberties of the peoples who came under his sway nor to dethrone or annihilate their royal houses or replace their archons by his officials and governors. His function was to establish a suzerain power possessed of sufficient military strength to preserve internal peace and to combine at need the full forces of the country. And to this elementary function came to be added the ideal of the fulfilment and maintenance under a strong uniting hand of the Indian dharma, the right functioning of the spiritual, religious, ethical and social culture of India.

The full flowering of the ideal is seen in the great epics. The Mahabharata is the record of a legendary or, it may be, a historic attempt to establish such an empire, a dharmarājya or kingdom of the Dharma. There the ideal is pictured as so imperative and widely acknowledged that even the turbulent Shishupala is represented as motiving his submission and attendance at the Rajasuya sacrifice on the ground that Yudhisthira was carrying out an action demanded by the Dharma. And in the Ramayana we have an idealised picture of such a Dharmarajya, a settled universal empire. Here too it is not an autocratic despotism but a universal monarchy supported by a free assembly of the city and provinces and of all the classes that is held up as the ideal, an enlargement of the monarchical state synthetising the communal autonomies of the Indian system and maintaining the law and constitution of the Dharma. The ideal of conquest held up is not a destructive and predatory invasion annihilating the organic freedom and the political and social institutions and exploiting the economic resources of the conquered peoples, but a sacrificial progression bringing with it a trial of military strength of which the result was easily accepted because defeat entailed neither humiliation nor servitude and suffering but merely a strengthening adhesion to a suzerain power concerned only with establishing the visible unity of the nation and the Dharma. The ideal of the ancient Rishis is clear and their purpose: it is evident that they saw the military and political utility and necessity of a unification of the divided and warring peoples of the land, but they saw also that it ought not to be secured at the expense of the free life of the regional peoples or of the communal liberties and not therefore by a centralised monarchy or a rigidly unitarian imperial State.”11

“There is no historical evidence that this ideal was ever successfully carried into execution, although the epic tradition speaks of several such empires preceding the Dharmarajya of Yudhisthira. At the time of Buddha and later when Chandragupta and Chanakya were building the first historic Indian empire, the country was still covered with free kingdoms and republics and there was no united empire to meet the great raid of Alexander. It is evident that if any hegemony had previously existed, it had failed to discover a means or system of enduring permanence. This might however have evolved if time had been given, but a serious change had meanwhile taken place which made it urgently necessary to find an immediate solution. The historic weakness of the Indian peninsula has always been until modern times its vulnerability through the north-western passes. This weakness did not exist so long as ancient India extended northward far beyond the Indus and the powerful kingdoms of Gandhara and Vahlika presented a firm bulwark against foreign invasion. But they had now gone down before the organised Persian empire and from this time forward the trans-Indus countries, ceasing to be part of India, ceased also to be its protection and became instead the secure base for every successive invader. The inroad of Alexander brought home the magnitude of the danger to the political mind of India and from this time we see poets, writers, political thinkers constantly upholding the imperial ideal or thinking out the means of its realisation. The immediate practical result was the rise of the empire founded with remarkable swiftness by the statesmanship of Chanakya and constantly maintained or restored through eight or nine centuries[2], in spite of periods of weakness and incipient disintegration, successively by the Maurya, Sunga, Kanwa, Andhra and Gupta dynasties. The history of this empire, its remarkable organisation, administration, public works, opulence, magnificent culture and the vigour, the brilliance, the splendid fruitfulness of the life of the peninsula under its shelter emerges only from scattered insufficient records, but even so it ranks among the greatest constructed and maintained by the genius of the earth’s great peoples. India has no reason, from this point of view, to be anything but proud of her ancient achievement in empire-building or to submit to the hasty verdict that denies to her antique civilisation a strong practical genius or high political virtue.”12

‡ The mainstay of the accusations of incompetence against Indian polity has been the fact that India could not protect herself from foreign invasions and had to endure a thousand years of continuous foreign invasions, gruesome brutalities and even foreign rule. The barbarous atrocities committed against the Indians would certainly disturb any sympathiser and in such a case it is natural for doubts to arise that, though the nation might have been very spiritually advanced, it failed completely in establishing any kind of defensive and political oneness. But we will never be able to resolve this meaningfully if we try to assess it by superficial modern standards. We will have to delve deep into the core of Indian culture to consider the significant facts – because nothing in Indian culture can be understood if one bases oneself on a surface standpoint and outer appearances.

When we talk of India’s political consolidation in the past, it important that we appreciate her geographical vastness because the difficulties in such a political unity cannot be compared to that of a small nation. Indian culture and her Rishis stressed her cultural oneness before her political unity because of the difficulties arising from the political vastness of India and even more for reasons so profound that they are difficult to comprehend for our surface human understanding. To obtain a meaningful and comprehensive assessment of the problem, we have to begin by diving into the depths of Indian culture to enter into its spirit and empathise with how this culture saw this problem, then can we accurately gauge how this culture approached its resolution.

Firstly, we have to keep in mind that this huge geographical entity was home to thousands of societies, classes, races etc. each of which had its own cultural identity with ways of living, worship etc. As we have been discussing from the beginning, the spirit of Indian culture has been the integral Vedic spirit in which the various parts of a human being, each and every aspect of the life, thought and works of the individual and collectivity were connected to the Divine and were given the complete freedom to express the truth of the Divine inherent within them and so, the culture accepted every possible means of approaching the Divine. That is why along with a cultural diversity, there was an ever increasing mass of different spiritual paths, beliefs, sects, doctrines, creeds, philosophies, yogas, Darshanas and a variety of religions. It was only the intuitive intelligence of the Rishis that recognized this vitality of the culture and that, imposing some form of external political unity at the cost of this infinite cultural and spiritual diversity, would risk damaging the spirit of this culture irreparably. Indeed, political unity can be established firmly only on the basis of a living cultural oneness, otherwise, in the absence of such a oneness, a mechanical political unity will eventually disintegrate. It is a fundamental truth that, an effective unity can only be established when every unit within it has the full liberty to move towards its inner reality because only when it is integrated and assimilated in its inner consciousness can it be capable of a genuine outward harmony. Accordingly, it was a conscious and considered decision of the Rishis to reject any political unity achieved by ‘the ordinary means of a centralised uniform imperial State crushing out all that made for free divergence, local autonomies, established communal liberties.’ The first accusation against this willed decision of preserving this cultural and spiritual oneness, is that, in the absence of a powerful united empire India had to suffer debilitating foreign invasions. However, we find many historical examples of militarily powerful political empires which soon disappeared in the face of a lack of any inner oneness. It would also be misleading to say that the insistence of Indian culture on inner unity based on spirituality and culture first was destructive for it. If we step out of our prejudices and biases and looker deeper into history, we will see that the repeated barbaric attempts by aggressors, for centuries, to destroy the physical body and spirit of this culture and root it out, remained futile to the end. It is also noteworthy that careful research is now providing a completely different picture from the one presented of the pitiful and destitute condition of Indian culture. It reveals the extraordinary political astuteness and capability of the culture and this is what Sri Aurobindo is indicating here.

All these discussions have made it indubitably clear that the exceptional proficiency displayed by Indian culture when dealing with the spirit and mind extended even to the most external aspects of life such as politics and governance, which are normally considered the playground of the blind egoistic and hedonistic tendencies of the life-nature with conflict, strife and possessiveness dominating the field and spiritual light finding it impossible to enter. But Indian culture took even these in hand, and there can hardly be a comparable example of the adeptness it employed in handling these and the superlative gains it made in these fields.

If we look at world-history, we find that governments have been based on various systems and philosophies like democracy, monarchy, socialism, communism among others, but after a certain period, longer or shorter, they have proven to be ineffective and inadequate because the individual and collective human spirit cannot be limited by any single dimensional system. Indian culture understood this from the beginning and as an example of its profound understanding we find that, though externally the government was monarchical it contained elements that incorporated within it the essentials of democracy and all other possible systems of governance. It knew that each system has a truth at its centre and only by truly synthesising these truths can a system be flexible enough to work according to the Spirit. That is why it did not bind itself to any one system, created an original form, which was living and effective and despite resembling in some outward aspects the modern systems, was uniquely Indian. The following example given by Sri Aurobindo will clarify the point:

“Sri Aurobindo : The old Indian system grew out of life, it had room for everything and every interest. There were monarchy, aristocracy, democracy. Every interest was represented in the government, while the Western system grew out of the mind. In Europe they are led by reason and want to make everything cut and dry without any chance of freedom or variation. If it is democracy, then democracy only and no room for anything else. They cannot be plastic.

India is now trying to imitate the West. Parliamentary government is not suited to India. But we always take up what the West has thrown off.” (Evening Talks with Sri Aurobindo, Recorded by A. B. Purani 2007, pp. 584-585)

“Disciple: It seems political ideas and ideals are not worth fighting for. Thousands fought for democracy, and now they are in a hurry to give it up! Nothing seems to be permanent in the political field.

Sri Aurobindo: Quite so. All human values are half values – they are relative. They have no permanence or durability about them.

Disciple: Perhaps if men became more mentalised, they would understand things better.

Sri Aurobindo: By being mentalised? No! The difficulty is that men don’t follow the principles of life.

Disciple: How is that?

Sri Aurobindo: Life compromises between different elements, but mind, when acting on its own, does not compromise. Mind takes up one thing and makes it absolute, considers it as apart from and opposed to all other things.

Hegel boasted that in Europe they had succeeded in separating reason from life, and you see their philosophy – it has nothing to do with life; it is all mental gymnastics, it does not form part of life. While in India, philosophy has always been a part of life; it has an aim to realise everything.

So also in the political philosophy of Europe you find that if they accept democracy, it is only democracy – all the rest is opposed to it. If monarchy, then it is only monarchy.

That is what happened in Greece. They fought for democracy, aristocracy and monarchy, and in the end they were conquered by the Romans.

Disciple: Then what is the truth in all these attempts at political organisation?

Sri Aurobindo: If you want to arrive at something true and lasting, you have to look at life and learn from it, that is to say, you must learn the nature of the oppositions and contradictions and then reconcile them.

As regards government, life shows that there is a truth in monarchy – whether hereditary or elective, there is a man at the top who governs. Life also shows that there is a truth in aristocracy, whether it is of strong men, or rich men, or intellectuals. The current fiction is that it is the majority that rules, but the fact is that it is the minority, the aristocracy.

Life also shows that the rule of the king or the aristocracy should be with the consent, silent or vocal, of the people.

In ancient India, they recognised the truth of these things. That is why India has lasted through millenniums – and China also.” (Evening Talks with Sri Aurobindo, Recorded by A. B. Purani 2007 : 675-76)

We find an apposite example of how the democratic spirit was a crucial element in government in the episode of the Ramayana when Dasharatha seeks the counsel and permission of the people before crowning Sri Rama. We find a similar instance in the Mahabharata when Dhritarashtra wants to spend the last years of his life in contemplation in the forest, and is adamant despite the objections of his family, but very humbly asks the people for their permission. This democratic element was not only a façade but generally the operative element. Indian culture knew that real democracy cannot and should not depend on numbers, but ideally, the voice of any person coming from the true authority would be more important than any majority. Can a surgeon, or a pilot or member of any crucial or sensitive profession be selected, not on the basis of capability, but on the basis of a majority vote? There are all kinds of catastrophic consequences if we insist on the external forms at the expense of the essential truth, as the working experiments of the various systems around the world make obvious to any thinking person. It should also be obvious that the more humankind has tried to solve the problems of our various systems of life (political, social, etc.) through mere external arrangements, systems, ‘isms’ etc. the more it has failed. It seems however, that instead of learning from history, we tend to repeat the same mistakes again and again.

Indian culture clearly understood this fundamental truth from the beginning, which is why it tried to organize its various systems and institutions in alignment with the inner law of the being. By taking this deeper approach, we can begin to enter into the mysteries of this culture. It is not as if Indian culture was unaware of the necessity of political unification. But it did not wish to facilitate this unification by any artificial means, the result of which would have meant disrupting the self-rule and independence of kingdoms, tribes, and other units and institutions or, at least, suppressing the uniqueness of their native cultural and life specialties, as that would have been counter productive and against the spirit of the Indian Vedic Culture. That is why a power that could unite the nation without damaging the infinite diversity within it, was needed. The duties and ideals for such a power have, previously, been elaborated comprehensibly in the words of Sri Aurobindo. If we read history in the light of this exposition, the whole scenario changes. Along with his other duties, a king was expected to expand his kingdom and become an emperor. But he could expand his kingdom only according to Dharma (righteously), not in a barbaric or cruel manner. It is for this reason that if we study the wars in ancient Indian history, we find that the ordinary life of the people remained largely unaffected by them because primarily, wars were only fought between armies and, the vanquished ruler – and if he was killed in battle, his heirs or minister or some other capable person – was put back on the throne after acknowledging the suzerainty of the victor. In certain cases, if the king acknowledged the suzerainty of the attacking emperor, there was no battle and he could continue his rule as before. The atrocities of war were reduced to the minimum in the Indian scenario, as we learn from a study of our long history, because war was not fought mostly to loot or plunder a country as was done by the foreign invaders and looters. If one glances at our history with a clear view it is indubitably demonstrated that this culture established such standards in polity too that, by effecting them, it could achieve superlatively by mitigating, considerably, the evil effects of war and mutual strife.

If political incompetence is presumed by the fact that the borders could not be defended against foreign invasions because of a lack of political unification, then Sri Aurobindo has already explained that this was the result not of any kind of incompetence, but the considered choice of the custodians of this culture when they risked everything to keep the soul of the nation intact. We can get a comprehensive perspective if the background to this choice made by the Rishis is studied in the light of Sri Aurobindo. If we look behind the surface of the physical evolution, we find that while externally Nature creates more and more complex forms, a hidden inner evolution is also happening. It is as if the Spirit, through this process, is descending into successively lower and more external parts of humankind to try to invigorate and transform these parts so as to express itself in them. This can eventually lead to the establishment of the Divine Life in this material world – the goal of the terrestrial evolution. But when the light of the Spirit reaches the level of the physical nature and Matter, it has to face a tremendous resistance and it can no longer work as freely as it does on its own plane and to a large extent, on the higher planes. We can say that it is more or less buried under the rigidity of matter. In this condition, the egoistic forces grow more prominent and the organization of harmony becomes more difficult. The attempt to create an external unification without the basis of a true inner oneness is doomed to fail and is against the wisdom of a culture like the Indian, which lives more in its depths than the surfaces. Indeed, as Sri Aurobindo and the Mother have said, India is a divinely chosen country which possesses a spiritual truth, an eternal light and has been given the mission of spreading it throughout the world. It is, therefore her Divine work to lead and direct the whole of mankind towards the true goal. That is why India does not live for itself but for all mankind. It is impossible for us to fully appreciate the faithfulness to the Divine work displayed by the wisdom of this culture, not only for its own survival but for that of the whole of humankind, especially when it eschewed political unification to preserve its spiritual and cultural oneness. For the true existence of a culture is its cultural and spiritual originality without which it is dead in the true sense even if some external signs remain. So if we judge its choice even on the basis of the results, we see that where other cultures live only in the pages of history, Indian culture is not only alive but with the advent of Sri Aurobindo has been able to articulate the voice of her spirit and breathe into it a new energy so that it gets moving consciously once more, towards its chosen goal. ‡

[2]	‡ This period is actually about two millenniums. In Indian history, the invasion by Alexander has been placed in the time of Chandragupta Maurya instead of the time of Chandra Gupta, and consequently a long period of Indian history has been omitted by western historians and their apologist Indians. These people place the Mahabharata a mere thousand years before Christ. ‡

V. The Future of India

‡ After discussing the greatness of the Indian political system, the burning question remains, if prior to foreign invasions and domination the political system was so great then, even so many decades after Independence, why is the situation so distressingly grim and what hope do we have for the future? To understand the background to the question we need to refer to some recent history. When the British fully took over India, they set upon establishing an intermediary race of Indians whom they could entrust with their work at middle and lower levels of government and administration. In the words of Macaulay: “We must at present do our best to form a class, who may be interpreters between us and the millions we govern, a class of persons, Indians in blood and colour, but English in taste, in opinions, in morals and in intellects.” (Francois Gautier, India’s Self-Denial, page 43)

Most of our pre-independence leaders belonged to this class and at independence not only the British education system, but the whole of their constitutional, judicial, legal and administrative system was blindly adopted and remains in effect even today virtually unchanged. Our post-independence leaders too, having been educated and groomed under this system, show little or no true appreciation or even understanding of the genius of India – its great culture, its Sanatana – because eternally true – Dharma and its soul. Our leaders of the time believed that with the help of Science, Socialism and Economic Planning and the Indian people’s own government – after seven centuries of most painful subjection to foreign rule – they will be able to take the country to an ideal state superior to anything that might have been achieved in the ancient past. The initial concentration of the economic planning was on the construction of big multipurpose hydroelectric power projects, steel plants, a network of roads, etc. The big steel plants and huge hydroelectric power projects like Bhakhara-Nangal dam were declared to be the true and fitting places of worship for all forward looking spirits in the new India. As minds and hearts were completely shaped by western ways of thinking, Indian culture, being considered parochial, was completely ignored while a slavish mentality looking to the West for everything, brought us to our present sorry plight. It is a fundamental truth that it is never fruitful for an individual to attempt to bypass one’s own calling in order to live according to some other. Similarly, how can we expect positive results if this nation ignores its spiritual culture, its Sanatana Dharma, and tries to mould itself in alien forms.

In present times, India too has sunk into the morass of utilitarianism and in a worst possible way. As a nation, as a society, she seems to have forgotten her deeper well-springs of energy and has become lost in the chaos of conflicting narrow self-interests spiraling her into greater depths of depravation of every kind. A nationalistic pride in the country and her achievements may be the lever to pull her out of this degradation and set her on the road to her true destiny – the intelligent will to live for the spirit not only individually but also collectively. Sri Aurobindo writes at one place, “With us today Nationalism is our immediate practical faith and gospel not because it is the highest possible synthesis, but because it must be realised in life if we are to have the chance of realising the others. We must live as a nation before we can live in humanity. It is for this reason that Nationalist thinkers have always urged the necessity of realising our separateness from other nations and living to ourselves for the present, not in order to shut out humanity, but that we may get that individual strength, unity and wholeness which will help us to live as a nation for humanity. A man must be strong and free in himself before he can live usefully for others, so must a nation.” (CWSA 8, 84-85)

However, we must not forget that, though nationalism may be the need of the hour, it is but one state of the highest spirit and has to be transcended to achieve the goal towards which the Soul of India has been striving – the greater and greater revelation and manifestation of the Spirit in terrestrial nature. Because, “There are deeper issues for India herself, since by following certain tempting directions she may conceivably become a nation like many others evolving an opulent industry and commerce, a powerful organisation of social and political life, an immense military strength, practising power-politics with a high degree of success, guarding and extending zealously her gains and her interests, dominating even a large part of the world, but in this apparently magnificent progression forfeiting its Swadharma, losing its soul. Then ancient India and her spirit might disappear altogether and we would have only one more nation like the others and that would be a real gain neither to the world nor to us... It would be a tragic irony of fate if India were to throw away her spiritual heritage at the very moment when in the rest of the world there is more and more a turning towards her for spiritual help and a saving Light. This must not and will surely not happen; but it cannot be said that the danger is not there.” (CWSA 36, 503-04)

To avoid the dangers elaborated by Sri Aurobindo above, the Indian renaissance has three tasks before it. In the words of Sri Aurobindo, “The recovery of the old spiritual knowledge and experience in all its splendour, depth and fullness is its first, most essential work; the flowing of this spirituality into new forms of philosophy, literature, art, science and critical knowledge is the second; an original dealing with modern problems in the light of the Indian spirit and the endeavour to formulate a greater synthesis of a spiritualised society is the third and most difficult. Its success on these three lines will be the measure of its help to the future of humanity.” (CWSA 20: 15)

Among the above, the first has been largely completed by Sri Ramakrishna-Vivekananda and Sri Aurobindo. The second has also been partially accomplished but a lot has still to be done. It seems that there has not even been a thought about the third, because it has not even been clearly articulated by anyone except Sri Aurobindo. That is why at the root of all our problems is the fact that light of the Soul of India has been so buried under the dust of the glitz of western culture that, instead of trying to find a solution to the dire difficulties we face in the sun that is the Soul of India, we turn towards the flicker of western materialism. We conclude this book with the inspiring words of Swami Vivekananda.

“There are two great obstacles on our path in India, the Scylla of old orthodoxy and the Charybdis of modern European civilisation. Of these two, I vote for the old orthodoxy, and not for the Europeanised system; for the old orthodox man may be ignorant, he may be crude, but he is a man, he has a faith, he has strength, he stands on his own feet; while the Europeanised man has no backbone, he is a mass of heterogeneous ideas picked up at random from every source — and these ideas are unassimilated, undigested, unharmonised. He does not stand on his own feet, and his head is turning round and round. Where is the motive power of his work? — in a few patronizing pats from the English people. His schemes of reforms, his vehement vituperations against the evils of certain social customs, have, as the mainspring, some European patronage. Why are some of our customs called evils? Because the Europeans say so. That is about the reason he gives. I would not submit to that. Stand and die in your own strength, if there is any sin in the world, it is weakness; avoid all weakness, for weakness is sin, weakness is death. These unbalanced creatures are not yet formed into distinct personalities; what are we to call them — men, women, or animals? While those old orthodox people were staunch and were men.…

The secret of a true Hindu’s character lies in the subordination of his knowledge of European sciences and learning, of his wealth, position, and name, to that one principal theme which is inborn in every Hindu child — the spirituality and purity of the race. Therefore between these two, the case of the orthodox man who has the whole of that life-spring of the race, spirituality, and the other man whose hands are full of Western imitation jewels but has no hold on the life-giving principle, spirituality — of these, I do not doubt that every one here will agree that we should choose the first, the orthodox, because there is some hope in him — he has the national theme, something to hold to; so he will live, but the other will die. Just as in the case of individuals, if the principle of life is undisturbed, if the principal function of that individual life is present, any injuries received as regards other functions are not serious, do not kill the individual, so, as long as this principal function of our life is not disturbed, nothing can destroy our nation. But mark you, if you give up that spirituality, leaving it aside to go after the materialising civilisation of the West, the result will be that in three generations you will be an extinct race; because the backbone of the nation will be broken, the foundation upon which the national edifice has been built will be undermined, and the result will be annihilation all round.” (CWSV 3: 151-53)

“…the way out is that first and foremost we must keep a firm hold on spirituality — that inestimable gift handed down to us by our ancient forefathers. Did you ever hear of a country where the greatest kings tried to trace their descent not to kings, not to robber-barons living in old castles who plundered poor travellers, but to semi-naked sages who lived in the forest? Did you ever hear of such a land? This is the land. In other countries great priests try to trace their descent to some king, but here the greatest kings would trace their descent to some ancient priest. Therefore, whether you believe in spirituality or not, for the sake of the national life, you have to get a hold on spirituality and keep to it. Then stretch the other hand out and gain all you can from other races, but everything must be subordinated to that one ideal of life; and out of that a wonderful, glorious, future India will come — I am sure it is coming — a greater India than ever was. Sages will spring up greater than all the ancient sages; and your ancestors will not only be satisfied, but I am sure, they will be proud from their positions in other worlds to look down upon their descendants, so glorious, and so great.

Let us all work hard, my brethren; this is no time for sleep. On our work depends the coming of the India of the future. She is there ready waiting. She is only sleeping. Arise and awake and see her seated here on her eternal throne, rejuvenated, more glorious than she ever was — this motherland of ours. The idea of God was nowhere else ever so fully developed as in this motherland of ours, for the same idea of God never existed anywhere else. Perhaps you are astonished at my assertion; but show me any idea of God from any other scripture equal to ours; they have only clan-Gods, the God of the Jews, the God of the Arabs, and of such and such a race, and their God is fighting the Gods of the other races. But the idea of that beneficent, most merciful God, our father, our mother, our friend, the friend of our friends, the soul of our souls, is here and here alone. And may He who is the Shiva of the Shaivites, the Vishnu of the Vaishnavites, the Karma of the Karmis, the Buddha of the Buddhists, the Jina of the Jains, the Jehovah of the Christians and the Jews, the Allah of the Mohammedans, the Lord of every sect, the Brahman of the Vedantists, He the all-pervading, whose glory has been known only in this land — may He bless us, may He help us, may He give strength unto us, energy unto us, to carry this idea into practice. May that which we have listened to and studied become food to us, may it become strength in us, may it become energy in us to help each other; may we, the teacher and the taught, not be jealous of each other! Peace, peace, peace, in the name of Hari!” (CWSV 3: 153-54)

“Let them talk of India’s regeneration as they like. Let me tell you as one who has been working — at least trying to work — all his life, that there is no regeneration for India until you be spiritual. Not only so, but upon it depends the welfare of the whole world. For I must tell you frankly that the very foundations of Western civilisation have been shaken to their base. The mightiest buildings, if built upon the loose sand foundations of materialism, must come to grief one day, must totter to their destruction some day. The history of the world is our witness. Nation after nation has arisen and based its greatness upon materialism, declaring man was all matter. Ay, in Western language, a man gives up the ghost, but in our language a man gives up his body. The Western man is a body first, and then he has a soul; with us a man is a soul and spirit, and he has a body. Therein lies a world of difference. All such civilisations, therefore, as have been based upon such sand foundations as material comfort and all that, have disappeared one after another, after short lives, from the face of the world; but the civilisation of India and the other nations that have stood at India’s feet to listen and learn, namely, Japan and China, live even to the present day, and there are signs even of revival among them. Their lives are like that of the Phoenix, a thousand times destroyed, but ready to spring up again more glorious. But a materialistic civilisation once dashed down, never can come up again; that building once thrown down is broken into pieces once for all. Therefore have patience and wait, the future is in store for us.

Do not be in a hurry, do not go out to imitate anybody else. This is another great lesson we have to remember; imitation is not civilisation. I may deck myself out in a Raja’s dress, but will that make me a Raja? An ass in a lion’s skin never makes a lion. Imitation, cowardly imitation, never makes for progress. It is verily the sign of awful degradation in a man. Ay, when a man has begun to hate himself, then the last blow has come. When a man has begun to be ashamed of his ancestors, the end has come. Here am I, one of the least of the Hindu race, yet proud of my race, proud of my ancestors. I am proud to call myself a Hindu, I am proud that I am one of your unworthy servants. I am proud that I am a countryman of yours, you the descendants of the sages, you the descendants of the most glorious Rishis the world ever saw. Therefore have faith in yourselves, be proud of your ancestors, instead of being ashamed of them. And do not imitate, do not imitate! Whenever you are under the thumb of others, you lose your own independence. If you are working, even in spiritual things, at the dictation of others, slowly you lose all faculty, even of thought. Bring out through your own exertions what you have, but do not imitate, yet take what is good from others. We have to learn from others. You put the seed in the ground, and give it plenty of earth, and air, and water to feed upon; when the seed grows into the plant and into a gigantic tree, does it become the earth, does it become the air, or does it become the water? It becomes the mighty plant, the mighty tree, after its own nature, having absorbed everything that was given to it. Let that be your position. We have indeed many things to learn from others, yea, that man who refuses to learn is already dead.” (CWSV 3: 380-81) ‡

References:

1. 	CWSA 7: 943

2. 	CWSA 20: 384-87

3. 	CWSA 20: 391-95

4. 	CWSA 20: 425-26

5. 	CWSA 20: 426-27

6. 	CWSA 20: 427-28

7. 	CWSA 20: 429-30

8. 	CWSA 20: 430-31

9. 	CWSA 20: 431-32

10.	CWSA 20: 432-33

11. CWSA 20: 434-36

12. CWSA 20: 436-37

13. CWSA 20: 441-42

CWM: Collected Works of the Mother, Sri Aurobindo Ashram Trust 1978, Puducherry, Second Edition 2004

CWSA: Complete Works of Sri Aurobindo, Sri Aurobindo Ashram Trust, Puducherry

CWSV: Complete Works of Swami Vivekananda, Mayavati Memorial Edition, Published by Advaita Ashram, Kolkata.